<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The healing attempt being a representation of the government of the Church of England, according to the judgment of her bishops unto the end of Q. Elizabeths reign, humbly tendred to the consideration of the thirty commissionated for a consult about ecclesiastical affairs in order to a comprehension, and published in hopes of such a moderation of episcopacy, that the power be kept within the line of our first reformers, and the excercise of it reduced to the model of Arch-Bishop Usher.</title>
            <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 215 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45129</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3679</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20326</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12224506</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12224506</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56457</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45129)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56457)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 919:32)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The healing attempt being a representation of the government of the Church of England, according to the judgment of her bishops unto the end of Q. Elizabeths reign, humbly tendred to the consideration of the thirty commissionated for a consult about ecclesiastical affairs in order to a comprehension, and published in hopes of such a moderation of episcopacy, that the power be kept within the line of our first reformers, and the excercise of it reduced to the model of Arch-Bishop Usher.</title>
                  <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 84 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Epistle signed: J.H.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to John Humfrey.  Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. 84.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56457:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56457:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Healing Attempt: Being a Repreſentation OF THE GOVERNMENT OF THE Church of England, According to the Judgment of her Biſhops unto the End of Q. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Reign.</p>
            <p>Humbly Tendred To the Conſideration of the Thirty Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated for a Conſult about <hi>ECCLESIASTICAL AFFAIRS</hi> in Order to a <hi>Comprehenſion;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Publiſhed, In hopes of ſuch a Moderation of Epiſcopacy, that the <hi>Power</hi> be kept within the Line of our <hi>Firſt Reformers:</hi> and the <hi>Exerciſe</hi> of it reduced to the Model of <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Biſhop</hi> USHER.</p>
            <p>Mediocria firma.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Parkhurſt,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> near <hi>Mercers-Chappel,</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:56457:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56457:2"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the Commiſſioners.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Most Reverend, Right Reverend and Reverend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Bleſs you all in the Name of the Lord, and Bleſſed be your Meeting this Day, and this Appointment for you to Sit about ſo Bleſſed a reconciling Work. I have but this ſhort Grace to ſay, <hi>Bleſſed are the Peacemakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When ſuch a <hi>Choice</hi> of Perſons is Congregated, and their Buſineſs <hi>Accommodation,</hi> the Tidings hereof to the poor <hi>Outed Shepherds</hi> ſhould, methinks, be ſo <hi>affecting,</hi> as if the <hi>Angels</hi> were again upon the Wing, and ſinging <hi>over</hi> that Hymn, <hi>Glory be to God in the higheſt, in Earth Peace, and good will towards Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alas! How many Years have paſſed ſince the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, wherein your Nonconformiſt Brethren have been a Loading, and their Burthen encreaſing, and none of you that were willing, were able to eaſe them, when by the Artifice of the Papiſts, and the Higher Powers influenced by them, you were forced to <hi>bear</hi> the <hi>blame</hi> of thoſe things which your Souls did <hi>abhor:</hi> And now is the time come when God hath ſent us ſuch a <hi>Nurſing Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> and <hi>Nurſing Mother</hi> to his Church, as hath <hi>called you to the liberty</hi> of ſhewing <hi>of what manner of ſpirit</hi> indeed <hi>you are.</hi> Bleſſed be his Name for it, and the ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es we have on that account. <hi>This is the day which the Lord hath made, we will be glad, and rejoyce in it.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:56457:3"/>
            <p>I know indeed how hard of belief the moſt of our Brethren generally are that any good ſhould be done for us by a <hi>Convocation</hi> or this <hi>Meeting. It is impoſſible</hi> (they are readier to ſay) <hi>that thoſe—But</hi> Reverendly <hi>beloved, I am perſwaded better things of you, and things that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company Salvation, though</hi> they <hi>thus ſpeak.</hi> I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that even this will ſtimulate you to a greater ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſs to do them the more good (for ſuch is Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity), and that I ſhall not need to ſay any thing (not any more than in the Title) to put you on this grateful task, <hi>The ſame alſo which ye are forward to do:</hi> I have leſs need to be impertinent in offering <hi>Arguments</hi> to ſuch <hi>Wits,</hi> which were to bring <hi>Water</hi> to the <hi>Spring:</hi> but this one thing I have need to do, which is, to beg of you that you will Pardon what is done, if in any thing the Author ſeems to <hi>preſume,</hi> or to be more <hi>ſlender</hi> than he ought, for want of more <hi>time</hi> and <hi>ſearch,</hi> or does in any regard <hi>offend.</hi> I will alſo beg of you more <hi>Two</hi> things; the <hi>One</hi> is, To take heed how you make more conditions neceſſary to us for Communion with you, than Chriſt requires of you for Communion with him: The <hi>Other</hi> is, That you do not <hi>Tantalize</hi> your Brethren, or <hi>Procra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate</hi> that Kindneſs (whatſoever it is) which you intend towards thoſe who are capable to receive it; <hi>For we muſt needs die, and are as water ſpilt upon the ground, which cannot be gathered up again: Neither doth God reſpect any perſon, yet doth he deviſe means that his baniſhed be not expelled from him.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A Friend to the Deſign and Subſtance of theſe Papers, <hi>J. H.</hi>
               </signed>
               <date>
                  <hi>Octob.</hi> 3. 1689.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:56457:3"/>
            <head>THE AUTHOR TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THE Greateſt thing in Controverſie amongſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants is, Whether <hi>the Office</hi> of a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> and <hi>Biſhop</hi> be, according to the Holy Scriptures, the <hi>ſame?</hi> and on a Juſt Determination of this Queſtion depends the Peace of our Church.</p>
            <p>To affirm, <hi>That</hi> the Biſhop and Presbyter are of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Orders, <hi>That</hi> the Power of Ordination is the ſole Prerogative of Biſhops, <hi>That</hi> Ordination, only by Presbyters, is void and null, and that the Ordaining 'em again by Biſhops is not <hi>Re-Ordination,</hi> deſtroys the Church State, not only of Diſſenters, but of all other Proteſtants in the World, except of thoſe in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> nulling their Miniſtry, Sacraments, and Diſcipline.</p>
            <p>A Comprehenſion therefore on theſe Terms is none at all; It's only an offer to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nite with Diſſenters on their
<pb facs="tcp:56457:4"/>doing what is to them Impoſſible; They cannot Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce their Ordination, nor Conſent to the Deſtroying their own, nor the Church State of Reformed Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants Abroad.</p>
            <p>But, leſt the Impoſſibility they lie under be Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted <hi>a</hi> Peeviſh Humour, and Obſtinacy in them, the Sentiments of the <hi>Firſt-Reformers,</hi> in the Days of <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, and Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> are Impartially Propos'd and found to be exactly the ſame with theirs; and, what will, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Matters of Church Government, Heal our Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</p>
            <p>The Author could Deſcend lower than the laſt of <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> but there's no need on't, and he muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that tho' a great many Eminent Writers, Learned Divines of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> aſſerted this Old Reformer's Principle; yet the <hi>Canons</hi> of <hi>James I.</hi> ran another way, and in his Reign the Learned were divided in their Opinions about the Office of Biſhop and Presbyter; and ſo they are at this very time: However, it cannot be denied, that the <hi>Firſt Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers,</hi> adher'd unto by Archbiſhop <hi>Uſher,</hi> held the ſame, which the Diſſenters have all along ſtifly main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd, and have <hi>Antiquity</hi> on their ſide.</p>
            <p>The Learned <hi>Carleton</hi> is Poſitive, that the <hi>Power of Order</hi> by all Writers, that He could ſee, even of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> is underſtood to be Immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from Chriſt, given to all <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Prieſts,</hi> alike by their Conſecration, and that in this there was no Difference between <hi>Papiſt</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant;</hi> whence it follows, that the Diveſting the <hi>Pariſh Presbyter</hi> of the <hi>Paſtoral Office</hi> is but a late Invention.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:56457:4"/>
            <p>Thus much He Aſſerts of that Power of <hi>Order</hi> which he diſtinguiſheth from the Power of <hi>Juriſdiction,</hi> and includes in it the Power of <hi>Ordination.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And although, according to the moſt taking Opinion amongſt thoſe, who ſeem'd to be ſomewhat Zealous for Prelacy, the Power of <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> was peculiarly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated to the Biſhop, yet this Juriſdiction follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Orders, could never be ſo ſeparated from it, but that there ſtill remain ſome Convincing Inſtances of its belonging unto Presbyters.</p>
            <p>In the Caſe of a <hi>Biſhop's Suſpenſion,</hi> it's clear; I will only obſerve what is at this time moſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious.</p>
            <p>On the Suſpenſion of the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> All Eccleſiaſtical and Spiritual Juriſdiction belongs to the <hi>Dean</hi> and <hi>Chapter,</hi> who are but <hi>Presbyters,</hi> as is daily Aſſerted in theſe words. <hi>Nos Johannes <hi>Til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotſon</hi> Sacrae Theologiae Profeſſor,</hi> Decanus <hi>Eccleſiae Cathedralis &amp; Metropoliticae Chriſti Cant'. Et Ejuſdem Eccleſiae</hi> Capitulum, <hi>ad quos <hi>Omnis, &amp; omnimoda Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictio Spiritualis,</hi> &amp; <hi>Eccleſſiaſtica,</hi>
               </hi> quae ad Archiepiſcopum <hi>Cant.</hi> pertinuit, nunc <hi>ratione Suſpenſionis,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcitur pertinere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Condeſcending to ſettle the Power of Orders, and Juriſdiction on Presbyters, as well as Biſhops, according to the Learned Archbiſhop <hi>Uſher's Model,</hi> will as to Matters of Church Government End the Controveſie between the <hi>Moderate Epiſcopal,</hi> and <hi>Presbyterian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to what relates unto <hi>Stinted-Forms</hi> of Prayer, the Judicious Mr. <hi>Clerkſon,</hi> in his Excellent <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of Liturgies,</hi> having ſo Learnedly and fully
<pb facs="tcp:56457:5"/>diſcuſſed it, the Author need do no more than only Commend its Peruſal to the Candid <hi>Reader,</hi> with an Aſſurance, that until it be cleared that Stinted Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgies are Ancienter than that Learned Perſon Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents them to be, we ſhall be freed from a ſtrict Impoſition.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56457:5"/>
            <head>THE Healing Attempt.</head>
            <div type="introduction">
               <head>The Introduction.</head>
               <p>THoſe, who are moſt ſenſible of the late Deliverance from the Dangers we were in of being overturn'd by the <hi>Papists,</hi> muſt be of an Opinion, that the many <hi>Diviſions,</hi> amongſt our ſelves, had too great a hand in bringing on us what was the true Ground of our Danger; <hi>that</hi> we can never be perfectly free from the Fears of a Return, ſo long as our Breaches remain Uncured; and, <hi>that,</hi> it's abſolutely neceſſary, that every one do his Part to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Settlement</hi> of a <hi>laſting <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> amongſt Proteſtants, as the ſtrongeſt Bulwark againſt <hi>Popery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus much I count is very manifeſt to every Conſidering Mind; for, at this time, Proteſtants, of all Perſwaſions, ſeem to be deſirous of it.</p>
               <p>Although there are different Apprehenſions about the <hi>Means</hi> of attaining it, as, whether by an <hi>Indulgence</hi> only; or, whether by Indulgence, and <hi>Comprehenſion,</hi> yet is there no doubt, that I know, about the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> it ſelf; and ſeeing an <hi>Indulgence</hi> is already given, Extending <hi>Liberty of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> even to the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and a <hi>Bill of Comprehenſion</hi> is at this time on the Anvil, I will humbly offer my thoughts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning it.</p>
               <p>That ſuch as are only for an Indulgence will be angry with this Eſſay, is no other than I expect. However, the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:56457:6"/>for a well-Eſtabliſh'd Comprehenſion influencing me more than the Diſpleaſure of any Party of Men on Earth, I am reſolv'd in God's ſtrength, to do the uttermoſt in me lyeth towards the obtaining it.</p>
               <p>It is a Concernment for the Proteſtant Faith, the Salvation of Souls, the Glory of God, that puts me on this work; all which have been Endangered through that want of Powerful Preachers in Pariſh Churches, which hath been the Effect of our Diviſions.</p>
               <p>I bleſs God, there are ſo many Faithful and Laborious Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters in <hi>Publick</hi> Places, and yet, conſidering how few theſe are in compariſon of the Churches wants, I cannot but la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the Deplorable Condition of Thouſands in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who on this occaſion are like Eternally to Periſh, and pray the Lord of the Harveſt to <hi>Open</hi> the Door, that more Labourers may enter in, even men of the moſt Tender Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, who, no doubt. will be the moſt ſucceſsful in their Miniſtry.</p>
               <p>In Queen <hi>Elizabeths,</hi> and <hi>James</hi> the Firſt's days, it ſo fell out, that a ſtrict <hi>Injunction</hi> of <hi>Subſcription</hi> Depriv'd the Church of the Labours of ſeveral Divines eminent for their Learning, Holineſs of Life, and Converſation.</p>
               <p>Conſult the <hi>Complaint,</hi> Preſented to the Right Honourable the Lords of Her Majeſties Council, and their Lordſhips <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer:</hi> The <hi>Copy of a Letter,</hi> written by a Gentleman in the Countrey to a <hi>Londoner, touching the Anſwer to the Archbiſhop's Articles:</hi> The <hi>Lamentable Complaint</hi> of the Commonalty by way of Supplication to the High Court of Parliament for a Learned Miniſtry, and you'l ſee, that for Non-conformity ſome of the moſt Conſcientious, and Painful Preachers were brought to the Barr, Marſhalled with the worſt Malefactors, Indicted, Arraigned, Condemned, New Chriſtned with the odious name of <hi>Puritan,</hi> Depriv'd, to the Advancement of Popery, Debauchery, Atheiſm, and to the great Declenſion of the Power of Godlineſs.</p>
               <p>A Diſgracing thoſe Miniſters, that are ſound in the Faith and Induſtrious in their Work, hath been one of the moſt ſucceſsful Engines the Antichriſtian Party have uſed.</p>
               <p>The firſt Ten years of Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Reign, the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:56457:6"/>kept to our Churches, and if <hi>Saunders,</hi> and ſome others, had not with an unexpected ſucceſs nick-named ſome of the moſt Valiant Oppoſers of <hi>Popery,</hi> and Painful Preachers with the odious names of <hi>Puritan</hi> and <hi>Preciſian,</hi> to the good liking of ſome amongſt our ſelves, they might have ſtill continued their Communion with us.</p>
               <p>This is not the Obſervation of ſome Nonconformiſts only,<note place="margin">The N. C. in their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint to the Queens Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil humbly advertiſe their Lordſhips, that the Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary very cunningly new Chriſtned them with an odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous name of <hi>Puritan,</hi> that whilſt they were occupied in the Defence of their Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency the Adverſary might have greater freedom to go about their hateful Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery. <hi>Part of the Regiſt. pag. 129.</hi>
                  </note> but of the Wiſe and Judicious Sir <hi>Robert Cotton,</hi> who aſſures us, that the Reaſon of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts ſeparating from our Church, and returning to their old Apoſtacy, was not the <hi>Bull</hi> of <hi>Pius Quintus</hi> on the Biſhop of <hi>London</hi>'s Door (as the Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Coke</hi> apprehended) or the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing to hang up Prieſts, but in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with the Idleneſs and Inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency of many Teachers conſpiring with the Peoples cold Zeal, <hi>Saunders</hi> his pinning the name of <hi>Puritan</hi> on ſome of the moſt Learned and couragious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, gave life to that Faction.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>It was not (ſaith this Noble Baronet) the Bull of <hi>Pius Quintus</hi> on the Biſhop of <hi>London</hi>'s Doors,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Poſth. Cotton.</hi> p. 147, 148.</note> or the forbearing to hang up Prieſts, that have wrought this Apoſtacy, but the Idleneſs and Inſufficiency of many Teachers, conſpiring with the Peoples cold Zeal, that hath been the Contriver of this Web. Until the Eleventh year of Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Reign, Recuſants name was ſcarcely known, the Reaſon was, becauſe the Zeal, begotten in the time of the <hi>Marian</hi> Perſecution, was yet freſh in Memory, and the late Perſecutors were ſo amazed with the ſudden alteration of Religion, that they could not chuſe but ſay, <hi>Digitus Dei eſt hîc.</hi> In thoſe days there was an Emulation between the Clergy, and the Laity; and a ſtrife aroſe whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them ſhould ſhew themſelves moſt affectionate to the Goſpel: Miniſters haunted the Houſes of worthieſt Men, where <hi>Jeſuits</hi> now build their Tabernacles, and poor Country Churches were frequented with the beſt of the Shire, the Word of God was precious, Prayer and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:56457:7"/>Preaching went hand in hand together, until Archbiſhop <hi>Grindal</hi>'s <hi>Diſgrace,</hi> and <hi>Hatfield</hi>'s hard conceit of Prophecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, brought the flowing of thoſe good Graces to a ſtill water; the name of a Papiſt ſmelt rank even in their own Noſtrils, and for pure ſhame to be accounted ſuch they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted duly both to our Churches, and Exerciſes; But when they ſaw their great <hi>Coryphaeus Saunders</hi> had ſlily pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the name of <hi>Puritan</hi> upon the ſleeves of the Proteſtants that encountred them with <hi>moſt Courage,</hi> and perceiv'd that the <hi>Word</hi> was pleaſing to ſome of our own ſide, they took heart at Graſs, to ſet little by the Service of God, and Duty to their Soveraign—moſt Men grew to be frozen in Zeal and benummed, that whoſoever (as the worthy Lord Keeper <hi>Bacon</hi> obſerv'd in thoſe days) pretended a little ſpark of <hi>Earneſtneſs,</hi> he ſeemed no leſs than red fire hot, in compariſon of the other. And as ſome fare the worſe for an ill Neighbour's ſake dwelling beſide them; ſo did it betide the Proteſtants, who, ſeeking to curb the the Papiſts, or reprove an idle Drone, were incontinently branded with the Ignominious note of <hi>Preciſian,</hi> all which wind brought plenty of water to the <hi>Pope's Mill,</hi> and there will moſt Men grind where they ſee Appearance to be well ſerved: So far Sir <hi>Robert Cotton.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And as the diſgracing Godly-Miniſters by faſtning the names of <hi>Puritan, Preciſian,</hi> &amp;c. on 'em, and the laying 'em aſide from the publick exerciſe of their Miniſtry, did in the Reign of <hi>Elizabeth</hi> give life to Popery, ſo 'twill ſtill, and all thoſe Proteſtant Miniſters that are now denied en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the Pariſh Churches will be in diſgrace amongſt the People and their Miniſtry not half ſo ſucceſsful amongſt thoſe that moſtly need it.</p>
               <p>The <hi>wider</hi> therefore the Church Doors are made, the greater will be the number of Pious and Painful Preachers, the greater the Advantage on Truth's ſide, and the greater Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement on the other hand.</p>
               <p>But that the Door may be made <hi>wide enough</hi> to anſwer the deſired End, ſeeing our Governours are inclin'd to lay aſide the ſtrict uſe of Ceremonies, with ſome more offenſive Impoſitions there is this one thing, to wit, The <hi>Ordering,</hi> and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56457:7"/>
                  <hi>Declaring the Government of the Church</hi> to <hi>be now no other,</hi> but <hi>what it was held, and intended to be by the firſt</hi> Reformers, <hi>will,</hi> as I humbly apprehend, be the moſt Effectual Expedient of any elſe in the World.</p>
               <p>Some of our Clergy have Notions about <hi>Church-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> very Diſſonant from what the Gentry, and <hi>Parliament Men</hi> have, and the firſt Reformers heretofore had, and it's feared by ſome thinking Perſons, that the <hi>Laws,</hi> yet in Being, have Eſtabliſhed a Government in the Church, very different from what the <hi>Legiſlators,</hi> I mean, the King, the Temporal Lords and Commons generally deſigned.</p>
               <p>The Government ſettled in the Church by the firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers, and ſtill ſuppoſed by our Gentry to continue, is conſiſtent enough with the Church ſtate of all other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants; but <hi>that,</hi> which is really Eſtabliſhed by Law is Inconſiſtent with, and Deſtructive of it, driving many Learned Godly Proteſtant Divines from that Conformity which is at this time made neceſſary to the Exerciſe of their Miniſtry in Pariſh Churches.</p>
               <p>To clear thus much is (methinks) one of the moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary things to be attempted, and the very <hi>next ſtep</hi> to be taken towards the ſetling a Comprehenſion, which will be of validity with Judicious Men.</p>
               <p>What were the Sentiments of the Firſt-Reformers about <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and <hi>Church Government,</hi> during Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Reign, I will with the greateſt impartiality declare, as near as poſſibly I can in their own words, and add ſome Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to ſhew, that the moſt effectual way to ſettle ſuch a <hi>Comprehenſion</hi> as will beſt ſecure the Proteſtant Religion, is the Forming and Framing the Government of the Church, according to the Sentiments of our <hi>Firſt-Reformers;</hi> which in the Learned Archbiſhop <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi>'s <hi>Reduction</hi> of Epiſcopacy, I take to be very happily copied out unto us.</p>
               <p>I will begin with thoſe who liv'd in <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth's days; for then began the <hi>Reformation.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:56457:8"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> The Senſe of our Firſt Reformers in <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth's Days.</head>
               <p>IN this King's Reign <hi>Tindall, Lambert</hi> and <hi>Barnes,</hi> Men of good Learning, and bleſſed Martyrs, ſealing the Truths they profeſſed with their Blood, ſtruggled ſtrenuouſly for a Reformation of <hi>Church Government.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tindall,</hi> looking on Corruptions in <hi>Diſcipline</hi> to be a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal occaſion of that greater Deluge of Enormities in the Church, preſſeth for a Reduction of all things in the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline to the <hi>Apoſtolical Inſtitution,</hi> and therefore makes En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry after thoſe Officers, the Apoſtles Ordained in Chriſt's Church, and what their Offices were, and gives us an account of his Perſwaſion of it thus: <q>Wherefore the Apoſtles following and obeying the Rule,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tindall</hi>'s Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Popiſh Prelates.</note> Doctrine and Commandment of our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, Ordained in his Kingdom and Congregation <hi>TWO OFFICERS:</hi> one called after the <hi>Greek</hi> word <hi>Biſhop,</hi> in <hi>Engliſh</hi> an <hi>Overſeer,</hi> which ſame was called <hi>Prieſt</hi> after the <hi>Greek, Elder</hi> in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> becauſe of his Age, Diſcretion, and Sadneſs; for he was as nigh as could be always an <hi>Elderly Man.</hi> And this Overſeer hath put his hands unto the Plough of God's Word, and fed Chriſt's Flock, and tended them only, without looking to any other Buſineſs in the World. Another <hi>Officer</hi> they choſe, and called him <hi>Deacon,</hi> after the <hi>Greek,</hi> a <hi>Miniſter</hi> in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> to <hi>Miniſter the Alms of the People unto the Poor, and Needy.</hi> For in the Congregation of Chriſt, love maketh every Man's Gifts and Goods common to the Neceſſity of his Neighbour—There is <hi>Presbyteros</hi> called an <hi>Elder</hi> by birth,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tindall</hi> on the word <hi>Elder.</hi>
                     </note> which ſame is called imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> or <hi>Overſeer,</hi> to declare what
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56457:8"/>Perſons are meant,—They were called <hi>Elders,</hi> becauſe of their Age, Gravity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Overſeers</hi> by reaſon of their <hi>Offices.</hi> And all that were called <hi>Elders,</hi> or <hi>Prieſts</hi> (if they ſo will) were called <hi>Biſhops</hi> alſo, tho' they have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided the names now, which thing thou mayſt evidently ſee by the firſt Chapter of <hi>Titus,</hi> and the twentieth of the <hi>Acts.</hi> Thoſe <hi>Overſeers,</hi> which we now call <hi>Biſhops</hi> after the Greek word, were alway <hi>biding in One</hi> place to Govern the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation there; But <hi>Deacons</hi> were Overſeers of the Poor, and crept not into Orders till the Church grew <hi>rich.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lambert</hi> is of the ſame Opinion. <q>As touching Prieſthood (ſaith he) in the <hi>Primitive Church,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ach. Mon.</hi> Vol. 2.</note> when Vertue bare (as ancient Doctors do deem, and Scripture in mine opinion recordeth the ſame) the moſt room, there were no more Officers in the Church of God than <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Deacons,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>Miniſters,</hi> as witneſſeth beſides Scripture, full apertly <hi>Hierome</hi> in his <hi>Commentaries</hi> upon the Epiſtles of <hi>Paul;</hi> whereas he faith, That thoſe we call <hi>Prieſts,</hi> were all one and no other but <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> none other but <hi>Priests,</hi> Men ancient both in Age and Learning, ſo near as they could be choſen. Neither were they <hi>Inſtitute,</hi> and choſen as they be now adays, with ſmall regard of a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> or his <hi>Officer,</hi> only appoſing them, if they can conſtrue a Collect.—To conclude, I ſay, the <hi>Order,</hi> or <hi>State</hi> of <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Deacons</hi> was Ordained by God.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The Sixth Article againſt Dr. <hi>Barnes</hi> was, That he declared himſelf thus. <q>I will never believe, nor yet can I ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that one Man may be by the Law of God a Biſhop of two, or three Cities, yea, of an whole Countrey; for it is contrary to St. <hi>Paul,</hi> which ſaith, <hi>I have left thee behind, to ſet in every City a Biſhop.</hi> And if you find in one place of Scripture that they be called <hi>Epiſcopi,</hi> you ſhall find in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that they be called <hi>Presbyteri.</hi>—I was (ſaith he) brought before my Lord <hi>Cardinal</hi> into his Gallery, and there he read all my Articles till he came to this, and there he ſtopped, and ſaid, That <hi>this touch'd him,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ask'd me, if I thought it wrong that <hi>One Biſhop</hi> ſhould have ſo many Cities underneath him? Unto whom I
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:56457:9"/>anſwered, That I could no further go than to St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Text, which, ſet in every City a Biſhop. Then asked he me, whether I thought it unright (ſeeing the Ordinance of the Church, that one Biſhop ſhould have ſo many Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties? I anſwered, that I knew no Ordinance of the Church, as concerning this thing, but St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Saying only? Nevertheleſs I did ſee a contrary Cuſtom and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice in the World, but I know not the original thereof. Then ſaid He, There were divers Cities, ſome ſeven Miles, ſome ſix Miles long, and over them was there ſet but one <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and of their Suburbs alſo; ſo likewiſe now a <hi>Biſhop</hi> has alſo but one City to his <hi>Cathedral</hi> Church, and the Country about it as Suburbs to it. Methought this was far fetch'd, but I durſt not deny it, becauſe it was ſo great Authority, and of ſo <hi>Holy a Father,</hi> and ſo great a Divine. But this I dare ſay, that his Holineſs could never prove it by Scripture, nor yet by any Authority of Drs. nor yet by any Practice of the Apoſtles, and yet it muſt be true, becauſe a Pillar of the Church has ſpoken it: But let us ſee what the Drs. ſay to mine Article. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> doth declare this Text of the Apoſtle, <hi>I have left thee behind,</hi> &amp;c. He would not commit unto one <hi>Biſhop</hi> a whole <hi>Ylde,</hi> but he did injoyn, that every City ſhould have his <hi>Proper Paſtor,</hi> ſuppoſing, that by this means they ſhould more diligently <hi>Overſee</hi> the People—Alſo <hi>Chryſostom</hi> on that ſame Text: <hi>He would not that a whole Country ſhould be permitted unto One man,</hi> but <hi>He enjoyned to every man his Cure, by that means he knew, that his Labour ſhould be more eaſie,</hi> and <hi>the Subjects ſhould be with more Diligence Govern'd, if the Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers were not diſtract with the Governing of</hi> many <hi>Churches, but had <hi>Cure,</hi> and <hi>Charge</hi> of <hi>one Church</hi> only,</hi> &amp;c. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks theſe be plain words, and able to move a man to ſpeak as much as I did—But I, poor Man, muſt be an Heretick, there is no Remedy, you will have it ſo, and who is able to ſay nay? <hi>Not all Scripture, nor yet God Himſelf.</hi>
                  </q> So far theſe three Worthies.</p>
               <p>About this time the Notion of theſe bleſſed Martyrs found reſpect amongſt thoſe, that bore a great Figure in the Church. The Author of the <hi>True Difference between the Regal Power
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56457:9"/>and the Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> gives countenance unto it, and at laſt <hi>Cranmer</hi> with many others fell in with it, and it became a Point eſtabliſh'd by Authority, as may be ſeen in the <hi>Neceſſary Erudition of a Chriſtian Man,</hi> where, after the Deſcription given of the Office of <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>Deacons,</hi> it's affirmed, That of theſe <hi>Two Orders only <hi>Scripture makes expreſs mention,</hi>
                  </hi> and that we may not miſtake 'em, it's added, <hi>of theſe two <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders only,</hi> that is to ſay, Prieſts, and Deacons, Scripture makes expreſs mention, and how they were conferred by the Apoſtles by Prayer, and Impoſition of hands.</hi> Beſides, The Deſcription they give of the Office of a Biſhop or Prieſt, for when they ſpeak of the Divine Inſtitution, they make no diſtinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween 'em; it's thus: <hi>The Office conſists in true Preaching and Teaching the Word of God unto the People, in Diſpenſing and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring the Sacraments, in Conſecrating and Offering the bleſſed Body and Blood of Christ in the Sacrament of the Altar, in loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and aſſoyling from Sin ſuch Perſons as be ſorry and truly pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent for the ſame, and Excommunicating ſuch as be guilty in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest Crimes, and will not be reformed otherwiſe, and finally in Praying for the whole Church of Christ, and eſpecially for the Flock committed to them.</hi> Thus there are but two <hi>Orders only,</hi> that is to ſay, Prieſts and Deacons, no third Order; Biſhops therefore muſt be of the ſame Order with Prieſts, and their Office the ſame, and the Superiority of one above the other only by Humane Ordinance and Appointment. <hi>And whereas</hi> (ſay they) <hi>we have thus ſummarily declared what is the Office and Miniſtration which in Holy Scriptures has been committed to Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Priests, and in what things it conſiſteth, as is afore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed, we think it expedient and neceſſary, that all men ſhould be advertis'd, and taught, that all ſuch Lawful Power and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of any one Biſhop</hi> [or <hi>Priest,</hi> for they are in the ſenſe of theſe Great Divines the ſame] <hi>over another were,</hi> and <hi>be given them by the Conſent, Ordinance, and Poſitive Laws of Men only, and not by any Ordinance of God in Holy Scripture.</hi> So far the <hi>Neceſſary Erudition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus in <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth's days, the Biſhop and Prieſt of the ſame Order according to the Scriptures, and their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice the ſame, the Difference therefore between 'em and the Government that is grounded thereupon by Prelatick
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56457:10"/>Biſhops, Archbiſhops, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is only by the Poſitive Laws of Men.</p>
               <p>In a <hi>Declaration</hi> made of the <hi>Functions</hi> and <hi>Divine Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Biſhops and Priests,</hi> ſubſcrib'd by <hi>Thomas Cromwell,</hi> the Archbiſhops of <hi>Canterbury</hi> and <hi>York,</hi> and divers other Biſhops,<note place="margin">Conſult the <hi>Adden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> in Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi>'s Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>p. 321, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Civilians,</hi> and Learned Men, it is thus Reſolved. <q>As touching the Sacrament of Holy Orders. We will, That all Biſhops and Preachers ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct and teach our People committed by us unto their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Charge. Firſt, How that Chriſt and his Apoſtles did inſtitute and ordain in the New Teſtament, that beſide the Civil Powers, and Governance of Kings and Princes, which is called in Scripture <hi>Poteſtas gladii,</hi> the Power of the Sword, there ſhould be alſo continually in the Church Militant, certain other Miniſters, or Officers, which ſhould have Spiritual Power, Authority and Commiſſion under Chriſt to Preach and Teach the Word of God unto his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and to Diſpenſe and Adminiſter the Sacraments of God unto them; and by the ſame to confer and give the Grace of the Holy Ghoſt, to conſecrate the bleſſed Body of Chriſt in the Sacrament of the Altar, to looſe and abſoile from Sin, all Perſons which be duly penitent, and ſorry for the ſame; to bind and Excommunicate ſuch as be Guilty in manifeſt Crimes and Sins, and will not amend their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faults, to order and conſecrate others in the ſame room, Order and Office whereunto they recalled &amp; admitted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and finally, to feed Chriſt's People like good <hi>Paſtors</hi> and <hi>Rectors,</hi> as the Apoſtle calleth them, with their whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom Doctrin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and by their continual Exhortations and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions to reduce them from Sin and Iniquity ſo much as in them lieth, and to bring them unto perfect Knowledge the perfect Love and Dread of God, and unto the perfect Charity of their Neighbours.—That this Office, this Power and Authority was committed and given by Chriſt and his Apoſtles unto certain Perſons <hi>only,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>unto <hi>Prieſts,</hi> OR <hi>Biſhops,</hi> whom they did Elect, call and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit thereunto by their Prayer, and Impoſition of their hands.</hi>—And to the intent the Church of Chriſt ſhould never
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:56457:10"/>be deſtituted of ſuch Miniſters as ſhould have and execute the ſaid Power of the <hi>Keys,</hi> it was alſo Ordained and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the Apoſtles, that the ſame Sacrament ſhould be applied and miniſtred by the Biſhops from time to time, unto ſuch other Perſons as had the Qualities which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles very diligently deſcryve; as it appeareth evidently in the third Chapter of the firſt Epiſtle of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi> and his Epiſtle unto <hi>Titus.</hi> And ſurely this is the whole Vertue and Efficacy, and the Cauſe alſo of the Inſtitution of this Sacrament, as it is found in the <hi>New Teſtament;</hi> for albeit the Holy Fathers of the Church of Chriſt, with all thoſe things which were commendable in the Temple of the <hi>Jews,</hi> did deviſe not only certain other Ceremonies than before rehearſed, as <hi>Tonſures, Raſures, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nctions,</hi> and ſuch other Obſervances to be uſed in the Adminiſtration of the ſaid Sacraments; but did alſo Inſtitute certain Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Orders or Degrees, as <hi>Janitors, Lectors, Exorciſts, Acolits,</hi> and <hi>Sub-Deacons;</hi> and deputed to every one of thoſe certain Offices to execute in the Church, wherein they fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed undoubtedly the Example and Rites uſed in the Old Teſtament; yet the Truth is, <hi>That in the New Teſtament there is no mention made of any <hi>Degrees,</hi>
                     </hi> or <hi>Diſtinctions <hi>in Orders, but only of</hi> Deacons, <hi>OR</hi> Miniſters, <hi>and of</hi> Prieſts, <hi>OR</hi> Biſhops: <hi>Nor there is any word ſpoken of any other Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony uſed in the Conferring of this Sacrament; but only of Prayer, and the Impoſition of the Biſhops hand.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Thus the Power of <hi>Excommunication,</hi> and <hi>conferring Orders</hi> by Prayer and Impoſition of Hands, as declared in the <hi>New Testament,</hi> belongs unto the <hi>Priest,</hi> which is the ſame with the Biſhop; there being no Degrees or Diſtinctions in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, but only of <hi>Deacons</hi> or <hi>Miniſters;</hi> and <hi>Priests</hi> or <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and conſequently no Superiority therefore of a Biſhop above a Prieſt to be found in the New Teſtament, during King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth's days.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:56457:11"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> The Judgment of the <hi>Reformers</hi> in <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth's Days the ſame 'twas in <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth's, holding no Difference by Divine Law between a <hi>Biſhop</hi> and <hi>Presbyter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN the Firſt Year of <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth's Reign, an Act of Parliament paſſed, ſufficiently Declaring the Epiſcopal Orders as diſtinct from, and above that of the Presbyter, to be wholly from the Crown; for it was affirm'd, That all Authority of Juriſdiction <hi>Spiritual,</hi> is derived and deducted from the King's Majeſty, as <hi>Supream Head</hi> of theſe Churches of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>The Deſign of this Law, as Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> has it, <hi>was to weaken</hi> the Authority of the <hi>Epiſcopal Order,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hiſt.</hi> Edw. 6. p. 51.</note> by forcing them from their ſtrong hold of <hi>Divine Inſtitution,</hi> and making them no other than the King's Miniſters only, His Eccleſiaſtical Sheriffs (as a man might ſay) to execute his Will, and diſperſe his Mandates.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Poynet</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Winchester,</hi> in this King's Reign, in Anſwer unto a Book writ by <hi>Stephen Gardiner,</hi> tho' ſent out under the Name of Dr. <hi>Martin,</hi> about the <hi>Marriage of Prieſts,</hi> doth ſufficiently ſhew that the <hi>Reformers</hi> in thoſe days were great Approvers of <hi>Calvin</hi>'s Notions about Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and therefore willing to lay aſide even the very Name <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and make uſe of the Names [<hi>Superintendent, Minister, Senior, Elders,</hi> &amp;c.] for theſe are his words. <q>And further, whereas it pleaſeth <hi>Martin,</hi> not only in this place, but alſo hereafter, to Jeſt at the Name <hi>[Superintendent,]</hi> he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth himſelf bent to condemn all things that be good. Who knoweth not, that the Name <hi>[Biſhop]</hi> hath ſo been abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that when it was ſpoken, the People underſtood no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but a great <hi>Lord, that went in a white Rochet, with a wide ſhaven Crown,</hi> and that <hi>carrieth an Oyl Box with him,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:56457:11"/>wherewith he uſeth once in ſeven years, riding about to Confirm Children,</hi> &amp;c. Now to bring the People from this <hi>abuſe,</hi> what better means can be deviſed than to teach the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple their Error by another word out of the Scriptures of the ſame ſignification, which thing by the term <hi>[Superin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendent]</hi> would in time have been well brought to paſs—The name <hi>[Biſhop]</hi> ſpoken amongſt the Unlearned, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified to them nothing leſs than a <hi>Preacher of God's Word,</hi> becauſe there was not, nor is any thing more rare in any Order of Eccleſiaſtical Perſons than to ſee a Biſhop Preach.—I deny not, but the name <hi>[Biſhop]</hi> may be well taken, but becauſe the Evilneſs of the Abuſe hath marred the Goodneſs of the Word, it cannot be denied but that it was not amiſs to joyn for a time another word with it in his place, whereby to reſtore that abuſed word to his Right Signification.—Oh how the Papiſts would tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph over us, if they had like proof for the names (I ſay) of <hi>Pope, Cardinal, Canon, Prebendary, Monk,</hi> &amp;c. as we, that profeſs Chriſt have for the maintainance of the terms and names <hi>(Superintendent, Miniſter, Seniors, Elders, Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,)</hi> and ſuch like by us uſed.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The Reſolution Archbiſhop <hi>Cranmer</hi> gave to the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions propounded by <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. approved by the Biſhop of St. <hi>Aſaph, Therleby, Redman</hi> and <hi>Cox,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See Dr. <hi>Stilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flèet</hi>'s MS.</note> makes it manifeſt, that theſe great <hi>Reformers</hi> owned not Epiſcopacy as a Diſtinct Order from Presbytery, of <hi>Divine Right,</hi> but only, as a prudent Conſtitution of the Civil Magiſtrate for the better Governing the Church. <q>In the Apoſtles time (ſays <hi>Cranmer</hi>) when there was no Chriſtian Princes by whoſe Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity Miniſters of God's Word might be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Reſol.</hi> to Q. 9.</note> nor Sins by the Sword corrected, there was no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy then for the Correction of Vice, or appointing of Miniſters, but only the conſent of Chriſtien multitude by themſelfe, by an Uniform conſent to follow the advice and perſwaſion of ſuch Perſons, whom God had moſt endued with the Spirit of wiſdom and counſaile.—Sometime the Apoſtles and other unto whom God had given abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly his Spirit, ſent, or appointed Miniſters of God's
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:56457:12"/>Word, ſometime the People did chooſe ſuch as they thought meet thereunto.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>—The <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Priests were at one time,</hi> and <hi>were not two diſtinct Things,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Reſol. to</hi> Q. 10.</note> but <hi>both one Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice</hi> in the Beginning of Chriſt's Religion.—The People before Chriſtian Princes were,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Reſol. to</hi> Q. 11.</note> commonly elected their Biſhops and Prieſts.—In the <hi>New Testament,</hi> he that is appointed to be a Biſhop or Prieſt, needeth no conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration by the Scripture;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Reſol. to</hi> Q. 12.</note> for Election or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing thereto is ſufficient.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Thus far that Excellent Perſon (ſaith a Reverend Divine of the Church of <hi>England</hi>) in whoſe Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment nothing is more clear than his aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing the particular Form of Government in the Church to the Determination of the <hi>Supream Magistrate.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Divine Right of Forms of Church Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment Examined, <hi>p. 390, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III. Aley</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Exeter, Pilkington</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Durham, Jewel</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury, Whitgift</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> of the ſame Opinion with <hi>Tindall, Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert, Barnes,</hi> and the <hi>Reformers</hi> in King <hi>Edward's</hi> Time.</head>
               <p>IN Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Reign, the firſt I find to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion any thing about the Office of <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Priests,</hi> is Dr. <hi>Alley</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Exeter,</hi> in his <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellanea</hi> on his third <hi>Praelection,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Alley<hi>'s Poor Man's Library,</hi> Tom. 1. pag. 95, 96.</note> read at <hi>Paul</hi>'s in the Year 1560. on the word <hi>Biſhops.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>What difference is between a Biſhop and a Prieſt, St. <hi>Hierome</hi> writing <hi>ad Titum,</hi> doth declare, whoſe words be theſe: <hi>Idem est ergo Presbyter, qui Epiſcopus, &amp;c.</hi> A Prieſt therefore is the ſame that a Biſhop is. And before Schiſms
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:56457:12"/>and Factions by the inſtinct of the Devil begun in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and before it was ſaid among the People, I am <hi>Pauls,</hi> I am <hi>Apollos,</hi> I am of <hi>Cephas,</hi> the Churches were Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned <hi>with the Common Councel of the Priests</hi> (or Elders.)</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>But after that every one thought thoſe whom he Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed to be his, and not Chriſt's, it was decreed throughout the World, that one of the Prieſts or Elders ſhould be choſen to be ſet over the reſt, unto whom all the care (or charge) of the Church ſhould appertain, and that the beginnings of Schiſms ſhould be taken away. Some do think, that it is not the ſentence of the Scriptures, but ours, that a Biſhop and Prieſt, (or Elder) are one thing, and they do alſo think the one to be a name of Age, and the other to be a name of Office. Let them read again the words of the Apoſtle to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> ſaying, Paul <hi>and</hi> Timotheus <hi>the Servants of Jeſu Chriſt, to all the Saints in Chriſt Jeſu, which are at</hi> Philippos, <hi>with the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Deacons, Grace and Peace be with you,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Philippi</hi> is one of the Cities of <hi>Macedonia.</hi> And truly there could not be many (as they are called) Biſhops in one City. But becauſe at that time they called thoſe Biſhops, which they did alſo call Prieſts (or Elders) therefore indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he ſpake of Biſhops, as of Prieſts (or Elders). It may yet ſeem doubtful to ſome, unleſs it be approved by other Teſtimonies. In the <hi>Acts of the Apostles</hi> it is written, that when the Apoſtle came to <hi>Miletum,</hi> he ſent to <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and did call the Prieſts (or Elders) of the ſame Church, unto whom among other things he ſaid thus, <hi>A Hand to your ſelves,</hi> &amp;c. And here mark you diligently, how that he calling the Prieſts or Elders of that one City of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> did afterwards call them <hi>Biſhops,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>Peter</hi> which took his name of the firmneſs of his Faith, in his Epiſtle ſaith, <hi>I your fellow Elder do beſeech the Elders that are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Haec Hieronimus.</hi> Theſe words are alledg'd, (ſaith Biſhop <hi>Aley</hi>) that it may appear, Prieſts among the Elders, to have been even the ſame that Biſhops were. But it grew by little and little, that the whole charge and care ſhould be appointed to one Biſhop within his Precinct, that the Seeds of Diſſention might be utterly rooted out.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:56457:13"/>
               <p>In his Second <hi>Tome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 15.</note> the Biſhop adds out of St. <hi>Jerom,</hi> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>Sicut Preſbyteri, &amp;c.</hi> Like as Prieſts do know themſelves to be ſubject by the <hi>Custom of the Church,</hi> unto him which is made Ruler over them: So let the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> know, that they are greater than the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> rather <hi>by Custom,</hi> than <hi>by the</hi> verity <hi>of Diſpenſation given of the Lord.</hi> He ſaith alſo in another place, with the old Fathers, the Biſhops were the ſame that the Prieſts were; for the name of one is the name of Dignity, and the other of Age and Time.</q> So far Biſhop <hi>Aley.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next I meet with is <hi>Pilkington,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Dureſme,</hi> the Author of the <hi>Confutation</hi> of an <hi>Addition</hi> with <hi>an Apology,</hi> written, and caſt in the Streets of <hi>West-Chester</hi> againſt the <hi>Cauſes</hi> of <hi>Burning Paul</hi>'s Church in <hi>London,</hi> declared by the Biſhop at <hi>Paul's Croſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Biſhop did at <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Croſs</hi> Exhort the people to take the burning of <hi>Paul</hi>'s to be a warning of a greater <hi>Plague</hi> to follow to the City of <hi>London,</hi> if amendment of Life be not had in all Eſtates, the Author of the Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (a Papiſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hiſtor. Q.</hi> Eliz. pag. 312.</note> notwithſtanding what <hi>Heylin</hi> ſaith to the contrary, when he tells us that the Papiſts aſcribe it to ſome practice of the <hi>Zuinglian</hi> Faction, out of their hatred unto all Solemnity and Decency in the Service of God, perform'd more punctually in that Church for Examples ſake than in any other in the Kingdom) im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes it to the laying aſide of the midnight Mattins, forenoon Maſſes formerly had in the Church, and Anthems and Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in the Steeple.</p>
               <p>This Biſhop, a Perſon of great Learning and good Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, in Anſwer to this Paper, doth in the Sixth year of the Queens Reign, thus expreſs himſelf. <q>Yet remains one doubt unanſwered in theſe few words, when he ſaith, that <hi>the Government of the Church was committed to Biſhops,</hi> as tho' they had received a <hi>Larger</hi> and <hi>Higher Commiſſion</hi> from God, of <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline</hi> than other. Lower Prieſts and Miniſters have, and hereby might challenge a greater Prerogative. But this is to be underſtood, that the Privileges and Superiorities which Biſhops have above other Miniſters, are rather granted by Man, for maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:56457:13"/>of better Order and Quietneſs in Common-wealths, than Commanded by God in his Word. Miniſters have better Knowledge and Utterance ſome than other; but their Miniſtry of <hi>Equal</hi> Dignity. God's Commiſſion and Commandment is like, and indifferent to all, Prieſt, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, Archbiſhop, Prelate, by what name ſoever he be called—Saint <hi>Jerome</hi> in his Commentary on 1 Chap. <hi>Tit.</hi> ſays, that a Biſhop and Prieſt is all One, and in his Epiſtle <hi>ad Evagrium</hi> he ſays, That the Biſhop whereſoever he be, is of the ſame Power and Prieſthood.—If they [the Papiſts] were not too much blinded in their own fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, they might ſee in the laſt Subſidy granted in the time of their own Reign, that they grant thoſe to be their betters and above them, from whence they receive their Authority. The Parliament gives them and their Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors Power to Suſpend, Deprive and Interdict any Prieſt, that Pays not the Subſidy: In that doing they grant the Parliament to be above them, and from it to receive their Power.—I had not thought to have ſaid ſo much on theſe his few words, and yet much more hangs on <hi>this</hi> their Opinion of claiming their Uſurped Power above Princes and other Miniſters.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The Learned Biſhop <hi>Jewel</hi> is of the ſame Mind with this Author,<note place="margin">Apol. <hi>Par.</hi> 2. <hi>Ch.</hi> 5. <hi>Diviſ.</hi> 1. <hi>Ch.</hi> 6. <hi>Diviſ.</hi> 1.</note> and thus much he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livereth, not as his private Opinion, but as the ſenſe of the Church of <hi>England,.</hi> 
                  <q>Furthermore we ſay, That the Miniſter ought lawfully, duly, &amp; orderly to be preferr'd to that Office of the Church of God,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ch.</hi> 6. <hi>Diviſ.</hi> 3. <hi>Ch.</hi> 7. <hi>Diviſ.</hi> 5.</note> and that no man hath power to wreſt himſelf into the Holy Miniſtry at his own pleaſure; That Chriſt hath given to his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Power to bind, to looſe, to open, to ſhut; That the Miniſter doth execute the Authority of binding and ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, as often as he ſhutteth up the Gate of the Kingdom of Heaven againſt Unbelieving and Stubborn Perſons, denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing unto them God's Vengeance, and everlaſting Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; or elſe when he doth quite ſhut them out from the boſom of the Church, by open <hi>Excommunication.</hi> Out of doubt, what Sentence ſoever the Miniſter of God ſhall give
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:56457:14"/>in this ſort, God himſelf doth ſo well allow it, that, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever here in Earth by their means is looſed and bound, God himſelf will looſe and bind, and confirm the ſame in Heaven.—And ſeeing one word is given to all, and one only <hi>Key</hi> belongeth to all, we ſay, <hi>there is but one only Power of all Miniſters, as concerning opening and ſhutting.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>At this time ſo much was given the Prieſt, that no room was left to make the Biſhop of an Order diſtinct from him: The Keys belong'd to all Miniſters, to the Prieſt as well as Biſhop.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>Defence of the Apology</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Part. 2. Ch. 3. Diviſ. 5.</note> this Learned Biſhop is more full and particular in his Aſſertions. <q>In St. <hi>Jerom</hi>'s time (ſaith he) there were <hi>Metropolitans, Archbiſhops, Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacons,</hi> and <hi>others,</hi> but Chriſt appointed not theſe Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of Orders from the beginning. Theſe names are not found in all the Scriptures: This is the thing which we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend. St. <hi>Jerom</hi> ſaith, <hi>Sciant Epiſcopi,</hi> &amp;c. Let Biſhops un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that they are in Authority over Prieſts more by <hi>Cuſtom,</hi> than by <hi>Order</hi> of <hi>God's Truth.—Eraſmus</hi> ſpeaking of the times of <hi>Jerom,</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Id temporis idem erat Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copus, Sacerdos, &amp; Presbyter.</hi> Theſe three names <hi>Biſhop, Priest, Presbyter,</hi> at that time were all one.—</q>
               </p>
               <p>To the Teſtimony of <hi>Jerom,</hi> the Biſhop adds that of St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin,</hi> Epiſt. 19. ſaying, <q>That the Office of a Biſhop is above the Office of a Prieſt, not by Authority of the Scriptures, but after the names of Honour, which the cuſtom of the Church hath now obtained.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The Biſhop in Defence of the Church of <hi>England,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Part</hi> 2. <hi>Ch.</hi> 9. <hi>Diviſ.</hi> 1.</note> had affirm'd, That againſt the Sacred Scripture, neither Law, nor Ordinance, nor any Cuſtom ought to be heard, no, tho' <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, or an Angel from Heaven ſhould come, and teach the contrary.</p>
               <p>To this <hi>Harding</hi> replies, <hi>If all things neceſſary to Salvation be contain'd in the Scriptures, then whatever is not in them contained, the ſame is not neceſſary; if not neceſſary, why ſhould we be la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with unneceſſary Burdens? Then away with all Traditions at a Clap, be they never ſo Apoſtolick.—Remember you not what the most Renowned Fathers have ſaid of the Neceſſity of Traditions?—
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:56457:14"/>If we go about to reject the Cuſtoms that be not ſet forth in Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting—we ſhall bring the Preaching of the Faith but to a bare name.</hi> For ſo <hi>they were taken for Hereticks, who denied the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of a Biſhop, and a Prieſt,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jewel</hi> rejoyns, <q>This [in the Margin] in an Untruth, for hereby both St. <hi>Paul</hi> and St. <hi>Jerom,</hi> and other good men are condemn'd of Hereſie.—But what meant Mr. <hi>Harding</hi> here to come in with the Difference between <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Biſhops?</hi> thinketh he that <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>Biſhops</hi> hold only by Tradition? or is it ſo horrible a Hereſie as he makes it, to ſay, That by <hi>the Scriptures of God, a Biſhop and a Priest are all One?</hi> or, knoweth he how far, and to whom he reacheth the name of an Heretick? Verily, <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſaith, Between a Biſhop and a Prieſt, in a manner there is no difference; St. <hi>Jerom</hi> ſaith ſomewhat in a rougher ſort, I hear ſay, There is one become ſo peeviſh, that he ſetteth Deacons before Prieſts, that is to ſay, before Biſhops; whereas the Apoſtle plainly teacheth us, that Prieſts and Biſhops are all one. St. <hi>Austin</hi> ſaith, what is a Biſhop but the <hi>firſt Prieſt,</hi> that is to ſay, the Higheſt Prieſt? ſo ſaith Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> There is but <hi>One Ordination</hi> of <hi>Priest</hi> and <hi>Biſhop,</hi> for both of them are Prieſts, but the Biſhop is the <hi>first.</hi> All theſe and other Holy Fathers, together with St. <hi>Paul</hi> the Apoſtle, for thus ſaying, by Mr. <hi>Harding</hi>'s Advice, muſt be held for Hereticks.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides, as the Biſhop is very expreſs in his aſſerting a Biſhop and Presbyter to be according to Chriſt's Inſtitution all one;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Part</hi> 6. <hi>Chap.</hi> 9. <hi>Diviſ.</hi> 1, &amp; 2.</note> He is no leſs ſo in granting that the Biſhop has receiv'd from the Prince the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Privileges he has above a Presbyter. <q>I grant there be many ſpecial Privileges granted upon great and juſt Conſiderations of the <hi>meer favour of the Prince,</hi> that a Prieſt being found negligent, or otherwiſe offending in his Miniſtry, ſhould be convinced and puniſhed, not by the Temporal and Civil Magiſtrate, but by the Diſcretion of the Biſhop.—Mr. <hi>Harding</hi> muſt remember that all theſe, and other like Privileges paſſed unto the Clergy <hi>from the Prince,</hi> and not from God; and proceed only of ſpecial <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour,</hi> and not of <hi>Right.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:56457:15"/>
               <p>Archbiſhop <hi>Whitgift</hi> in oppoſing <hi>Cartwright</hi>'s Platform a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Government of the Church, aſſerted to be <hi>de Jure divino,</hi> diſtinguiſheth between <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>External</hi> Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſaith, <q>That the <hi>External</hi> Government hath both a <hi>Subſtance</hi> and <hi>Matter</hi> about which it is occupied, and alſo a <hi>Form</hi> to attain the ſame, conſiſting in certain Offices and Functions, and in the Names and Titles of them. The <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> and <hi>Matter</hi> of Government muſt indeed be taken out of the Word of God, and conſiſteth in theſe points: That the Word be truly taught, the Sacraments rightly admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, Vertue furthered, Vice repreſſed, and the Church kept in quietneſs and order: The <hi>Officers</hi> in the Church, whereby this Government is wrought, be <hi>not namely,</hi> and <hi>particularly expreſſed in the Scriptures,</hi> but in ſome points left to the Diſcretion and Liberty of the Church to be diſpoſed according to the ſtate of Times, Places, and Perſons.</q> Thus much in his <hi>Preface;</hi> conform to thoſe who went before. The Miniſtry of the Word and Sacraments, and Reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which belong to the Prieſt, is of God, the other Offices and Functions, which as he elſewhere has it, belong to the external Order and Policy of the Church, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently the Diſtinction between Biſhop and Prieſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Defence, Tract.</hi> c. 3. <hi>Div.</hi> 38, 39, 40, 41.</note> and Superiority of a Biſhop above a Prieſt, are only of humane Inſtitution.</p>
               <p>More particularly, <hi>Cartwright</hi> contending for a ſort of Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline which is a Matter of Faith, and neceſſary to Salvation, the <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> diſtinguiſheth between ſuch things as are <hi>ſo neceſſary,</hi> that <hi>without them we cannot be ſaved,</hi> and ſuch things as are <hi>ſo neceſſary,</hi> that <hi>without 'em, we cannot ſo <hi>well</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently</hi> be ſaved;</hi> and then adds, To be ſhort, <q>I confeſs, that in a Church collected together in <hi>one Place,</hi> and at Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, Government is neceſſary with the ſecond kind of Neceſſity, but that any one kind of Government is ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, that without it, the Church cannot be ſaved, or, that it <hi>may not be altered into ſome other kind,</hi> thought to be more Expedient, <hi>I utterly deny;</hi> and the reaſons that move me ſo to do, be theſe: The firſt is, becauſe I find no <hi>one certain and perfect kind of Government preſcribed or comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the Scriptures,</hi> to the Church of Chriſt; which no
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:56457:15"/>doubt ſhould have been done, if it had been a matter neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to the Salvation of the Church. Secondly, Becauſe the Eſſential Notes of the Church be theſe only; The true Preaching of the Word, and the right Adminiſtration of Sacraments:—So that notwithſtanding, <hi>Government,</hi> or <hi>ſome kind</hi> of <hi>Government</hi> may be a part of the Church, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the outward Form and Perfection of it; yet it is not ſuch a part of the Eſſence and Being, but that it may be the Church of Chriſt without this or that kind of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and therefore the <hi>kind</hi> of the Government is not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary unto Salvation.—There is <hi>no certain kind of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> or <hi>Diſcipline preſcribed to the Churches,</hi> but that the ſame may be altered, as the Profit of the Churches requires; and out of <hi>Gualters</hi> he ſaith, Let every Church follow the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Diſcipline which doth moſt agree with the People with whom it abideth, and which ſeemeth to be moſt fit for the place and time, and let no man here raſhly preſcribe unto others, neither let him bind all Churches to one and the ſame Form.—I do deny, <hi>that the Scriptures do ſet down any one certain Form,</hi> and <hi>kind of Government of the Church to</hi> be <hi>Perpetual,</hi> for all <hi>Times, Perſons,</hi> and <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces:</hi> without Alteration.—It is well known,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tract.</hi> 17. <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. <hi>Diviſ.</hi> 29.</note> that the <hi>manner</hi> and <hi>form of Government</hi> uſed in the <hi>Apoſtles time,</hi> and expreſſed in the Scriptures, <hi>neither is now,</hi> nor <hi>can,</hi> or <hi>ought to be obſerved,</hi> either <hi>touching the Perſons,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">How then can the Government of the Church by Bîſhops, Archbiſhops, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be Apoſtolical?</note> or <hi>the Functions.</hi>—We ſee manifeſtly, that in ſundry points the Government of the Church uſed in the Apoſtles times, is, and hath been of neceſſity <hi>altered,</hi> and that it neither may nor can be revoked; whereby 'tis plain, that any one kind of External Government <hi>perpetually</hi> to be obſerved, is no where in the Scripture preſcribed to the Church, but the charge thereof is left to the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> ſo that nothing be done contrary to the Word of God. This is the Opinion of the beſt Writers,<note place="margin">This was it's like U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſally<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> received by all the Engliſh Clergy in <hi>Whitgifts</hi> time.</note> 
                     <hi>Neither do I know</hi> (ſaith the Archbiſhop) <hi>any Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Man of a contrary Judgment.</hi>—Either we muſt admit another Form <hi>now</hi> of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:56457:16"/>the Church than was in the Apoſtles time, or elſe we muſt ſeclude the Chriſtian Magiſtrate from all Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in Eccleſiaſtical Matters.—I am perſwaded that the External Government of the Church under a Chriſtian Magiſtrate muſt be according to the Kind and Form of Government uſed in the Common-wealth; elſe how can you make the Prince Supream Governour of all States and Cauſes Eccleſiaſtical?—If you therefore will have the <hi>Queen</hi> of <hi>England</hi> Rule as Monarch over all her Dominions, then muſt you alſo give her leave to uſe one Kind and Form of Government in all, and every part of the ſame, and <hi>ſo</hi> to Govern the Church in Eccleſiaſtical Affairs, as ſhe doth the Common-wealth in Civil.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Coſins,</hi> Chancellor to this Archbiſhop, in his Anſwer to the <hi>Abſtract,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 58.</note> aſſerts, <q>That all Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches have not the ſame Form of Diſcipline, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>is it neceſſary that they ſhould,</hi> ſeeing it cannot be proved that any certain particular Form of Church Government is commended to us by the Word of God.</q> Dr. <hi>Low</hi> ſpeaks to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>Complaint of the Church,</hi> No certain Form of Government is preſcribed in the Word;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 64, 66.</note> only general Rules laid down for it.</p>
               <p>Biſhop <hi>Bridges;</hi> God hath not expreſſed the Form of Church Government, at leaſt not ſo as to bind us.</p>
               <p>What is here mention'd of <hi>Coſins, Low,</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Bridges,</hi> I have out of Dean <hi>Stillingfleet</hi>'s <hi>Weapon Salve,</hi> and out of a Learned MS. I have this following paſſage about <hi>Whitaker,</hi> who, making his Remarques on St. <hi>Hierom</hi>'s tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us,<note place="margin">Whitaker, <hi>De Ecleſ. Regimin. Contr.</hi> 4. q. 1. §. 29. p. 540. Col. 2.</note> That the Difference between Presbyters and Biſhops was brought in by Men, long after the Apoſtles, as a Remedy againſt Schiſm, aſſures us, That <hi>it's a Remedy almoſt worſe than the Malady, for it begat and brought in the Pope with his Monarchy into the Church;</hi> and this other of Biſhop <hi>Morton,</hi> telling the Papiſts, That Power of Order, and of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, which they aſcribe to Biſhops, doth <hi>de jure divino</hi> belong to all other Presbyters and particularly,<note place="margin">Morton<hi>'s Apol. Cath.</hi> lib. 1. c. 21. p. 55.</note> That [to <hi>Ordain</hi>] is the <hi>jus anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quum,</hi> the Ancient Right of Presbyters, in fine,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:56457:16"/>That Dr. <hi>Laurence Humfrey,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Holland,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Humf. <hi>againſt</hi> Campian. <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit.</hi> Part 2. p. 273.</note> both of them Doctors of the Chair in <hi>Oxford,</hi> did teach and maintain the ſame Doctrine; <hi>Holland</hi> in the <hi>Act,</hi> July 9. 1608. concluded that the contrary is moſt falſe againſt the Scriptures, the Fathers, the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> the Schoolmen, <hi>Lombard, Aquinas, Bonaventure,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV. Dr.</hi> Willet<hi>'s Sentiments</hi> much the ſame with the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd <hi>Biſhops,</hi> The Difference between a <hi>Biſhop</hi> and <hi>Presbyter</hi> as of <hi>Divine Right</hi> declur'd to be <hi>Popiſh,</hi> and oppos'd as <hi>ſuch.</hi> The ſpecial <hi>Conſecration</hi> of <hi>Biſhops</hi> was Ordained, not by a Divine Law, but by the <hi>Church,</hi> for the Dignity of their Calling. <hi>Saravia</hi> for no other Difference between a <hi>Presbyter</hi> and <hi>Biſhop</hi> but in <hi>Degree. Bancroft</hi> for a <hi>Priority</hi> in <hi>degree only,</hi> holding with Dr. <hi>Robinſon,</hi> Dr. <hi>Reynolds,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Fulk,</hi> whoſe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities <hi>he</hi> inſiſts on to Confirm his Opinion about <hi>a</hi> Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual <hi>Difference</hi> between <hi>Biſhop</hi> and <hi>Presbyter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TO theſe I will add another, namely,<note place="margin">In his Life of <hi>Willet.</hi>
                  </note> Dr. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew Willet;</hi> who, as Dr. <hi>Smith</hi> obſerves, is by Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi> numbred amongſt thoſe <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hall <hi>in his</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah<hi>'s</hi> Dove.</note> to whom he gives this Elogy, <hi>Stupor mundi Clerus Britannicus.</hi> This Dr. in his <hi>Synopſis Papiſmi</hi> is very large in diſcuſſing the Difference between a Biſhop and Presbyter, and in his Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations in moſt things agreeth with the Learned Authors I have already quoted.</p>
               <p>The grand Queſtion under Debate is,<note place="margin">Willet<hi>'s Synopſ. Papiſm. Contr.</hi> 5. <hi>Queſt.</hi> 3. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Clergy. <hi>Append.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Difference between Biſhops and other Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, be grounded upon the Law of God,</hi> and <hi>Inſtitution of the Apoſtles?</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:56457:17"/>
               <p>The <hi>Papiſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Bellarmine</hi> (ſaith the Dr.) affirmeth,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>De Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricis,</hi> c. 14.</note> That the Juriſdiction of Biſhops, as now it ſtandeth in their Church, and the Difference between them, and other Presbyters is, <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> grounded upon the Law of God, and of ſuch neceſſity, that he holdeth the contrary to be <hi>Hereſie;</hi> and thoſe to be Hereticks that hold this Difference to ariſe rather of a Politick Conſtitution of the Church to avoid Schiſm, than of the Inſtitution of the Apoſtles; yea, they hold them to be no Churches at all, which are not under the Government of Biſhops, but of other Overſeers and Superintendents. Surely, I ſee not (ſaith one) How there can be any Church where there is no Biſhop.<note place="margin">Eſpenc. <hi>in</hi> 1 Tim. 194. h.</note>—</q>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Proteſtants.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Of the Difference between Biſhops and Prieſts, there are three Opinions: The firſt of <hi>Aerius,</hi> who did hold that all Miniſters ſhould be Equal, and that a Biſhop was not, <hi>nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ought to be</hi> Superiour to a Prieſt, neither that there was any Difference at all between them,<note place="margin">Auguſt. <hi>de Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ.</hi> c. 53. Epiphan. <hi>Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ.</hi> 75.</note> which Opinion of his was counted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other <hi>Hereſies:</hi> The ſecond Opinion in the other Extream is of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> as we have ſeen, that would have not only a Difference, but a Princely Pre-eminence of their Biſhops over the Clergy, and that by the <hi>Word of God.</hi> The third Opinion is between both, that altho' this Diſtinction of Biſhops and Prieſts, as it is now received, cannot be directly proved out of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: yet it is very good for the Policy of the Church, to avoid Schiſm, and to preſerve it in Unity. Of this Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Biſhop <hi>Jewel</hi> againſt <hi>Harding,</hi> ſheweth both <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Biſh.</hi> Whitgift.</note> 
                     <hi>Ambroſe</hi> and <hi>Hierom</hi> to have been. And another moſt Reverend Prelate of our Church in theſe words: I know theſe Names be confounded in the Scriptures, but I ſpeak according to the manner and Cuſtom of the Church ever ſince the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles times; which ſaying is agreeable to that of St. <hi>Auguſtine;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Epiſt. <hi>19.</hi> ad Hieron.</note> 
                     <hi>Secundum,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>according to the Names of Honour, which the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe or Cuſtom
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:56457:17"/>of the Church hath obtain'd,</hi> a <hi>Biſhop is greater than a Prieſt;</hi> ſo that <hi>Auguſtine</hi> himſelf, who was no <hi>Aerian,</hi> doth ground this Diſtinction rather upon <hi>Ancient Cuſtom</hi> than the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>—The Difference between the Opinion of <hi>P.</hi> 275. <hi>Aerius</hi> on the one part, and of <hi>Hierom, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe, Auſtin, Chryſoſtom</hi> on the other, lyeth here: <hi>Aerius</hi> would have no difference at all between a Biſhop and a Prieſt: the Fathers above allowed a difference, holding it to be profitable for the Peace of the Church: They only affirm'd, That this Diſtinction was rather Authorized by the Ancient Practice of the Church, than by any direct place of Scripture. For the proof that a Biſhop and Prieſt were all one in the Apoſtles time, St. <hi>Hierom</hi> alledgeth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers places of Scripture. The ſecond Argument is thus: <hi>Archbiſhops and Primates have the ſame Right of Juriſdiction over other Biſhops, which Biſhops have over ſimple Prieſts:</hi> But their Authority and Juriſdiction is rather grounded upon the <hi>Ancient Cuſtom</hi> of the Church, than any <hi>Apoſtolical Injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> or <hi>Inſtitution</hi> in Scripture.—A fourth Argument, If the Diſtinction of Biſhops and Prieſts were by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment and Inſtitution of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, it ſhould neceſſarily be enjoyned unto all Churches; But this cannot, without prejudice of many Reformed Churches, be affirmed, which have no Biſhops, tho' they have other Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers in their ſtead—Wherefore I cannot conclude <hi>that this ſpecial Form of Eccleſiaſtical Government is abſolutely preſcribed in the Word:</hi> for then all thoſe Churches, which have not that Preſcript Form, whether of Biſhops or other, ſhould be condemned as Erroneous Churches. So then here is a difference between our Adverſaries the Papiſts, and us: They ſay, it is of <hi>neceſſity</hi> to Salvation to be ſubject to the <hi>Pope,</hi> and to <hi>Biſhops and Archbiſhops under him,</hi> as neceſſarily preſcribed in the Word; but ſo do not our <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Archbiſhops,</hi> which is a <hi>not able difference</hi> between the Biſhops of the Popiſh Church, and of the Reformed Churches.—Let every Church uſe that Form which beſt <hi>fitteth their ſtate:</hi> In <hi>External Matters</hi> every Church is Free, not one bound to the Preſcription of another; ſo they meaſure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:56457:18"/>by the Rule of the Word.—Now to conclude this whole Matter, and to ſpeak diſtinctly of every Point, that it may appear how far this Difference in Eccleſiaſtical Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions is <hi>Divine,</hi> and wherein <hi>Humane:</hi> This I judge may ſafely without any Contradiction be affirmed, that in this Diſtinction of the Miniſters of the Church there is ſome. what <hi>Apoſtolical,</hi> ſomewhat alſo <hi>Political.</hi>—Firſt, In the calling of Biſhops, as they are now Ordain'd in ſome Reformed Church, there is ſomewhat <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolical:</hi> for it cannot be denied, but that to have Order in the Church, and to have diverſity of Degrees, and Miniſtrations to avoid confuſion, proceedeth from the Inſtitution of Chriſt.—This then we ſay is agreeable to the Inſtitution of Chriſt, that there ſhould be, not a <hi>Popular Equality,</hi> but a conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient Superiority, and <hi>Priority</hi> in the Miniſters of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; as St. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo ſheweth, <hi>Firſt, Apostles; Secondly, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> &amp;c. Secondly, there is ſomewhat <hi>Political,</hi> and that of two ſorts, as touching the Politie <hi>Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> and <hi>Civil.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>To the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Politie</hi> in the advancing the Dignity of Biſhops theſe things do appertain.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Firſt of all St. <hi>Hierom</hi> ſaith, of <hi>Confirmation</hi> commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted only to Biſhops, <hi>Diſce hanc,</hi> &amp;c. Know that this Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is rather for the Honour of their Prieſthood, than by neceſſity of any Law. <hi>Hierom. adver. Luciferian.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Secondly, The Council of <hi>Aquiſgrane,</hi> cap. 8. ſaith, That the <hi>Ordination</hi> and <hi>Conſecration</hi> of Miniſters is now reſerved to the <hi>Chief Minister, Solum propter Authoritatem;</hi> only for Authority ſake, leſt that the Diſcipline of the Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing challenged by many, ſhould break the Peace of the Church.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Thirdly, The Author of the Book under <hi>Hierom</hi>'s Name, <hi>De</hi> 7. <hi>Ordinib.</hi> ſaith, That the Conſecration of Virgins, which is not now in uſe, in the Reformed Churches, was reſerved to the Biſhop for <hi>Concord ſake.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Fourthly, The Juriſdiction of the Church which in time paſt, <hi>Hierome</hi> ſaith, was committed to the <hi>Senate,</hi> or <hi>College of Presbyters,</hi> was afterward to avoid Schiſm, devolv'd to the Biſhop.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:56457:18"/>
               <p>
                  <q>Fifthly, S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>Epiſcopi &amp; Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teri,</hi> &amp;c. A Biſhop and a Presbyter have but one Ordination; for they are both in the Prieſthood. Whereby it may appear, that the <hi>Special Conſecration of Biſhops</hi> was ſince Ordain'd for the Dignity of that Calling. And S. <hi>Hierom</hi> ſaith, <hi>That in the Church of</hi> Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria, <hi>the Presbyters did make Choice of one,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Hier. <hi>ad</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagr.</note> 
                     <hi>whom they placed in a Higher Degree, and called him their Biſhop; like as if an Army ſhould chooſe a</hi> General, <hi>or the Deacons ſhould chooſe an Induſtrious man whom they make their</hi> Archdeacon. So it ſhould ſeem that the very <hi>Election</hi> of a Biſhop in thoſe Days without any other circumſtances, was his <hi>Ordination.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Sixthly, In <hi>Hierom</hi>'s time, it was lawful for Prieſts and Miniſters to Preach without further Licence obtain'd from the Biſhop, as it may appear <hi>Diſtinct.</hi> 95. <hi>c.</hi> 6. <hi>Qui non vult Presbyteros,</hi> &amp;c. He that will not have a Miniſter to do that which is commanded him of God (that is, to Preach) would be greater than Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>—But ſince to ſtay the Humour of Contentious and Schiſmatical Preachers, it hath ſeemed good to the Church to refer the Allowance of Preachers to the <hi>Ordinary,</hi> according to the Decree of the <hi>Lateran</hi> Council <hi>Sub Innocent.</hi> 3. c. 3. <hi>Praeter Autoritatem.</hi> He that Preacheth privately or publickly without the Authority of the Biſhop, let him be Excommunicated.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Divers other Conſtitutions have been made in Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Politie for the maintaining the Dignity of Biſhops—So alſo the <hi>Civil State</hi> hath augmented and enlarged the Privileges and Immunities of Biſhops, which they have <hi>rather by the Munificence of Princes,</hi> than by <hi>Divine Authority,</hi> As firſt, the Diviſion of Provinces and Cities unto Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops and Biſhops, and the limitation of their Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction was brought in by the conſent of Princes. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, The Revenues and Lands of Biſhopricks have been given by Devout and Religious Princes unto Biſhops and their Succeſſors, and divers Imperial Laws have been made in favour of the Maintenance of the Church. Thirdly, The <hi>Titles</hi> of Honour annexed to Biſhopricks, as that they are created Barons and made Lords of the Parliament-Houſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:56457:19"/>here in <hi>England,</hi> have been beſtowed by the Liberality of the Kings of this Realm, not yet above 400 years ſince.—Fourthly, The Judgment of <hi>Matrimonial</hi> and <hi>Teſtamentary</hi> Cauſes, and of other ſuch like Matters hath been reſerved unto Biſhops by the Civil and Imperial Authority.—Thus we ſee how in Civil Policy, the Dignity of Biſhops, by the favour of Chriſtian Emperors, hath been enlarged: And hitherto I have ſhewed, what is to be judged Political in the Diſtinction of Biſhops from the reſt of the Clergy, both as touching the Civil and Eccleſiaſtical Policy.</q> So far <hi>Willet,</hi> out of whom I obſerve,</p>
               <p>That the Government of the Church is not <hi>de jure divino; That</hi> according to the Scriptures, the Office of a Biſhop, and Prieſt is the ſame; <hi>That</hi> a convenient Priority of Order a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Miniſters is Divine and Apoſtolical; <hi>That</hi> the Powers of Confirmation, Ordination, and Juriſdiction are reſerv'd to the Biſhops by Eccleſiaſtical conſtitutions only; <hi>That</hi> in the Beginning, a Biſhop and Presbyter had but one Ordination, and the Conſecration of Biſhops was added ſince for their greater Dignity: In <hi>Hierom</hi>'s days, the Election of Biſhops without any other circumſtances being their Ordination; That Prieſts without a Licence from the Biſhop might Preach.</p>
               <p>There is one thing more to be regarded touching the Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Biſhops and other Miniſters, for ſays he, <q>We differ from the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in two Points. Firſt, they ſay, That Biſhops are not only in a higher degree of Superiority to other Miniſters, but they are as Princes of the Clergy, and other Miniſters, as Subjects, and in all things to be commanded by them; Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, They affirm, That Biſhops are <hi>only</hi> properly <hi>Pastors,</hi> and that to them only it doth appertain to Preach, and that other Miniſters have no Authority without their Licence or Conſent to preach at all, and that not <hi>principally,</hi> or <hi>chiefly,</hi> but <hi>ſolely</hi> and wholly to them appertaineth the Right of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrating, and giving Orders;</q> ſo that the making the Biſhop to be of a diſtinct Order from the Prieſt, and the denying the Prieſt to have a Power to Preach without the Biſhop's Licence, or any hand in Ordination, <hi>Willet</hi> oppoſeth as Popiſh Doctrines repreſenting the oppoſite Notions to have been then held by the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:56457:19"/>
               <p>Hitherto the Government of the Church by Biſhops, lays no claim to a Divine Right: On the contrary, it's generally aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, that according to the Scriptures, the Prieſt and Biſhop are the ſame, and that the ſuperiority of the Biſhop above the Presbyter is only by Eccleſiaſtick Cuſtom, and the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church now different from what it was in the Apoſtles days.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Willet</hi> indeed ſaith, That for the ſake of Order the <hi>Preſidence</hi> of one above the reſt is Divine and Apoſtolical, and towards the latter end of the Queens Reign, the Epiſcopal Government is affirm'd to be Apoſtolical, and a Divine Inſtitution; yet not to be <hi>de jure divine,</hi> and <hi>unalterable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saravia</hi> about the two and thirtieth year of the <hi>Queen,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth,<note n="*" place="margin">Hoc enim pacto fiet magis clarum, quid om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Evangelii miniſtri inter ſe <hi>habeant com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune</hi> &amp; quid cui<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dini ſit peculiare.—Ea vero in tres partes ego diſtribuo. Prima eſt. Evangelii Praedicatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>: altera Communicatio ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentorum. &amp; tertia Eccleſiaſticae Guberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis authoritas.—<hi>De Diverſ. Grad. Miniſt. Evang. p. 15.</hi> Quamvis unum, &amp; idem. Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelii Miniſterium ſit om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus Paſtoribus Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae concreditum; in hac tertia parte non parva. inter eos invenitur <hi>Inaequalitas</hi> propter diverſos Authoritatis Gradus, quos primo Dominus ſtatim ab initio, &amp; poſtea Apoſtoli conſtituerunt.—<hi>p. 7.</hi> Primum ab ipſo Domino Duos Gradus Evangelii miniſtrorum inſtitutos videmus, quorum al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter altero fuit ſuperior, <hi>p. 25.</hi> Conſenſu totius Orbis Eccleſiarum probatur Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porum ſupra Presbyteros authoritas. Quod inde ab Apoſtolorum temporibus &amp; patribus per univerſum terrarum Orbem factum ab omnibus Eccleſiis legimus uſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>. ad noſtra tempora Canonem Apoſtolorum immutabilem eſſe judico, <hi>p. 44. c. 20.</hi>
                  </note> That the general Nature of the Evangelical Miniſtry, common both to Biſhops and Presbyters, containeth theſe three things.
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>The Preaching of the Goſpel.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>The Communication of the Sacraments.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. <hi>The Authority of Church Government;</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list> and doth only plead, that in this laſt, the Power of Biſhops and Presbyters is not <hi>equal;</hi> but the Biſhop's Power is principal in Government. Whence ariſes a Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of <hi>Degrees,</hi> not of <hi>Orders</hi> between them, and thus much he affirms hath been held by the Fathers of the Church univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally ever ſince the Apoſtles days, and therefore may well be look'd on as an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable Canon of the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>The Difference between <hi>Saravia</hi> and thoſe who went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him lyeth here.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:56457:20"/>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Whit gift, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Saravia.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The Miniſtry of the Word and Sacraments divinely Inſtituted, and to continue to the End of the World; but no particular Form of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment left on Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord in Scripture.</cell>
                        <cell>The Superiority of a Biſhop above a Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter according to St. <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom,</hi> rather by <hi>Cuſtom</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> than an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Christ.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Not only the Miniſtry of the Word and Sacraments, but the <hi>Form of Government,</hi> inſtituted by the Lord himſelf, delivered by the Apoſtles, confirm'd by the Obſervation of the Fathers ought to continue for ever.</cell>
                        <cell>The Superiority in <hi>Degree</hi> of a <hi>Biſhop</hi> above a <hi>Presbyter</hi> a <hi>Divine Institution,</hi> and that St. <hi>Hierom</hi> was in the ſame Error with <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius. Dico privatam fuiſſe Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nymi Opinionem, conſentaneam cum</hi> Aerio, <hi>&amp; Dei verbo contrariam,</hi> p. 51.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>A Year or two after <hi>Saravia</hi>'s Book came out, <hi>Bancroft</hi> (afterwards Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi>) publiſheth a <hi>Survey of the pretended Holy Diſcipline,</hi> as he calls his Book in the <hi>Preface,</hi> to which he ſaith, <q>That we have a Church Government of our own, which is in my conſcience <hi>truly Apoſtolical,</hi> and far to be preferred before any other that is receiv'd this day by any Reformed Church in <hi>Christendom.</hi>
                  </q> And elſewhere in the Book it ſelf,<note place="margin">P. 105.</note> 
                  <q>The <hi>Apostles</hi> (ſaith he) having received the Promiſe of the Holy Ghoſt, after a ſhort time diperſed themſelves (by advice) into di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Regions; and there, by painful Preaching and Labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in the Lord's Harveſt, they planted, no doubt, very many Churches. As the number of Chriſtians grew, and had their particular Aſſemblies and Meetings in many Cities and Countries within every one of their Circuits: they pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced <hi>Paſtors</hi> in every Congregation, they ordained certain <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> men, to be <hi>Chief</hi> Aſſiſters unto them: whom they placed, ſome one in this particular Country, and ſome others in ſundry Cities to have the Rule and Overſight under them, of the Churches there, and to redreſs and ſupply ſuch wants as were needful! And they themſelves (after a
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:56457:20"/>while, and as they grew in age, and eſcaped the Cruelty of Tyrants) remained for the moſt part in ſome Head City within their Compaſs, to overſee them all, both <hi>Churches Paſtors</hi> and <hi>Biſhops,</hi> or <hi>Superintendents,</hi> and to give their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections as occaſions required, and as they thought it conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient. When any of theſe <hi>Apoſtolical Aſſiſtants,</hi> or of the <hi>Apostles</hi> themſelves died, there were ever ſome worthy Men choſen, and appointed to ſucceed them in thoſe Cities and Countries, where they had remained. For we may not idlely Dream, that when they died, the <hi>Authority</hi> which was given them ceaſed: no more than we may, that the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of <hi>Aaron</hi> and of his Natural Sons expired with them; beſides, it is manifeſt by all Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtories, that many Churches were planted after their Deaths. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, it could not be, but that ſome Churches, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially under thoſe Apoſtles, that were ſooneſt put to Death, were (when they died) in the ſame caſe that <hi>Crete</hi> was, when <hi>Titus</hi> was ſent thither, and had therefore as much need of a <hi>Titus</hi> as <hi>Crete</hi> had. Furthermore, who can be accounted to be well in his wits, that will imagine that Chriſt ſhould ordain ſuch an Authority, but for ſome <hi>Threeſcore years?</hi> eſpecially, the ſame Cauſes continuing, <hi>why it was first in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted,</hi> that were before. Nay, I may boldly ſay, that there was greater need for the continuance of it afterward. For the Apoſtles having ſo great Power to work Miracles, and by their Prayers to procure from God ſuch ſtrange Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions of his Pleaſure upon the contemptuous, as did fall upon <hi>Ananias</hi> and his Wife (and I doubt not but in like caſes, ſometimes upon ſome others) their <hi>Ruling and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding Authority,</hi> was not ſo neceſſary then, as it was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, when the Power to work Miracles ceaſed.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>But what ſhould I need to uſe many words in a matter ſo apparent? After the Death of the Apoſtles, and of their Aſſiſtants, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Biſhops</hi> placed by them, as is mentioned, the Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtories, and the Ancient Fathers, have kept the Regiſter of their Names, that ſucceeded ſundry of them, and ruled the Churches after them, as they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had ruled them. Whereupon they were called from all Antiquity the <hi>Apostles,</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> man's Succeſſors.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:56457:21"/>This <hi>Inequality</hi> in the Miniſtry of the Word hath been ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved and honoured by all the Ancient Fathers (none ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) by all the General Councils, that ever were held in <hi>Christendom:</hi> and by all other Men of Learning (that ever I heard of) for many Hundred years after the Apoſtles time, ſaving that <hi>Aerius</hi> the Heretick, an ambitious Perſon, grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into great rage, for that he miſſed of a Biſhoprick, which he ſued for, firſt broached the Opinion, which is now ſo currant amongſt his Scholars, that there ought to be no <hi>difference</hi> between a Biſhop and a Prieſt.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Bancroft,</hi> who ſeems to be of the ſame mind with <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravia</hi> about the Apoſtolicalneſs of the Inequality, and that he means no more,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 390.</note> ſeems clear from what he urges out of Dr. <hi>Robinſon,</hi> Dr. <hi>Reynold's</hi> and <hi>Fulk,</hi> in favour of his own Opinion, and his holding Ordination by Presbyters without a Biſhop to be valid.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>I have</hi> (ſaith <hi>Robinſon</hi>) <hi>maintained it in the Pulpit,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">D. <hi>Robinſ.</hi> Anſw. Exhib. to the Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>that the Titles of Honour, which we give to Biſhops, are no more repugnant to the Word of God, than it is for us to be called</hi> Wardens, Preſidents, Provoſts of Colleges. <hi>And in my Judgment, they may with as good Conſcience be Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours of their</hi> Dioceſs, <hi>as we being Miniſters, may be</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours <hi>of</hi> Colleges <hi>of Miniſters. Neither do I think, that this was a late deviſed Policy. For I am perſwaded, that the Angel of the Church of</hi> Epheſus, <hi>to whom S.</hi> John <hi>writeth, was one Miniſter ſet over the reſt. For ſeeing there were many</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors <hi>there, why ſhould S.</hi> John <hi>write to the</hi> Angel <hi>of the Church of</hi> Epheſus, <hi>and not rather to the</hi> Angels, <hi>if there had been no difference amongſt them? And if this <hi>Preſidency</hi> had had that Fault, which is reproved in</hi> Diotrephes, <hi>as St.</hi> Hierom <hi>proveth, that the</hi> Jews <hi>had not corrupted the Original Text before Chriſt's coming.</hi> Quod nunquam Dominus &amp; Apoſtoli, qui caetera crimina arguunt in S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ribis &amp; Phariſaeis, de hoc crimine quod erat maximum reticuiſſent: <hi>So I may ſay, neither would our Saviour, who by his Servant reproveth thoſe Diſorders, which he found in the Seven Churches, have paſſed over this great fault in ſilence. Therefore as</hi> Titus <hi>was left to Reform the Churches throughout the whole Iſland of</hi> Crete; <hi>ſo I am perſwaded that in
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:56457:21"/>other places ſome of that Order of</hi> Paſtors <hi>and</hi> Teachers, <hi>which is <hi>Perpetual</hi> in the Church, even in the time of the Apoſtles had a <hi>Prelacy</hi> amongst their Brethren, and that this <hi>Prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence</hi> is approved by our Saviour. And if we come any lower, tho' the word <hi>Epiſcopus,</hi> ſignifie that care which is required of all, and in Scripture be applied to all that have charge of Souls: yet I do not remember any one Eccleſiaſtical Writer that I have read, wherein that word doth not import a greater <hi>Dignity</hi> than is common to all Miniſters. Neither do I think that any old Writer did under the name of Biſhop, mean the <hi>Paſtor</hi> of every Pariſh.</hi>—"And thus far Dr. <hi>Robinſon,</hi> with whom, if Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Dr. <hi>Reynolds</hi> do agree, I ſee not whither the <hi>Factioners</hi> will turn them. For this Dr. in his Book againſt <hi>Hart,</hi> ſaith, <hi>That in the Church of</hi> Epheſus, <hi>tho' it had ſundry Elders and Pastors</hi> (He uſeth theſe two words in one ſignification, as by the Sentence going before is manifeſt) <hi>to guide it, yet amongſt thoſe ſundry, was there one <hi>Chief,</hi> whom our Saviour calleth the</hi> Angel <hi>of the Church, and writeth that to him, which by him the reſt ſhould know. And this is he whom afterwards in the Primitive Church, the Fathers called <hi>Biſhop.</hi> For,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>the name of <hi>Biſhop,</hi> common <hi>(before)</hi> to all Elders and Paſtors of the Church, was then by the uſual Language of the Fathers ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated to him, who had the <hi>Preſidentſhip</hi> over Elders. Thus are certain Elders reproved by <hi>Cyprian</hi> Biſhop of</hi> Carthage, <hi>for receiving to the Communion them who had faln in time of Perſecution, before the Biſhop had adviſed of it, with them and others.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Here then you have two for <hi>Oxford,</hi> touching the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the Ancient Fathers when they ſpeak of Biſhops. Now you ſhall have a <hi>Cambridge</hi> Man's Opinion, I mean Dr. <hi>Fulke,</hi> who in his Confutation of the <hi>Rhemiſh</hi> Notes upon the New Teſtament writeth thus, <hi>Amongst the Clergy for Order and ſeemly</hi> Government, <hi>there was always one <hi>Principal,</hi> to whom by long uſe of the Church the name of Biſhop or <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intendent</hi> hath been applied, which room</hi> Titus <hi>exerciſed in</hi> Creta; Timothy, <hi>in</hi> Epheſus; <hi>and others in other Places. Therefore altho' in the Scripture a</hi> Biſhop, <hi>and an Elder is of one Order, and Authority in Preaching the Word, and Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Sacraments</hi> (as <hi>Hierom</hi> doth often confeſs) <hi>yet
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:56457:22"/>in Government by ancient uſe of Speech,</hi> He <hi>is only called a</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, <hi>which is in the Scriptures called</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>or</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Rom. 12.8. 1 Tim. 5.17. Heb. 13.17. <hi>that is, <hi>Chief</hi> in Government, to whom the</hi> Ordination, <hi>or</hi> Conſecration <hi>by Impoſition of hands, was always</hi> Principally <hi>committed, and which moſt ancient Form of Government, when <hi>Aerius</hi> would take away, it was noted amongst his other Errors.</hi> Hitherto Dr. <hi>Fulke;</hi> ſo as hereby I truſt it may appear to Maſter <hi>Cart-wright</hi>'s Reproach, and to all their Shames that ſhall pretend any Authority from the ancient Fathers to impugn the Right Honourable and Lawful calling of <hi>Biſhops,</hi> not Parſons in every Pariſh, but Biſhops in their Dioceſſes and Provinces, appointed in the Apoſtles times, for the right Order and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Church of Chriſt.</q>
               </p>
               <p>So far <hi>Rancroft,</hi> who introduceth theſe three great Men's Authority to countenance the <hi>Preſidency,</hi> or <hi>Chiefty</hi> of the Biſhop over Presbyters in Government, as Apoſtolical, tho' <hi>Fulke</hi> goes no higher than the <hi>Custom</hi> of the Church, agreeing with <hi>Jewel</hi> and <hi>Whit gift,</hi> and it muſt be obſerved, that they make not the Biſhop to be a diſtinct Order from that of Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, nor deny the Presbyters to be <hi>Pastors;</hi> nor affirm the Invalidity of the Presbyterial Ordination, only that the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation by Impoſition of hands, was <hi>Principally</hi> committed to the <hi>Biſhops;</hi> and as Archbiſhop <hi>Spotiſwood</hi> reports, <hi>Bancroft</hi> held the Ordination only by Presbyters, to be valid and lawful.<note place="margin">Hiſtor. Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> lit. <hi>7. p. 514.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Spotiſwood</hi> has it in theſe words, <q>A Queſtion was moved by Dr. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Ely,</hi> touching the Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Biſhops; who, as he ſaid, muſt firſt be Ordained <hi>Presbyters,</hi> as having received no Ordination from a Biſhop. The Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> Dr. <hi>Bancroft,</hi> who was by, maintained, <hi>That thereof there was no neceſſity, ſeeing where Biſhops could not be had, the Ordination given by</hi> Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters <hi>muſt be eſteemed Lawful; otherwiſe that it might be doubted if there were any Lawful Vocation in moſt of the Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</hi> This applauded to by the other Biſhops, <hi>Ely</hi> acquieſced, and at the day and in the place appointed the three <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Biſhops were conſecrated.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:56457:22"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> The Learned <hi>Hooker,</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Bilſon</hi>'s Opinion impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially ſtated, differing but little from <hi>Saravia</hi> and <hi>Bancroft.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Learned and Judicious <hi>Hooker</hi> ſeems alſo to be of the ſame mind with <hi>Saravia</hi> and <hi>Bancroft,</hi> for in his <hi>Third Book,</hi> it's only Polity in the general, that in his Opinion is neceſſary to the ſeveral particular Churches;</p>
               <p>
                  <q>For,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. Sect. 1. p. 66. <hi>Edit.</hi> 61.</note> (ſaith he) even the ſeveral Societies of Chriſtian Men, unto every of which the name of a Church is given, with addition betokening ſeverally, as the Church of <hi>Rome, Corinth, Epheſus, England,</hi> and ſo the reſt, muſt be endued with correſpondent general <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties</hi> belonging unto them, as they are Publick Chriſtian Societies. And of ſuch Properties common unto all Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties Chriſtian, it may not be denied, that one of the very chiefeſt is <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Polity.</hi> Which word I therefore the rather chooſe becauſe the name of <hi>Government,</hi> as common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Men underſtand it in ordinary ſpeech, doth not comprize the largeneſs of that whereunto in this Queſtion it is applied. For when we ſpeak of Government, what doth the greater part conceive thereby, but only the exerciſe of <hi>Superiority</hi> peculiar unto <hi>Rulers,</hi> and Guides of others? To our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe therefore the <hi>name</hi> of <hi>Church-Polity</hi> will better ſerve, becauſe it containeth both Government, and alſo whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver beſides belongeth to the Ordering of the Church in Publick.</q> Neither is any thing in this degree more neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary than Church <hi>Polity,</hi> which is a form of Ordering Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Spiritual Affairs of the Church of God.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Hooker</hi> looks on Polity to be neceſſary to the Church, and why neceſſary, but becauſe God himſelf is the Author of it. <q>It is not poſſible that any Form of Polity, much leſs of Polity Eccleſiaſtical ſhould be good,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. §. 2.</note>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:56457:23"/>unleſs God himſelf be Author of it. <hi>Thoſe things which are not of God</hi> (ſaith <hi>Tentullian) they can have no other than God's Adverſary for their Author.</hi> Be it whatſoever in the Church of God, if it be not of God, we hate it.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But then he diſtinguiſhed between what is of God by the <hi>Law of Nature,</hi> and the <hi>Revelation</hi> made of the Divine Will in Scripture. <q>Of God it muſt be either as thoſe things ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times were, which God ſupernaturally revealed, and ſo delivered them unto <hi>Moſes</hi> for Government of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> or elſe as thoſe things which Men find out by help of that Light which God hath given them unto that end. The very Law of Nature it ſelf, which no man can deny but God hath inſtituted, is not of God unleſs that be of God, whereof God is the Author as well this latter way as the former.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The Controverſie between <hi>Hooker,</hi> and the <hi>Old Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts</hi> was, <hi>Whether any particular Form of Polity be ſo of God,</hi> that <hi>it be ſet down in Scripture?</hi> and the <hi>Noncons</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted. That no Form of Church Polity was lawful,<note place="margin">Ubi ſupra.</note> or of God, unleſs God be ſo the Author of it that it be alſo ſet down in Scripture. <hi>Hooker</hi> on the contrary, <q>That he which affirmeth Speech to be neceſſary amongſt all men throughout the World, doth not thereby import, that all men muſt neceſſarily ſpeak one kind of Language; Even ſo the <hi>neceſſity</hi> of Polity, and Regiment in all Churches may be held without <hi>holding any one certain form to be neceſſary in them all;</hi> ſo far He, who doth moreover thus reaſon with the Noncons: "You ſhould tell us plainly, whether your meaning be that it muſt be there ſet down in <hi>whole,</hi> or in <hi>Parts.</hi> For if <hi>wholly,</hi> ſhew what one form of Policy ever was ſo; your own to be ſo taken out of Scripture, you'l not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, neither do you deny that in <hi>part</hi> even <hi>this,</hi> which you ſo much oppugn is alſo from thence taken. Again, you ſhould tell us, whether only that be taken out of Scripture, which is <hi>actually</hi> and <hi>particularly</hi> there ſet down; or elſe, that alſo, which the <hi>general Principles</hi> and <hi>Rules</hi> of Scripture <hi>Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially</hi> contain. The one way you cannot ſo much as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend that all the Parties of your own Diſcipline are in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and the <hi>other</hi> way your mouths are ſtop'd, when you
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:56457:23"/>would plead againſt all other Forms beſides your own; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the general Principles are ſuch as do not particularly preſcribe any one, but ſundry, may equally be conſonant unto the general Axioms of the Scripture.</q>
               </p>
               <p>After the moſt impartial Enquiry, this Learned Man's Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment about the <hi>Polity</hi> of the Church appears to me to be thus: That tho' <hi>Polity</hi> in <hi>general be neceſſary</hi> to the Church; yet it's <hi>not neceſſary that any one compleat Form of Church Polity be in Scripture. Beſides, it's his concluſion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sect. 10. <hi>p.</hi> 82.</note> 
                  <q>That neither God's being Author of Laws, for Government of his Church, nor his committing them unto Scripture, is any reaſon ſufficient, wherefore all Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ſhould for ever be bound to keep <hi>them without change.</hi>— Again, if we did ſeek to maintain that which moſt advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageth our own Cauſe, the very beſt way for us and the ſtrongeſt againſt them, [<hi>viz.</hi> The Noncons.] were to hold even as they do, <hi>That in Scripture there must needs be found ſome particular Form of Church Polity, which God hath inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted, and which for that very cauſe belongeth to all Churches, to all times.</hi> But with any ſuch <hi>partial</hi> Eye to reſpect our ſelves, and by cunning to make thoſe things ſeem the trueſt, which are the fitteſt to ſerve our purpoſe, is a thing, which we neither like, nor mean to follow. Wherefore <hi>that,</hi> which we take to be generally true concerning the <hi>Mutabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Laws,</hi> the ſame we have plainly delivered, as being perſwaded of nothing more than we are of this, that whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be in matter of Speculation, or of Practice, no <hi>Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth</hi> can poſſibly avail the Patron and Defender long, and that things moſt <hi>Truly</hi> are likewiſe moſt <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovefully</hi> ſpoken.<note place="margin">Sect. 11. p. 90.</note>—And to make manifeſt that from Scripture, we offer not to derogate the leaſt thing that truth thereunto doth claim; in as much as by us it is willingly confeſs'd, that the Scripture of God is a Storehouſe abounding with ineſtimable Treaſures of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Knowledge in many kinds—yea, even that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Polity</hi> are not therein omitted, but taught alſo, albeit not <hi>ſo taught as thoſe other things before-mentioned.</hi> For ſo perfectly are thoſe things taught, that nothing ever can need to be added, nothing ever ceaſe to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:56457:24"/>be neceſſary: <hi>Theſe</hi> on the contrary ſide, as being of a far other nature and Quality, not ſo <hi>ſtrictly</hi> nor <hi>everlaſtingly,</hi> commanded in Scripture, but that unto the compleat Form of <hi>Church-Polity</hi> much may be <hi>requiſite, which the Scripture teacheth not, and much, which it hath taught,</hi> become <hi>unrequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite,</hi> ſometime, becauſe we <hi>need not</hi> uſe it, ſometimes alſo becauſe <hi>we cannot.</hi> In which reſpect for my own part, altho' I ſee that certain Reformed Churches, the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> eſpecially, and <hi>French</hi> have not that which beſt agreeth with the Sacred Scriptures, I mean, the Government which is by Biſhops; inaſmuch as both theſe Churches are faln under a different kind of Regiment, which to remedy, it is for the one alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether too late, and to ſoon for the other during their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Affliction and Trouble.</q>
               </p>
               <p>He adds, <q>The Matters wherein Church-Polity is converſant,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>P.</hi> 92.</note> are the Publick religious Duties of the Church, as the <hi>Administration of the Word,</hi> and <hi>Sacraments, Prayers, Spiritual Cenſures,</hi> and the like; To <hi>theſe</hi> the Church <hi>ſtands always bound.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Laws</hi> of Polity, are Laws which appoint in what <hi>manner</hi> theſe Duties ſhall be performed.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>In their performance, the <hi>first</hi> thing in <hi>Polity</hi> required is a <hi>Difference of Perſons</hi> in the Church, without which diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, thoſe Functions cannot in orderly ſort be executed. Hereupon we hold, That <hi>God's Clergy are a State,</hi> which <hi>hath been,</hi> and <hi>will be as long as there is a Church upon Earth,</hi> neceſſary <hi>by the plain Word of God himſelf.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Again, <q>where the Clergy are any great Multitude, <hi>Order</hi> doth neceſſarily require that by <hi>Degrees</hi> they be diſtinguiſhed: we hold there have ever been and ever ought to be in ſuch caſe, at leaſtwiſe <hi>two ſorts</hi> of Eccleſiaſtical Perſons, the one <hi>ſubordinate</hi> unto the other, as to the Apoſtles in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and to <hi>Biſhops</hi> always ſince, we find plainly both in Scripture, and in all Eccleſiaſtical Records other Miniſters of the Word and Sacraments have been.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Moreover, it cannot enter into any man's conceit to think it lawful, that every man which liſteth, ſhould take upon him charge in the Church; and therefore a <hi>Solemn Admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> is of ſuch neceſſity, that without it there can be no <hi>Church-Polity.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:56457:24"/>
               <p>
                  <q>Theſe are the <hi>Principal</hi> and <hi>Perpetual</hi> parts in Eccleſiaſtical Polity.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Thus much in the <hi>Third Book,</hi> where he looks on Church-Polity in the general and ſome ſpecial parts thereof, ſuch as a diſtinction between <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Presbyters,</hi> and a <hi>Subordination</hi> of the Presbyter to the Biſhop to be agreeable to the Word of God, <hi>but no compleat form of Church Polity to be found in the Scripture, neither are all the Laws of God concerning the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church <hi>Immutable,</hi> and <hi>Everlaſting:</hi>
                  </hi> We muſt go to the Seventh Book for a more diſtinct account of the <hi>Office</hi> of a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and the difference between him and a Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter; where 'tis thus:</p>
               <p>
                  <q>But to let go the Name <hi>[Biſhop]</hi> and to come to the very Nature of that <hi>thing,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 7. Sect. 2. pag. 5.</note> which is thereby ſignified in all kinds of Regiment, whether Eccleſiaſtical or Civil: as there are ſundry Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions Publick, ſo likewiſe great <hi>Inequality</hi> there is in the ſame Operations, ſome being of <hi>Principal</hi> reſpect, and therefore not fit to be dealt in by every one to whom Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Actions, and thoſe of Good Importance, are notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding well, and fitly enough committed. From hence have grown thoſe different <hi>Degrees</hi> of Magiſtrates, or Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Perſons, even <hi>Eccleſiastical,</hi> as well as Civil. Amongſt <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Perſons therefore <hi>Biſhops</hi> being <hi>Chief</hi> ones, a Biſhop's Function muſt be defined by that wherein his <hi>Chiefty</hi> conſiſteth.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>A Biſhop is a Miniſter of God, unto whom with permanent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, there is given not only Power of adminiſtring the Word and Sacraments,</hi> which Power other Presbyters have, but alſo <hi>a further Power to Ordain Eccleſiaſtical Perſons, and a Power of Chiefty in Government over Presbyters, as well as Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; A Power to be by way of Juriſdiction, a Pastor even to Pastors themſelves.</hi> Thoſe things incident unto the Biſhop's Office, which do properly make him a Biſhop, cannot be common unto him with other <hi>Pastors.</hi> Now even as <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors,</hi> ſo likewiſe Biſhops being <hi>Principal Paſtors,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at <hi>Large;</hi> or elſe with <hi>Restraint. At Large,</hi> when the ſubject of their Regiments is indefinite, and not tied to any certain Place; Biſhops with <hi>Reſtraint,</hi> are they whoſe Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:56457:25"/>over the Church is contained within ſome definite lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal compaſs, beyond which compaſs their Juriſdiction reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not; ſuch therefore, we always mean, when we ſpeak of that Regiment by Biſhops, which we hold a thing moſt <hi>Lawful, Divine</hi> and <hi>Holy</hi> in the Church of Chriſt.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But what doth He mean by <hi>Chiefty</hi> in Government? In an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer unto this, he tells us how far the old <hi>Noncons</hi> went in the grant of an <hi>Inequality,</hi> and how much further He goeth. <q>They which cannot brook (ſaith he) the Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riority which Biſhops have,<note place="margin">Sect. 3. <hi>p.</hi> 6.</note> do, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves, admit that ſome kind of <hi>Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> and <hi>Inequality</hi> there may be <hi>lawfully</hi> amongſt Miniſters. Inequality touching Gifts and Graces they grant—Again, a <hi>Priority of Order</hi> they deny not, but that there may be, yea, ſuch a Priority as maketh one man amongſt many a Principal Actor in thoſe things, whereunto ſundry of them muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily concur, ſo that the ſame be admitted only <hi>during the time of ſuch Actions, and no longer.</hi>—The <hi>Inequality</hi> they complain of is, That <hi>one Miniſter of the Word and Sacraments ſhould have a permanent Superiority above another, or in any ſort a</hi> Superiority <hi>of Power Mandatory,</hi> Judicial, <hi>and <hi>Coercive</hi> over other Miniſters.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Thus you ſee how far the old <hi>Noncons</hi> could go, and no farther, and immediately after, he tells us how much farther the Church of <hi>England</hi> at that time went; for, ſays he, <q>By <hi>Vs</hi> on the contrary ſide, <hi>Inequality,</hi> even ſuch <hi>Inequality,</hi> as unto Biſhops, being Miniſters of the Word and Sacraments, is granted a <hi>Superiority Permanent</hi> above Miniſters; yea, a Permanent Superiority of Power <hi>Mandatory, Judicial</hi> and <hi>Coercive</hi> over them is maintained a thing <hi>Allowable, Lawful,</hi> and <hi>Good.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>In two things <hi>Hooker</hi> differs from the old <hi>Noncons.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>They</hi> make the Superiority, or Priority of Order to be but <hi>Temporary: Hooker</hi> makes it <hi>Permanent.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>They</hi> deny the Biſhops having a Power over other Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, that is, <hi>Mandatory, Judicial,</hi> and <hi>Coercive: Hooker</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms it.</item>
               </list>
               <p>There is one thing more to be enquired into, <hi>viz.</hi> whether He grants to Presbyters the <hi>Pastoral</hi> Office? He calls them
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:56457:25"/>
                  <hi>Paſtors,</hi> and in his very definition of a Biſhop, makes the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop to be a <hi>Paſtor</hi> of <hi>Paſtors</hi> (and of Presbyters) and he calls the Biſhop but <hi>Principal</hi> Paſtor, and makes him to have a <hi>Chiefty</hi> in Regiment above Presbyters; as if he held that the Presbyter had ſome, tho' not ſo great a ſhare in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; and out of <hi>Auſtin,</hi> 
                  <q>That a Biſhop is a <hi>Presbyter Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior,</hi> and in ſeveral places a <hi>Biſhop</hi> is of a <hi>Higher Degree</hi> than a Presbyter.</q> And altho' in his <hi>Third Book,</hi> he makes the Epiſcopal Office to be a part of Church Polity perpetual, as tho' the Epiſcopacy had been <hi>de jure Divino,</hi> and <hi>Immutable;</hi> yet in this <hi>Seventh Book,</hi> in clearing the ſenſe of St. <hi>Jerom,</hi> he is expreſly againſt the <hi>Immutability</hi> and <hi>Unchangeableneſs</hi> of the Biſhop's Superiority; as if he held it to be <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> in the ſame manner Biſhop <hi>Downame</hi> doth, of whom hereafter.</p>
               <p>The words of St. <hi>Hierom,</hi> on which he puts his own Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are theſe. <hi>As therefore Presbyters do know, that the</hi> Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom <hi>of the Church makes them ſubject to the</hi> Biſhop, <hi>which is ſet over them; ſo let Biſhops know, that</hi> Cuſtom <hi>rather than the</hi> Truth <hi>of any</hi> Ordinance <hi>of the</hi> Lord's <hi>maketh them greater than the rest, and that with Common Advice they ought to Govern the Church.</hi> To this <hi>Hooker</hi> replies, <q>To clear the ſenſe of theſe words therefore: Laws, which the Church from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning univerſally hath obſerv'd were ſome delivered by Chriſt himſelf, with a <hi>Charge to keep them to the worlds End,</hi> as the Law of Baptizing, and adminiſtring the Holy Euchariſt; ſome brought in <hi>afterwards</hi> by the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> yet not without the ſpecial Direction of the Holy Ghoſt, as occaſions did ariſe. Of this ſort are thoſe <hi>Apoſtolical Orders,</hi> and <hi>Laws,</hi> whereby Deacons, Widows, Virgins were firſt appointed in the Church.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>This Anſwer to St. <hi>Hierom</hi> ſeemeth dangerous, I have qualified it as I may by addition of ſome words of reſtraint; yet I ſatisfie not my ſelf in my Judgment it would be altered. <hi>Now whereas</hi> Jerom, doth term the Government of Biſhops by reſtraint, an <hi>Apoſtolical Tradition,</hi> acknowledging thereby the ſame to have been the Apoſtles own Inſtitution, it may be demanded how theſe two will ſtand together; namely, That the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> by Divine Inſtinct, ſhould be as <hi>Jerom</hi> confeſſeth, the Authors of that Regiment, and yet the <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom</hi>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:56457:26"/>of the Church be accounted (for ſo by <hi>Jerom</hi> it may ſeem to be in this place accounted) the <hi>Chiefeſt</hi> prop that upholdeth the ſame? <hi>To this we anſwer,</hi> That as much as the whole Body of the Church, hath <hi>Power</hi> to <hi>ALTER</hi> with general conſent, and upon neceſſary occaſions, even the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Laws of the Apoſtles, if there be no Commandment to the contrary, and it manifeſtly appears to her, that change of times have clearly taken away the very reaſon of God's firſt Inſtitution as by ſundry Examples may be moſt clearly proved; what Laws the Univerſal Church might change, and doth not; if they have long continued without any <hi>alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration;</hi> it ſeemeth that St. <hi>Jerom</hi> aſcribeth the continuance of ſuch <hi>Poſitive Laws,</hi> tho' inſtituted by God himſelf, to the <hi>Judgment</hi> of the <hi>Church.</hi> For they which might <hi>Abrogate a Law,</hi> and do not, are properly ſaid to Uphold, to Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh it, and to give it <hi>Being.</hi> The Regiment therefore, whereof <hi>Jerom</hi> ſpeaketh, being <hi>Poſitive,</hi> and conſequently not abſolutely neceſſary, but of a <hi>Changeable Nature,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is no Divine Voice, which in expreſs words forbiddeth it to be changed, He might imagine both that it came by the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> by very Divine Appointment <hi>at the firſt,</hi> and notwithſtanding after a ſort, ſaid to ſtand in force, rather by the <hi>Cuſtom</hi> of the Church, chooſing to continue it, than by the neceſſary conſtraint of any Commandment from the Word, requiring <hi>Perpetual Continuance</hi> thereof.</q> Thus <hi>Hooker,</hi> who a little after ſays, <q>Biſhops albeit they may avouch with Conformity of Truth, that their Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity hath thus deſcended even from the very Apoſtles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; yet the <hi>Abſolute and Everlaſting continuance</hi> of it they cannot ſay that any Commandment of the Lord doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn; And therefore muſt acknowledge, that the Church hath Power by Univerſal Conſent upon urgent cauſe to <hi>take it away,</hi> if thereunto ſhe be conſtrained through the <hi>Proud, Tyrannical, and unreformable Dealings of her Biſhops.</hi>— Wherefore leſt Biſhops forget themſelves, as if none on Earth had <hi>Authority</hi> to touch <hi>their States,</hi> let them continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally bear in mind, that it is rather the force of Cuſtom, whereby the Church, having ſo long found it good to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue under the Regiment of her vertuous Biſhops, doth
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:56457:26"/>ſtill uphold, maintain, and honour them in that reſpect, than that any ſuch <hi>true,</hi> and <hi>Heavenly Law</hi> can be ſhewed, by the Evidence whereof it may of a Truth appear, That the Lord himſelf hath appointed Presbyters for ever to be under the Regiment of Biſhops, in what ſort ſoever they behave themſelves.</q>
               </p>
               <p>This Anſwer of the Learned <hi>Hooker</hi> makes it manifeſt, that tho' he held the <hi>Inſtitution</hi> of Epiſcopal Superiority to be <hi>Apoſtolical;</hi> yet he was not of Opinion that 'twas <hi>unalterable.</hi> And altho' he held it Apoſtolical, yet ſuggeſts as if there had been a Church Government inſtituted <hi>before</hi> the Epiſcopal took place. <q>The Apoſtles of our Lord (ſays he) did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording unto thoſe Directions, which were given them from above, erect Churches in all ſuch Cities as received the Word of Truth, the Goſpel of God: All Churches by them erected, received from them the <hi>ſame Faith,</hi> the <hi>ſame Sacraments,</hi> the <hi>ſame Form of Publick Regiment.</hi> The Form of Regiment eſtabliſhed by them at <hi>firſt</hi> was, That the Laity or People ſhould be ſubject unto a College of <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Perſons,</hi> which were in every ſuch City appointed for that purpoſe. Theſe in their Writings they term ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time <hi>Presbyters,</hi> ſometimes <hi>Biſhops.</hi>—That in proceſs of time the Apoſtles appointed under them Biſhops, of an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Superiour above Presbyters;</hi> the cauſe wherefore they did appoint under themſelves ſuch Biſhops as were not eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where at the firſt, is ſaid to have been thoſe <hi>Strifes</hi> and <hi>Contentions,</hi> for remedy whereof, whether the Apoſtles alone did conclude of ſuch a Regiment, or elſe <hi>they,</hi> together with the whole Church, judging it a fit and needful Policy, did agree to receive it for a <hi>Cuſtom,</hi> no doubt but being eſtabliſhed by them, on whom the Holy Ghoſt was poured in ſo abundant meaſure for the ordering of Chriſt's Church, it had either <hi>Divine Appointment</hi> beforehand, or <hi>Divine Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation</hi> afterwards.</q>
               </p>
               <p>This paſſage of <hi>Hooker,</hi> moves me to think he very much agreed with his moſt Reverend Metropolitan, Archbiſhop <hi>Whit gift,</hi> who vehemently aſſerts an actual change of Church Government in the Primitive Times, as well as the changea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs of it in all Ages of the Church. There are other
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:56457:27"/>intimations in this Learned Author, which oblige me to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that the Church of <hi>England</hi> was not in his days come to a ſteady Reſolution either about the Nature of a Particular Church <hi>infimae ſpeciei,</hi> or of the whole belonging to the Epiſcopal Office.</p>
               <p>Touching the Nature of a Particular Church of the loweſt Rank, whether Parochial or Dioceſan, was not much with him; for ſpeaking of the Diſſimilitudes which in ſome reſpects are found to be between the preſent Biſhops, and the Biſhops in the Primitive times, he grants that many things there are in the State of Biſhops,<note place="margin">Lib. 7. Sect. 2. p. 4.</note> which the times have changed, ſaying, <q>That many a Parſonage at this day is larger than ſome ancient Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks were.—To Men that have any part of Skill, what more evident and plain in Biſhops than that Augmentation and Diminution in their Precincts, Allowances, Privileges, and ſuch like, do make a Difference indeed; but no Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Difference between one Biſhop and another.</q> But a Learned Nonconformiſt aſſures us, <hi>That he ſhall try among other things,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Treatiſe of Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy,</hi> chap. 5. pag. 49.</note> 
                  <hi>whether the Name of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprick will make a Parſonage and a Dioceſs to be</hi> Ejuſdem ſpeciei, <hi>and whether Magnitude do not make a ſpecifick Difference between the Sea, and a Rivulet or a Glaſs of Water, or between a Ship and a Nutſhell.</hi> And I may add, that if there be no Eſſential Difference between a Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick no larger than a Parſonage, and a Dioceſan Biſhoprick, the Controverſie between the Church of <hi>England</hi> and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of Nonconformiſts, may touching Church Government, be determined by ſuch Condeſcenſions made by the <hi>Church</hi> to the Diſſenters, as are ſhort of an <hi>Eſſential</hi> Alteration to Epiſcopacy. Let there be as many Biſhopricks as there are conſiderable Parſonages, or Pariſhes indowed, and a Proviſion made for the Presbyters who are to aſſiſt the Biſhops in the Government of theſe little Churches, and a Superiority of the Biſhop above the Presbyters, or a <hi>Chiefty</hi> in the Regiment will be no longer a bone of Contention.</p>
               <p>As to what belongs to the Epiſcopal Function as Different from the Presbyters, it's held by ſome that <hi>Ordination, Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> and <hi>Juriſdiction,</hi> are proper to it; Let us ſee then
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:56457:27"/>
                  <hi>Hooker</hi>'s Judgment for the firſt Point, <q>There may be (ſaith he) ſometimes very juſt and ſufficient Reaſons to all Ordination made without a Biſhop.<note place="margin">Lib. 7. Sect. 14. pag. 37.</note> The whole Church Viſible being the <hi>true-Original-Subject</hi> of all Power, it hath not ordinarily al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed any other than Biſhops alone to Ordain: Howbeit, as the ordinary courſe is ordinarily in all things to be obſerved, ſo it may in ſome Caſes not unneceſſary, that we decline from the ordinary wayes.</q> The Power of Ordination is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated to the Biſhop by the Churches Allowance and no otherwiſe, and the ſame Church allowing Presbyters to Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain, their Ordination is Good, ſo that Ordination is not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to a Biſhop <hi>quarto modo,</hi> for it doth not <hi>Convenire</hi> to him <hi>ſemper &amp; ſoli;</hi> and therefore he adds in the next Page, <q>
                     <hi>That we are not ſimply without Exception to urge a lineal Deſcent of Power from the Apoſtles by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſucceſſion of Biſhops in every Effectual Ordination.</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <note place="margin">Lib. 7. Sect. 6. pag. 14.</note>
               </p>
               <p>For the ſecond Point, <q>I make not Confirmation part of that Power which hath always belonged only unto Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops; becauſe in ſome places the <hi>Custom</hi> was that Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters might alſo Confirm in the abſence of a Biſhop.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Touching the laſt Point, How Biſhops together with Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters have uſed to Govern the Churches under them:<note place="margin">Lib. 7. Sect. 7. pag. 17.</note> 
                  <q>It is by <hi>Zonaras</hi> (ſaith he) ſomewhat plainly and at large declared, That the Biſhop had his Seat on high in the Church above the Reſidue, which were preſent; that a number of Presbyters did always there <hi>Aſſiſt him,</hi> and that in the Overſight of the People, thoſe Presbyters were after a ſort the Biſhops <hi>Coadjutors.</hi> The Biſhops and Presbyters who together with him governed the Church, are for the moſt part by <hi>Ignatius</hi> joyntly men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd; They are Counſellors and Aſſiſtants of the Biſhop.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Thus this great Man grants: That tho' Government in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral be neceſſary to the Church, yet no one particular kind of Government is ſo; That the Scriptures do not make the Epiſcopal Government unalterable; That the Power of confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Orders, is not by a Divine Law ſo appropriate to the Biſhops, that in no caſe an Ordination by Presbyters can be
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:56457:28"/>valid; That the Church Viſible is the <hi>true-Original-Subject</hi> of all Power, and can alter the Government of the Church; That Confirmation is not eſſential to the Office of a Biſhop; That Presbyters have a ſhare in the Government; That the Difference between the Biſhop and Presbyter is in the Degree, the Biſhop having a Chiefty in the Government, and Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters the Biſhops Coadjutors, Aſſiſtants, Adviſers and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors.</p>
               <p>The Learned <hi>Bilſon,</hi> afterwards Biſhop of <hi>Winchester,</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Controverſie between the Old Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts and the Church of <hi>England,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Perpetual Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Church.</note> expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth himſelf in theſe words. <q>Thus far we joyn, That to prevent Diſſention and Confuſion, there muſt needs,<note place="margin">Epiſtle to the Reader.</note> even by God's Ordinance, be a Preſident, or Ruler of every Presbytery; which Concluſion becauſe it is warranted by the Grounds of Nature, Reaſon and Truth, and hath the Example of the Church of God, <hi>before, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder</hi> and <hi>after</hi> the Law, we accept as Irrefutable, and lay it as the <hi>Ground-work of all that enſueth.</hi> But whether this <hi>Preſidentſhip</hi> did in the Apoſtles times, and by their Appointment go round by courſe to all the Paſtors and Teachers of every Presbytery, or were by Election committed to One choſen as the fitteſt to ſupply that Place ſo long as He diſcharged his Duty with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out blame, that is a main point betwixt us.—</q>
               </p>
               <p>But more particularly he adds, <q>In the Apoſtles I obſerve four things needful for the firſt Founding and Erecting of the Church, and four other Points that muſt be <hi>Perpetual</hi> in the Church of Chriſt. Theſe are <hi>the Diſpenſing the Word, Adminiſtring the Sacraments, Impoſing of Hands, and guiding the Keys to ſhut or open the Kingdom of God.</hi> The firſt two muſt be general to all Paſtors and Presbyters of Chriſt's Church; but ſo do not the other two.—I have largely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated and made it plain, as well by the Scriptures as by other Ancient Writers paſt all Exception, there have always been ſelected ſome of greater Gifts than the Reſidue to ſucceed in the Apoſtles Places, to whom it belonged, both to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate the Presbyters of each Church, and to take the ſpecial <hi>Charge</hi> of Impoſition of Hands, and this their <hi>Singularity</hi> in
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:56457:28"/>
                     <hi>Succeeding,</hi> and <hi>Superiority</hi> in Ordaining, have been obſerved from the Apoſtles times as the <hi>Peculiar</hi> and <hi>Subſtantial</hi> marks of Epiſcopal Power and Calling.</q>
               </p>
               <p>"The Power of the Keys, and Right to Impoſe Hands (by which he always means the Power to Ordain Miniſters, and Excommunicate Sinners) belong unto the Biſhop, diſtinguiſhing "him from a Presbyter.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>What the things are,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chap.</hi> 12. <hi>p.</hi> 208.</note> which muſt abide for ever in the Church I ſhewed before; it ſhall ſuffice now to rehearſe them; namely, <hi>Power to Preach the Word,</hi> and <hi>Adminiſter the Sacraments,</hi> the <hi>Right uſe of the Keys,</hi> and <hi>Impoſition of Hands.</hi>—Theſe four parts for Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vities ſake, I often reduce to two Branches, which are <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> comprizing in <hi>Doctrine</hi> the Dividing of the Word and Diſpenſing of the Sacraments, and referring the reſt, I mean, the <hi>Publick uſe of the Keys,</hi> and <hi>Impoſition</hi> of <hi>Hands to the Diſcipline,</hi> or <hi>Regiment</hi> of the Church.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>The Diſcipline and Government of the Church, (I mean the <hi>Power of the Keys,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ch.</hi> 12. <hi>p.</hi> 213.</note> and <hi>Impoſing of Hands</hi>) are two parts of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick Authority, which muſt remain in the Church for ever. Theſe Keys are double, the <hi>Key</hi> of <hi>Knowledge,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to the <hi>Word,</hi> the <hi>Key</hi> of Power referred to the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;</hi> Some late Writers by urging the one, aboliſh the other; howbeit, I ſee no ſufficient Reaſon to countervail the Scriptures and Fathers, that Defend, and Retain both. The <hi>Key</hi> of Knowledge muſt not be doubted of, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour in expreſs words nameth it. <hi>Wo be to you Interpreters of the Law,</hi> for ye have taken away the <hi>Key of Knowledge.</hi> The <hi>Key of Power</hi> ſtandeth in theſe words of Chriſt to <hi>Peter, I will give thee the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> and <hi>whatſoever thou ſhalt bind on Earth; ſhall be bound in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> &amp;c. And likewiſe to all his Apoſtles, <hi>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ye bind on Earth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>P.</hi> 218.</note> &amp;c.—It reſteth in this place to be conſidered to whom thoſe Keys were committed, whether <hi>Equally to all Presbyters,</hi> or <hi>Chiefly</hi> to Paſtors, and Biſhops. The like muſt be done for <hi>Impoſition</hi> of Hands, whether that alſo pertain'd <hi>indifferently</hi> to all, or <hi>ſpecially</hi> to Biſhops.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:56457:29"/>
               <p>This is the State of the Point in Controverſie; namely, <hi>Whether the Power of the Keys,</hi> and <hi>that of Impoſition of Hands</hi> belong <hi>Equally</hi> and <hi>Indifferently</hi> to all Presbyters, and <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops;</hi> or whether they do not belong <hi>chiefly</hi> and <hi>ſpecially</hi> to Biſhops: But whether the one or the other be affirm'd, 'twill unavoidably follow, that theſe Powers in a ſenſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to both. Thus much is ſuppoſed in the very ſtate of the Queſtion, which is not, whether theſe Powers do not at all belong to Presbyters, but whether they do belong ſo much to Presbyters as unto Biſhops, ſo that the holding them, to belong <hi>chiefly</hi> and <hi>ſpecially</hi> unto the Biſhop, implies, that they do, tho' in a leſſer <hi>Degree,</hi> belong unto <hi>Presbyters.</hi> They appertain both to the Presbyter and Biſhop, but not <hi>Equally,</hi> to the Biſhop <hi>chiefly</hi> and <hi>ſpecially.</hi> Now Conform hereunto the Learned <hi>Bilſon</hi> ſaith, <q>The Biſhop then, or <hi>Preſident of the Presbyters</hi> (for <hi>I ſtand not on Names,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ch.</hi> 14. p. 293.</note> 
                     <hi>while I diſcuſs their</hi> Powers) is by Chriſt's own Mouth pronounced to be the Angel of the Church; that is, the <hi>Chief <hi>Steward</hi>
                     </hi> over God's Houſhold, and Overſeer of his Flock.—And touching the Presbyter's Power,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>P.</hi> 319.</note> He adds, That at firſt the Presbyters ſate with the Biſhop as <hi>Aſſeſſors,</hi> and <hi>Conſenters,</hi> before Synods undertook ſuch Cauſes; But after, when once Councils began to have the Hearing of Grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, then ſate the Presbyters with the Biſhop only, as <hi>Behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> and <hi>Adviſers</hi> of his Judgment—The Private uſe of the Keys in appointing Offenders upon the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging their Sins,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>P.</hi> 317.</note> for a time to forbear the Lord's Table, we deny not to Presbyters.</q>
               </p>
               <p>However the Ambiguity of the Name of <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity of many things incident, and appertinent both to Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Presbyters, urged him to lay down certain Peculiar Marks and Parts of the Biſhop's Office, whereby they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Diſtinguiſhed from Presbyters, and never Confounded with them, either in Scriptures, Councils or Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. <q>There were many Prerogatives (ſays he) appropriate unto the Biſhop,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ch.</hi> 13. p. 244.</note> by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Canons and Cuſtom of the Church, ſuch as <hi>Reconciling of Penitents, Confirmation of Infants,</hi> and others
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:56457:29"/>that were Baptized, by <hi>Laying on their Hands, Dedication of Churches,</hi> &amp;c. But the things <hi>Proper</hi> to Biſhops, which might not be Common to Presbyters, were <hi>Singularity</hi> in <hi>Succeeding,</hi> and <hi>Superiority</hi> in Ordaining. Theſe two, the Scriptures and Fathers reſerve <hi>only</hi> to Biſhops, they never Communicate them to Presbyters. The <hi>Singularity</hi> of one Paſtor in every place preſerveth the Peace and Unity of the Churches, and ſtoppeth Schiſms and Diſſentions, for which Cauſe they were firſt Ordained by the Apoſtles.<note place="margin">246.</note> This is a certain Rule to Diſtinguiſh Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops from Presbyters, the Presbyters were many in every City, of whom the Presbytery conſiſted. Biſhops were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways <hi>Singular,</hi> that is, one in a City, and no more, except another intruded (which the Church of Chriſt counted a Schiſm) or elſe an <hi>Helper</hi> were given in reſpect of extream and feeble age; in which caſe the Power of the latter ceaſed in the preſence of the former. And this <hi>Singularity</hi> of one Paſtor in each place deſcended from the Apoſtles and their Scholars in all the famous Churches of the World by a <hi>Perpetual Chair of Succeſſion,</hi> and doth to this day continue; but where Abomination or Deſolation, I mean, Hereſie or Violence, interrupt it.—The ſecond aſſured ſign of Epiſcopal Power, is <hi>Impoſition of Hands</hi> to Ordain <hi>Presbyters</hi> and <hi>Biſhops,</hi> for as <hi>Pastors</hi> were to have ſome to <hi>aſſiſt</hi> them in their Charge, which were <hi>Presbyters,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>P.</hi> 248.</note> ſo were they to have others to <hi>ſucceed</hi> them in their Places, which were <hi>Biſhops.</hi> And this Right by Impoſing Hands to Ordain Presbyters and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops in the Church of Chriſt; was at firſt derived from the Apoſtles unto Biſhops, and not unto Presbyters; and hath for theſe fifteen Hundred Years without Example or Inſtance to the contrary, till this our Age, remained in Biſhops, and not in Presbyters.—<hi>Jerom,</hi> where he retcheth the Presbyters Office to the uttermoſt, of purpoſe to ſhew, that he may do by the Word of God as much as the Biſhop, he excepteth this <hi>One</hi> Point as unlawful for <hi>Presbyters</hi> by the Scriptures. <hi>Quid facit Exceptâ Ordinatione, Epiſcopus, quod Presbyter non facit?</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:56457:30"/>
               <p>And whereas 'tis objected, That Impoſition of Hands was by the Presbytery, he anſwereth out of <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> that by the word <hi>Presbytery</hi> in that place of Scripture muſt be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood <hi>Biſhops,</hi> not Presbyters, becauſe Presbyters in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles time did not impoſe Hands on a Biſhop.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>All that we can ſay for the Power of Biſhops above Presbyters out of the Scriptures,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>P.</hi> 299.</note> is this: That the Holy Ghoſt by the mouth of St. <hi>Paul</hi> hath given the Biſhop of each Place, Authority to <hi>Ordain</hi> ſuch as be worthy, to <hi>examine</hi> ſuch as be faulty, and <hi>Reprove</hi> and <hi>Diſcharge</hi> ſuch as be <hi>guilty</hi> either of Unſound Teaching, and Offenſive Living. Thus much he ſaith to <hi>Timothy,</hi> and to <hi>Tite,</hi> and in them to their Succeſſors, and to all other Biſhops of Chriſt's Church for ever.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The Power of Ruling the People is not <hi>ſolely,</hi> but <hi>chiefly</hi> in the Biſhop.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 304.</note> 
                  <q>My meaning (ſays he) is ſoon underſtood. You eſtabliſh one <hi>Chief</hi> in your <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteries</hi> by God's Eſſential and Perpetual Ordinance, to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute that which you decree, whom you call a <hi>Preſident.</hi> How far I joyn with you, you ſhall quickly perceive. <hi>To avoid Tumults</hi> and <hi>Diſſentions,</hi> God hath Authorized One in each Place and Church, Able, to have and maintain a Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery, who with <hi>Paſtoral,</hi> and <hi>Fatherly Moderation,</hi> ſhould Guide as well the <hi>Presbyters</hi> that <hi>aſſiſt him,</hi> as the <hi>People</hi> that are <hi>Subject to him,</hi> according to the Laws of God and <hi>Man;</hi> the Execution whereof is <hi>Chiefly</hi> committed to his Charge that is the Leader, and Overſeer of the reſt: whom we call a Biſhop. His Power I call a <hi>Moderation,</hi> and not a <hi>Domination;</hi> becauſe the Wiſdom of God hath likewiſe allowed and provided Chriſtian means as well to <hi>Bridle</hi> him from wrongs, as to <hi>Direct</hi> him in Doubts.</q> And whereas the Nonconformiſt tells him, that this is right the Power which they give to their Presbyteries; his Anſwer is, <q>Did you not put <hi>Lay-Men</hi> inſtead of Paſtors to be Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and make them Controulers, where they ſhould be but Adviſers, your Presbyteries might have ſome uſe in the Church of God; tho' far leſs now than when they firſt began. And amongſt the many uſes of Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>P.</hi> 307.</note> the Biſhop is Poſitive, "That at firſt, leſt
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:56457:30"/>the Biſhops <hi>only will</hi> ſhould be the Rule of all things in the Church, the <hi>Government</hi> of the Church was ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portioned that neither the Presbyters ſhould do any thing without their Biſhop; nor the Biſhop diſpoſe Matters of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance without his Presbytery.</q>
               </p>
               <p>He diſtinguiſheth between the <hi>Private</hi> uſe of the Keys in Refuſing to give the Lord's Supper unto the Impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, and the <hi>Publick uſe</hi> of the Keys, whereby the obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Perſon is excluded from all Fellowſhip of the Faithful, as well Sacred as Civil; The firſt belongs to the Presbyter, the laſt was by the Church of God allowed always and only to Biſhops. So in another place.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 320.</note>— <q>For our parts, tho' we take the Power of the Keys to be <hi>Common</hi> to all that have Paſtoral Charge of Souls, in <hi>their Degree,</hi> yet to avoid the infinite Showers of Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, which would overflow all Churches and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes, and the intolerable Quarrels and Brabbles that would enſue, if every Presbyter might Excommunicate without the Biſhops conſent and Licence, we praiſe the Wiſdom of God's Church in ſuffering no Inferiour to Excommunicate without the Biſhop's conſent and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Thus far this Learned Biſhop, who urgeth the ſingula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Succeſſion and Superiority in Ordination, to be the Eſſential Marks of a Biſhop, as he differs from a Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, yet not diveſting the Presbyter of all Governing Power in the Church of Chriſt. His Pleading for a Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periority of Power in the Biſhop, carries in it the grant of a leſſer degree of the ſame Power, as belonging to the Presbyter, and the denying Presbyters the Exerciſe of this Power without the conſent of the Biſhop, is but by an Eccleſiaſtical Conſtitution, ſuch as that which makes the Reconciling Penitents, and Confirmation to be rather Peculiar to the Biſhop for the Honour of his Calling, than for any Neceſſity of God's Word.</p>
               <p>Thus I have gone through the Principal Writers about Church Government that were in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Reign; namely, <hi>Alley</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Exeter, Pilkington</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſme,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:56457:31"/>Jewel</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> and <hi>Whitgift,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> who held, that according to the Scriptures, there was no Difference between a Presbyter and a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, that in Scripture account their Office and Powers were the ſame, and that the Apoſtles did not leave be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them any one kind of Church Government to be obſerved throughout all the Churches at all times. Theſe were followed by Dr. <hi>Coſins,</hi> Dr. <hi>Low,</hi> and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Bridges.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Learned <hi>Willet,</hi> in his <hi>Synopſis Papiſmi,</hi> a Book Publiſhed at leaſt three or four times in Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beths</hi> Days, and afterwards by King <hi>James</hi> his Special Command, doth in moſt things agree with the Biſhops, but now mention'd, and being more particular than they, affirming out of <hi>Jerom,</hi> That <hi>Confirmation</hi> and <hi>Ordination</hi> were appropriated to the Biſhop, rather for the Honour of their Prieſthood, and the Peace of the Church, than by neceſſity of any Law; the ſame he ſaith of the <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction</hi> of the Church; adding, That anciently there were no diſtinct <hi>Conſecrations of Biſhops.</hi> The thing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he may be ſuppoſed to differ from them is, that an <hi>Inequality</hi> amongſt the Presbyters, and the Preſidency of ſome one above the other for Orders ſake, he holds to be <hi>Apostolical;</hi> but herein differs not from the Old Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts.</p>
               <p>After theſe, I have given the Judgments of <hi>Saravia,</hi> Archbiſhop <hi>Bancroft,</hi> the Judicious <hi>Hooker,</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon;</hi> who affirm, the Government of the Church to be <hi>Apostolical.</hi> Tho' formerly 'twas eſteemed dangerous to the <hi>Civil</hi> Government to hold, that Church Government muſt <hi>now</hi> be the ſame 'twas in the Apoſtles days; yet it's look'd on by theſe, as what <hi>ought</hi> to be. The Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Church with them is a Divine and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical Inſtitution, but not <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nalterable. Bilſon,</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, ſays, it is <hi>Perpetual,</hi> and yet Biſhop * <hi>Downame,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Defence of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, <hi>p. 26.</hi>
                  </note> who moſt willingly and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly profeſſeth to conſent in Judgment with Him,<note place="margin">P. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> doth ſolemnly Declare in theſe words, <q>That
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:56457:31"/>although he holds the Calling of Biſhops in reſpect of their firſt Inſtitution, to be an <hi>Apoſtolical,</hi> and ſo a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Ordinance, yet that he doth not maintain it to be <hi>Divini Juris,</hi> as intending thereby, that it is <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, Perpetually,</hi> and <hi>Immutably</hi> neceſſary, as though there could not be a True Church without it.</q> And within a few Pages after this, He declares his Opinion to be the ſame with King <hi>James</hi>'s; who doth ſay, That <hi>it is granted to every Chriſtian King, Prince, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth to</hi> preſcribe <hi>to their Subjects, that</hi> Outward Form <hi>of Eccleſiaſtical Regiment, which may ſeem beſt to agree with the Form of their Civill Government; but ſo as they ſwerve not at all from the Grounds of Faith, and True Religion.</hi> This, ſaith <hi>Downame,</hi> maketh not againſt the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Biſhops, as I maintain it—Tho' I hold the Government-Epiſcopal to be of Apoſtolical and Divine Inſtitution; yet not as <hi>Generally, Perpetually</hi> and <hi>Immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly</hi> neceſſary: He doth not hold it neceſſary in all Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, nor in all Ages, but to be changeable by Man; and if herein He and <hi>Bilſon</hi> accord, the Perpetuity <hi>Bilſon</hi> is for, will admit of a Change.</p>
               <p>But whether <hi>Downame</hi> gives us <hi>Bilſon</hi>'s Notion, when he ſtates his own, I will not contend, nor is it need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful I ſhould; It's enough to my purpoſe, that the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence he placeth between a Biſhop and Presbyter is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in <hi>Degree,</hi> that <hi>Confirmation,</hi> and <hi>Excommunication</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long unto Presbyters; and that <hi>Bilſon</hi>'s Biſhop differs more from the Biſhops by Law Eſtabliſhed than from the Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſt Pariſh Presbyters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bancroft</hi> profeſſes to agree with <hi>Robinſon, Reynolds,</hi> and <hi>Fulk,</hi> who differed not from the Old Nonconformiſts, and <hi>Hooker</hi> never thought the Government of the Church to be in all Places and Ages neceſſarily the ſame; nor did he look on Biſhops to be of a Different <hi>Order</hi> from Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, but to be of the ſame Order, differing only in <hi>Degree,</hi> the Biſhop having only a <hi>Chiefty</hi> of Power in the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:56457:32"/>Church, nor did any Great Men of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, null the Miniſtry or Church State of the Reformed either in <hi>Scotland</hi> or beyond the Seas; They held their Churches to be true Churches, and their Government to be ſuch as agreed with the General Rules of God's Word, and tho' ſome eſteemed the Ordination only by Presbyters to be defective, yet did not judge it to be Invalid, but admitted thoſe who had their Ordination only from Presbyters abroad, to Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Promotions, on no other terms than their Subſcribing the Articles of Religion, which concern the Faith, and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of the Sacraments only.</p>
               <p>Theſe Sentiments, which our firſt Reformers entertain'd about Epiſcopacy are ſuch, as would (if the Government of the Church be at this time Fram'd accordingly) contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute much to the Peace of the Church, and Healing our Diviſions; and ſeeing they are moſt admirably copied out unto us in the Learned Archbiſhop <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi>'s <hi>Reduction of Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy,</hi> I will with ſome Notes preſent it to the Reader's more Deliberate Conſideration.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:56457:32"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:56457:33"/>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:56457:33"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Archbiſhop <hi>Uſher's</hi> Reduction of Epiſcopacy with ſome Notes on it.
<q>The Reduction of Epiſcopacy unto the Form of Synodical Government received in the <hi>Ancient Church;</hi> propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the year <hi>1641.</hi> as an Expedient for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of thoſe Troubles, which afterwards did ariſe about the matter of Church-Government.</q>
               </head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Epiſcopal and Presbyterial Government Conjoyned.</head>
                  <p>
                     <q>BY Order of the Church of <hi>England</hi> all Presbyters are charged to <hi>adminiſter the Doctrine and Sacraments,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">The Book of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</note> and <hi>the Diſcipline of Chriſt, as the Lord hath commanded,</hi> and as <hi>this Realm hath received the ſame;</hi> And that they might the better underſtand what <hi>the Lord had commanded</hi> therein,<note place="margin">Ibid. ex Act. <hi>20.27, 28.</hi>
                        </note> the Exhortation to St. <hi>Paul,</hi> to the Elders of the Church of <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> is appointed to be read unto them at the time of their Ordination; <hi>Take heed unto your ſelves and to all the Flock among whom the Holy Ghoſt hath made you Overſeers to</hi> Rule <hi>the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of God,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> ſo taken in Mat. 2.6. Revel. 12.5. &amp; 19.15.</note> 
                        <hi>which he hath purchaſed with his Blood.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <div type="notes">
                     <head>Notes.</head>
                     <p>Thus it was in the <hi>Old Book</hi> of Ordering <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Deacons;</hi> but on the Reſtauration of <hi>Charles</hi> II. there were ſuch <hi>Altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> made in the Books of Common Prayer and Ordering Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Prieſts and Deacons, as do plainly ſhew, that tho' here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore the Presbyters had Power to Rule, yet now they have none.</p>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:56457:34"/>
                     <p>In the <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> 14 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. it is Declared, <q>That the King's Majeſty (according to his Declaration of 25. <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> 1660.) granted his Commiſſion under the Great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> to ſeveral Biſhops, and other Divines, to Review the Book of Common Prayer, and to prepare ſuch <hi>Altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and <hi>Additions,</hi> as they thought fit to offer: And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards the Convocations of both the Provinces of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> and <hi>York,</hi> being by his Majeſty called and Aſſembled, (and now ſitting) his Majeſty hath been pleaſed to Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize and require the Preſidents of the ſaid Convocations, and other the Biſhops, and Clergy of the ſame, to Review the ſaid Book of Common Prayer, and the Book of the Form and Manner of the making and Conſecrating of Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons; And that after mature Conſideration, they ſhould make ſuch <hi>Additions,</hi> and <hi>Alterations</hi> in the ſaid Books reſpectively, as to them ſhould ſeem meet and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient; And ſhould Exhibit, and Preſent the ſame to his Majeſty in Writing, for his further Allowance, or Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; ſince which time, upon full and mature Delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, they, the ſaid Preſidents, Biſhops, and Clergy of both Provinces, have accordingly Reviewed the ſaid Books, and have made <hi>ſome Alterations,</hi> which they think fit to be inſerted to the ſame, and have Exhibited and Preſented the ſame unto his Majeſty in Writing. All which his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty having duly conſidered, hath fully Approved and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the ſame, and recommended to this preſent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Books thus <hi>altered,</hi> were by this Parliament confirm'd and eſtabliſhed, and the <hi>Alterations</hi> ſuch as make the Office of the Presbyter quite another thing than it was before; for tho' in the old Book of Ordering Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons, the Reading unto the Presbyters at the time of their Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.27, 28. did put it out of Doubt, that the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters were veſted with the Paſtoral Office, having Power gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven 'em to <hi>Rule</hi> the Church; In the <hi>new Book</hi> this Exhortation is removed from the Presbyters Ordination unto the Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Biſhops, thereby manifeſtly Evincing the <hi>Paſtoral Power</hi> to be taken from the Presbyter, and feated with the Biſhop only, and accordingly the name <hi>[Paſtor]</hi> which was in the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:56457:34"/>old Book given unto the Presbyter, is in the new omitted, and in ſeveral places the word [<hi>Curate,</hi> or <hi>Prieſt</hi>] ſubſtituted in its ſtead; and whereas, in the old Book, the Presbyter was admitted [to the <hi>Miniſtry of Prieſthood</hi>] in the new it's to the <hi>[Order]</hi> and Miniſtry of Prieſthood, thereby making Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood an <hi>Order</hi> diſtinct from thoſe of <hi>Deaconſhip</hi> and <hi>Epiſcopacy.</hi> In the Conſecrating of Biſhops in the <hi>Collect,</hi> to ſhew what they mean by Biſhop more than formerly, it's added by way of Explication to all <hi>Biſhops [the Paſtors of thy Church]</hi> and in the Prayer for the Biſhop [<hi>Almighty God,</hi> &amp;c.] in the old Book 'twas, <hi>Repleniſh him ſo with thy Truth— that He may faithfully ſerve thee in this Office to the Edifying of thy Church;</hi> in the new it is <hi>[to the well Governing thy Church.]</hi> And when the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop and other Biſhops preſent, do lay their Hands on the Elected, and according to the old Book, were to ſay, [<hi>Receive the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> &amp;c.] in the new it's added [<hi>for the Office and Work of a Biſhop <hi>Now</hi> committed unto thee by the Impoſition of our Hands in the Name of the Father,</hi> &amp;c.]</p>
                     <p>Thus the Alterations by Law eſtablſhed do clearly ſhew, that both the <hi>Name</hi> and <hi>Office</hi> of a <hi>Paſtor</hi> is taken from the Presbyter, and transferr'd over to the Dioceſan, who alone hath the Power of Ordering Prieſts and Deacons, and of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning or Ruling the Church; whence it follows, that as there is but <hi>One Paſtor in a Dioceſs,</hi> there is but one Church; That all Pariſh-Aſſemblies are but parts or parcels of this One ſingle Church, under the Conduct and Government only of the Dioceſan Biſhop, their only Paſtor; That all Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions by Presbyters are of no greater Validity than thoſe by Deacons or Lay-men; and therefore altho' Ordination is no more to be repeated than Baptiſm, yet thoſe who have had their Ordination only by Presbyters, muſt be Ordained again, or not admitted unto any Benefice, nor allowed the Exerciſe of the Prieſtly Office, nor be eſteemed <hi>Lawful</hi> Prieſts; ſo that as there is a vaſt Difference between Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and <hi>Charles</hi> the Second's, ſo between Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Law, and King <hi>Charles</hi>'s. <q>Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Act runs thus, <hi>That every Perſon under the Degree of a Biſhop, which doth or ſhall pretend to be a Prieſt or Miniſter of God's Holy Word and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, by reaſon of <hi>any other Form</hi> of Inſtitution, Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:56457:35"/>or Ordering, than the Form now uſed in the Reign of our moſt Gracious Soveraign Lady—ſhall—declare his Aſſent, and ſubſcribe to all the Articles of Religion,</hi> which only concern the Profeſſion of the true Chriſtian Faith, and the Doctrine of the Sacraments, compriſed in a Book Entituled, Articles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> [viz. 39 <hi>Articles</hi>]—upon pain, that every <hi>ſuch Perſon which ſhall not ſubſcribe, ſhall be</hi> (ipſo facto) deprived, and all his Eccleſiaſtical Promotions ſhall be void, as if he had been naturally dead.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>King <hi>Charles</hi> his Law is thus, <q>That no Parſon, who now is Incumbent, and in the Poſſeſſion of any Parſonage or Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefice, and who is not in Holy Orders by <hi>Epiſcopal Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> or ſhall not be before the ſaid Feaſt-day of St. <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholomew,</hi> Ordained Prieſt or Deacon, ſhall have, hold, or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy any Parſonage with Cure—but ſhall be utterly diſabled, and <hi>ipſo facto deprived of the ſame, and all his Eccleſiaſtical Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions ſhall be void, as if he had been naturally dead.</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>Touching Perſons ordained by any other Form than the <hi>Epiſcopal,</hi> a Subſcription to the Articles was ſufficient by 13 <hi>Eliz. c.</hi> 12. to Qualifie them for Spiritual Promotion, and <hi>Whitting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s, whoſe Ordination was only by Presbyters abroad, was eſteemed good, and he enjoyed his Benefice to the day of his death, as <hi>Traverſe,</hi> in his <hi>Supplication</hi> to the <hi>Council,</hi> affirms: but tho' the Articles be ſubſcribed unto by one having only an <hi>Ordination</hi> by <hi>Presbyters,</hi> he muſt be ordained by the Biſhop, or not admitted to any Eccleſiaſtical Promotion; or if admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, he is <hi>ipſo facto</hi> deprived; and whoever conſults the Book of <hi>Ordering Presbyters,</hi> will find that the whole of it plainly declares, that the former Odination of the Perſon thus re-or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, was invalid and null, and that till now he was never of the Presbyters Office; for the Ordination of one never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ordained, and the Ordination of him who was formerly ordain'd by Presbyters, is the ſame.</p>
                     <p>Whether I am right in theſe my Sentiments, I appeal to the Right Reverend and Reverend Biſhops and others of the Dignified Clergy, who, with the greateſt importunity, are deſired to declare their Judgments in this Matter.</p>
                     <p>To know what the Government of the Church of <hi>England</hi> is, that is by <hi>Archbiſhops, Biſhops;</hi> and <hi>what</hi> is the <hi>Office of a
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:56457:35"/>Presbyter,</hi> what that of a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> is a matter of extraordinary importance.</p>
                     <p>If it be the ſame it was in <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth and Queen <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi>'s days, which is the ſame with what the Learned <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> was for, the greateſt Bone of Contention between the <hi>Cons</hi> and <hi>Noncons</hi> will be removed farther. Every Pariſh-Presbyter will be granted to be a <hi>Paſtor, veſted with a Right to Rule the Church,</hi> (from whence, ſaith the Learned Archbiſhop, the name of <hi>Rector</hi> alſo was given unto him at firſt) <hi>and to adminiſter the Diſcipline of Chriſt, as well as to diſpenſe the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Sacraments,</hi> and the difference between the Biſhop and the Presbyter to be only in <hi>Degree,</hi> and not in <hi>Order,</hi> as this Learned Primate ever held, as he ſaith in an Anſwer to an abuſive Report, that went abroad of him: <q>I have ever de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared my Opinion to be (ſaith he) That <hi>Epiſcopus &amp; Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter gradu tantum differunt, non Ordine,</hi> and conſequently that in places where Biſhops cannot be had, the Ordination by Presbyters ſtandeth <hi>valid;</hi> and Dr. <hi>Bernard</hi> in his <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madverſions</hi> on the Archbiſhop's Opinion, aſſerts, That in this Judgment he was not <hi>ſingular;</hi> Dr. <hi>Davenant,</hi> that Pious and Learned Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> conſents with him in it,<note place="margin">Determinat. Q. <hi>42.</hi>
                           </note> produceth the Principal of the Schoolmen, <hi>Gulielmus Pariſienſis, Gerſon, Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Epiſcopatus non eſt Ordo praecise di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctus à Sacerdotio ſimplici, &amp;c. non eſt alia poteſtas Ordinis in Epiſcopis quàm Presbyteris, ſed ineſt modo perfectiori.</hi> And declares it to be the general Opinion of Schoolmen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Primate ſaith, That in Caſes of <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> where Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops cannot be had, the Ordination by Presbyters ſtandeth valid: Biſhop <hi>Davenant</hi> concurs with him alſo, and produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth the Opinion of <hi>Richardus Armathanus</hi> (one of this Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate's Predeceſſors, and one of the moſt Learned men in his time) to be accordingly. To which divers others might be added, as in ſpecial Dr. <hi>Field</hi> ſometimes <hi>Dean</hi> of <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter,</hi> in his Learned Book of the <hi>Church,</hi> where this Judgment of the Primate,<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 39. <hi>&amp; lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 27.</note> and the Concurrence of Biſhop <hi>Davenant</hi>'s, is large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confirmed. But that Book Entituled, <hi>The Defence of the Ordination of the Miniſters of the Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:56457:36"/>beyond the Seas,</hi> maintained by Mr. <hi>Archdeacon Maſon</hi> againſt the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> (who wrote alſo a Defence of Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy, and of the Miniſtry of the Church of <hi>England</hi>) is fuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently known, and I have been aſſur'd it was not only the Judgment of Biſhop <hi>Overal,</hi> but <hi>that he had a Principal hand in it.</hi> He produceth many Teſtimonies, the <hi>Maſter of the Sentences,</hi> and moſt of the Schoolmen, <hi>Bonaventure, Thomas Aquinas, Durand, Dominicus Soto, Richardus Armachanus, To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatus, Alphonſus à Caſtro, Gerſon, Caniſius</hi> to have affirmed the ſame; and at laſt quotes <hi>Medina,</hi> a Principal Biſhop of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> who affirm'd, That <hi>Jerom, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe, Auguſtine, Sedulius, Primaſius, Chryſoſtome, Theodoret, Theophylact</hi> were of the ſame Judgment alſo. In a word, if the <hi>Ordination</hi> of Presbyters in ſuch places where Biſhops cannot be had, were not <hi>valid,</hi> the late Biſhops of <hi>Scotland</hi> had a hard Task to maintain themſelves to be <hi>Biſhops,</hi> who were not Prieſts, for their <hi>Ordination</hi> was no other.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>What Dr. <hi>Bernard</hi> mentions about the Archbiſhop's diſlike of the late Prerbyterians here in <hi>England,</hi> is not ſo much againſt their Exerciſing the Power, as the <hi>Manner</hi> of their Exerciſe, they did not add to the Impoſition of Hands [<hi>Receive the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> &amp;c.] nor ſo much as theſe words [<hi>Be thou a faithful Diſpenſer of the Word of God and of his Holy Sacraments,</hi> &amp;c.] Moreover in the Cloſe to the Reduction the <hi>Primate</hi> and Dr. <hi>Holdſworth</hi> aver, That the Suffragans, mentioned in the ſecond Propoſition, may lawfully uſe the Power both of Juriſdiction and Ordination according to the Word of God and the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the Ancient Church, who yet are but the <hi>Chorepiſcopi,</hi> of no other Order than the Presbyters, as hereafter I ſhall prove. A Declaring therefore thus much, namely, That the Presbyter is of the ſame Order, veſted with the Power both of Order and Juriſdiction, and an entruſting them with the Exerciſe thereof, as in the ſecond Propoſition, will contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute very much towards a well Eſtabliſhed <hi>Comprehenſion;</hi> And in Requital it's not to be doubted, but the <hi>Latitudinarian Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſt,</hi> of which there are a great number in this Kingdom, will readily yield to the <hi>Preſidency</hi> of one Presbyter, for the ſake of Union, to be over them, and cloſe with what the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop further adds.</p>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:56457:36"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Archbiſhop.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <q>Of the many <hi>Elders,</hi> who in common <hi>Ruled</hi> the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> there was one <hi>Preſident,</hi> whom our Saviour in his Epiſtle to this Church, in a peculiar manner ſtileth <hi>the Angel of the Church of Epheſus:</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Revel. 1.</note> and <hi>Ignatius</hi> in another Epiſtle written about twelve years after unto the ſame Church, calleth the <hi>Biſhop</hi> thereof. Betwixt the Biſhop and the Presbytery of that Church, what an Harmonious Conſent there was in the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of the Church-Government, the ſame <hi>Ignatius</hi> doth fully declare, by the <hi>Presbytery,</hi> which St. <hi>Paul,</hi> underſtanding the <hi>Community of the reſt of the Presbyters</hi> or <hi>Elders,</hi> who then had a hand,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.14.</note> not only in the Delivery of the Doctrine and Sacraments, but alſo in the Adminiſtration of the <hi>Diſcipline</hi> of Chriſt: for further proof of which, we have that known Teſtimony of <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his general Apology for Chriſtians.<note place="margin">Ibidem etiam Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones, Caſtigationes, &amp; cenſura Divina; nam &amp; judicatur magno cum pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere, ut apud certos de Dei conſpectu, ſummum ſummum<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> futuri Judicii praejudicium eſt, ſi quis ita deliquerit, ut à Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municatione Orationis, &amp; Conventus &amp; omnis ſancti Commercii relegetur: prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident probati qui<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niores, honotem iſtum non pretio, ſed Teſtimonio adepti. <hi>Tertul. Apologet. c.</hi> 39.</note> 
                           <hi>In the Church are uſed Exhortations, Chaſtiſements, and Divine Cenſure; for Judgment is given with great advice, as amongſt thoſe, who are certain they are in the ſight of God, and it is the chiefeſt foreſhewing of the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which is to come, if any man have ſo offended, that he be baniſhed from the Communion of Prayer, and of the Aſſembly, and of all Holy Fellowſhip. The <hi>Preſidents</hi> that bear <hi>Rule</hi> therein, are certain approved <hi>Elders,</hi> who have obtained this Honour, not by <hi>Reward,</hi> but by good Report,</hi> who were no other (as he himſelf intimates elſewhere) but thoſe from whoſe hands they uſed to receive the Sacrament of the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt.</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Nec de aliorum mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus quàm Praeſidentium ſumimus. <hi>Id. de Corona Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litis, c.</hi> 3.</note>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <q>For with the Biſhop, who was the <hi>Chief</hi> Preſident (and therefore ſtiled by the ſame <hi>Tertullian</hi> in another place<note n="*" place="margin">Dandi quidem Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſini habet jus Summus Sacerdos, qui eſt Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus, dehinc Presbyteri &amp; Diaconi. <hi>Id. de Baptiſ. c.</hi> 17</note> 
                           <hi>Summus Sacerdos</hi> for diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:56457:37"/>ſake) the reſt of the Diſpenſers of the Word and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments joyned in the <hi>Common Government</hi> of the Church; and therefore, where in Matters of Eccleſiaſtical Judicature, <hi>Cornelius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> uſed the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Form of <hi>gathering together the Presbytery;</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Omni actu ad me per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lato placuit contrahi Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterium. <hi>Cornel. apud Cypr. Epiſt.</hi> 46.</note> of what perſons that did conſiſt, <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſufficiently declareth, when he wiſheth them to read his Letters to <hi>the flouriſhing Clergie,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Florentiſſimo illic clero tecum praeſidenti. <hi>Cypr. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt.</hi> 55. <hi>ad Cornel.</hi>
                           </note> 
                           <hi>which there did Preſide</hi> or Rule <hi>with him.</hi> The preſence of the <hi>Clergie</hi> being thought to be ſo requiſite in matters of <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal Audience,</hi> that in the fourth Council of <hi>Carthage,</hi> it was conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,<note place="margin">Ut Epiſcopus nullius cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam audiat abſ<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> praeſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia Clericorum ſuorum, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lioquin irrita crit ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia Epiſcopi, niſi Clerico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum praeſentia confirme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. <hi>Concil. Carthag.</hi> IV. <hi>cap.</hi> 23.</note> 
                           <hi>That the Biſhop might hear no mans cauſe without the Preſence of the Clergie, and that otherwiſe the Biſhop's Sentence ſhould be void, unleſs it were confirm'd by the Preſence of the Clergie;</hi> which we find alſo to be inſerted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Canons of<note n="*" place="margin">Except. Egberti, <hi>c.</hi> 43.</note> 
                           <hi>Egbert,</hi> who was Archbiſhop of <hi>York</hi> in the <hi>Saxon</hi> times, and afterwards in the Body of the <note n="‖" place="margin">15. <hi>q.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> nullus.</note> 
                           <hi>Canon Law</hi> it ſelf.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <q>True it is, that in our Church this kind of <hi>Presbyterial Government</hi> hath been long diſuſed, yet ſeeing it ſtill pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth, that every <hi>Paſtor</hi> hath a Right to <hi>Rule</hi> the Church (from whence the name of <hi>Rector</hi> alſo was given at firſt unto him) and to Adminiſter the <hi>Diſcipline of Chriſt,</hi> as well as to Diſpenſe the <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Sacraments,</hi> and the Reſtraint of the Exerciſe of that Right, proceedeth only from the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom <hi>now received in this Realm,</hi> no man can doubt, but by another Law of the Land, this hindrance may be well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved; And this <hi>Ancient</hi> Form of Government by the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Suffrages of the Clergy, might be reviv'd again; and with what little ſhew of <hi>Alteration,</hi> the <hi>Synodical</hi> Conventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Paſtors of every Pariſh might be accorded with the Preſidency of the Biſhops of each Dioceſs and Province,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:56457:37"/>the indifferent Reader may quickly perceive by the peruſal of the enſuing Propoſitions.</q>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="1" type="part">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <q>In every Pariſh the <hi>Rector,</hi> or incumbent <hi>Paſtor,</hi> together with the Church-Wardens and Sides-men, may every Week take notice of ſuch as live ſcandalouſly in that Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who are to receive ſuch ſeveral Admonitions and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs as the Quality of their Offence ſhall deſerve: And if by this means they cannot be reclaimed, they may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the next <hi>monthly Synod,</hi> and in the mean time de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barr'd by the <hi>Paſtor</hi> from Acceſs unto the Lord's Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</q>
                  </p>
                  <div type="notes">
                     <head>Notes.</head>
                     <p>The Name <hi>Rector,</hi> which ſignifieth a Governour or Ruler, was anciently given in common to Prelates, Biſhops, Abbots, and Pariſh-Presbyters, but chiefly to the Pariſh-Prieſt or Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that had Cure of Souls, as <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> FRESENE</hi> obſerves out of the <hi>Lombardian</hi> Laws,<note place="margin">Rectores Eccleſiarum Praelati, Epiſcopi, Abba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes Parochiarum Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri in lege <hi>Longob. l.</hi> 3. <hi>tit.</hi> 1. <hi>Sect.</hi> 42. <hi>tit.</hi> 10. <hi>Sect.</hi> 4. In Capitularibus <hi>Carol. M. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>tit.</hi> 75. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Maxime Rector Eccleſiae qui vulgo Curio, ſeu Curitus, ut in Charta <hi>Alaman.</hi> 43. apud <hi>Goldaſtum. D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> FRESNE Gloſ. in verb. Rector.</hi>
                        </note> and <hi>Charles Great</hi>'s Capitulars, and the <hi>Almaine</hi> Charter.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Lindwood</hi> alſo in his <hi>Provincial Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution,</hi> declares the ſame;<note place="margin">Communiter loquendo [per ipſorum Rectorum] intelligas de Rectoribus Eccleſiarum Parochialium. Poteſt etiam intelligi de omni Praelato Eccleſiae. <hi>Lindw. de Conſu. c.</hi> nullus ver. nullus Rector, &amp; ver. Ipſorum Rectorum.</note> and<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Vid.</hi> Cowel's Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>in</hi> Verb. Rector.</note> 
                        <hi>Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell</hi> affirms, That in our <hi>Common Law,</hi> Rector <hi>Eccleſioe Parochialis,</hi> is he that hath the Charge or Cure of a Pariſh-Church; <hi>qui tantum Jus in Eccleſia Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochiali habet, quantum Proelatus in Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiâ Collegiatâ,</hi> That a <hi>Parſon</hi> and Rector were anciently the ſame: So<note n="†" place="margin">Lib. <hi>4.</hi> Tract. <hi>5.</hi> ca. pri.</note> 
                        <hi>Bracton, Sciendum quod</hi> Rectoribus <hi>Eccleſiarum Parochialium competit Aſſiſa, qui inſtitui ſunt per Epiſcopos &amp; Ordinarios, ut</hi> Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae. <hi>Lindwood</hi> holds the ſame: For,<note place="margin">De Praeſump. c. ne Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra, Sect. quod ſi. ver. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonatus.</note> as he avers, That in <hi>aliquibus locis
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:56457:38"/>
                           <hi>Rectores</hi> Eccleſiarum vocantur</hi> Perſonae, ſo he is as expreſs, that <hi>haec dictio</hi> Perſonae, <hi>eſt vulgare</hi> Anglicorum, <hi>&amp; ponitur pro <hi>Rectore.</hi> Wats</hi> in his <hi>Gloſſary,</hi> obſerving the Word <hi>Perſonatus</hi> in <hi>Otho</hi>'s <hi>Conſtitutions,</hi> delivered by <hi>Matthew Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> in <hi>Henry</hi> the Third's days,<note place="margin">In quibus locis omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus accipitur pro <hi>Recto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> quam <hi>a Parſonage</hi> vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camus.</note> and in Pope <hi>Innocent</hi>'s Letter to the Abbot of St. <hi>Albans,</hi> aſſures us, that it ſignifies a <hi>Rectory,</hi> and the <hi>Perſona,</hi> or <hi>Parſon,</hi> is the <hi>Rector.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">De Confeſ Perſonar. &amp; Cleric. Quod in quodan. ver. Perſona.</note> 
                        <hi>John de Athon</hi> in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary on <hi>Otho</hi>'s <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> on the Word <hi>Perſonae,</hi> ſaith, <hi>(i.e.) Rectores; loqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur enim ſecundum</hi> vulgare <hi>Anglicorum. Lindwood,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">It is alſo clear from anciently acknowledged riſh-Church; and therefore</note> that <hi>Vicars Perpetual</hi> were to be <hi>Rectors</hi> or <hi>Governours</hi> of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Conſtitution of <hi>Simon Lang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> where it's Ordain'd, That <hi>Nullus Rector</hi> preſume to ſell thoſe Tithes of his Church not yet received,<note place="margin">Nullus Rector, ſupple vel Vicarius, ubi eſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuus <hi>De Conſuet. c.</hi> Nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Rector, ver. Nullus Rector.</note> before the Annunciation of the Bleſſed <hi>Mary,</hi> it muſt be underſtood alſo of <hi>Vicars Perpetual:</hi> And <hi>John de Athon</hi> is very large in diſcuſſing, and poſitive in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining it:<note place="margin">Credo reſpectu Recto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Vicarium dici Inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulatum, reſpectu vero a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liorum nominare debet Rectorem. <hi>Conſtit. Otho. de Inſtit. Vicarior. verb. ad. Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car.</hi>
                        </note> For, ſaith he, out of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent</hi>'s <hi>Extrav.</hi> though if you conſider a Vicar <hi>Perpetual,</hi> with reſpect to his Rector, whoſe Vicar he is, he is not called a <hi>Rector;</hi> yet if compared with others, he is a <hi>Rector.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>It's then very plain, That anciently every Parſon and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car <hi>Perpetual,</hi> were called <hi>Rectors</hi> or Governours; and why? but becauſe they were veſted with a Right to Govern their Churches, notwithſtanding which, it cannot now be inferr'd, that thoſe who ſtill bear the Name of <hi>Rector,</hi> are Governours of the Church; For the ancient Conſtitution of the Church is not only altered, whereby Pariſh Presbytens, Parſons, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors and Vicars <hi>Perpetual,</hi> have loſt all their ancient Power of Ruling; but by reaſon of Impropriations, <hi>mere Laicks,</hi> ever ſince the Statute of Diſſolution, that took away Appropriations
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:56457:38"/>from the Church, have been <hi>Parſons</hi> and <hi>Rectors,</hi> but not Rulers of the Church.</p>
                     <p>Sir <hi>Henry Spelman</hi> very Learnedly doth prove,<note place="margin">Of Tithes, <hi>c. 29.</hi>
                        </note> That after the Appropriations, the Parſonage ſtill continues Spiritual, as well in the Eye of the Common Law, as of the Canon Law: for if it became Temporal by Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priation, then were it within the Statute of <hi>Mortmaine,</hi> and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited by that Act; and as it continues <hi>Spiritual,</hi> it muſt be made to a Spiritual Perſon, and not Temporal, Spiritual Things and Spiritual Men being Co-Relatives, that cannot in Reaſon be divorced. However, we ſee that, <hi>de facto,</hi> Lay-men are poſſeſs'd of theſe Spiritual Impropriations, and thereby are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Parſons and Rectors; and the Eccleſiaſtical Incumbent, who hath the Cure of Souls, is his Vicar, who, although ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Ancient Dialect, might be called <hi>Rector,</hi> when compared with others, yet not with reſpect to the Lay-man, the Parſon or Rector of the Pariſh: He that hath the Parſonage or Rectory, is the Parſon or Rector; and that is the Lay-Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriator.</p>
                     <p>Beſides, according to what hath been offer'd in the firſt <hi>Note,</hi> it's plain, that now no Governing Power is left with the Pariſh-Presbyter; He is not only denied the Exerciſe of ſuch a Power, but diverſted of the Power it ſelf; and if any of 'em have the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>Rector</hi> left'em, it's <hi>vox &amp; praeterea nihil.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>If in this I am miſtaken, the Fathers of the Church are humbly deſired to tell the World ſo; but whether I am miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken or no, the reſtoring the Pariſh-Presbyters to the ancient Power of Rectors, and the Exerciſe of it, will be a great ſtep towards the healing our Breaches, eſpecially if what the ancient <hi>Chorepiſcopi,</hi> whom I muſt again mention, who were but Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, enjoyed, may be allowed them: Of whom, more in my Notes under the next Propoſition.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>
                     <q>Whereas by a Statute in the Six and Twentieth Year of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth (revived in the Firſt Year of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi>)<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ch.</hi> 14.</note> 
                        <hi>Suffragans</hi> are appointed to be erected in Twenty Six ſeveral places of this Kingdom, the Number of them might very well be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed unto the Number of the ſeveral <hi>Rural Deanries,</hi> into
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:56457:39"/>which every Dioceſ is ſub-divided; which being done, the <hi>Suffragan</hi> ſupplying the place of thoſe who in the ancient Church were called <hi>Chorepiſcopi,</hi> might every Month aſſemble a Synod of all the <hi>Rectors,</hi> or incumbent <hi>Paſtors</hi> within the Precinct, and according to the <hi>major part</hi> of their Voices, conclude all Matters that ſhall be brought into Debate before them.</q>
                  </p>
                  <div type="notes">
                     <head>Notes.</head>
                     <p>The <hi>Suffragans</hi> appointed to be erected in the Twenty Sixth Year of <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, were to be conſecrated by the Archbiſhop, and Two other Biſhops, or Suffragans, and by them admitted to the Epiſcopal Dighity; but yet were not to uſe, have, or execute any Juriſdiction or Epiſcopal Power or Authority within their ſaid Sees, nor within any Dioceſs or place of this Realm, or elſewhere within the King's Dominions, but only ſuch Juriſdiction, Power and Authority as ſhall be <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed</hi> and <hi>Limited</hi> to them, to take, do, and execute by a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from the Biſhop of the See in which he is a Suffragan; nor were they to uſe any Juriſdiction, Ordinary, or Epiſcopal Power otherwiſe, nor longer time than <hi>limited</hi> by ſuch Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
                     <p>Theſe were the Suffragans appointed to be erected by <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, who though Conſecrated and Ordained to the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopal Dignity, yet muſt exerciſe no other Epiſcopal Power than was delegated to 'em by the Dioceſan's Commiſſion, which was a very precarious and uncertain thing. This Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Archbiſhop doth therefore move, that inſtead of this ſort of <hi>Suffragan,</hi> we might have men to ſupply the place of the ancient <hi>Chorepiſcopi,</hi> who were not at firſt under ſuch Limitations, tho without Epiſcopal Conſecrations, they were veſted with the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Authorities of <hi>City</hi> Biſhops; and that they might be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd to the Number of <hi>Rural Deanries.</hi> A motion, which if cloſed with by the Church of <hi>England,</hi> would, no doubt, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this part of the Controverſie about the Government of the Church, heal the Diviſion; and the <hi>Church</hi> in her Conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcention herein, would conform unto an ancient Practice of the Church, recogniz'd by all to be common, at leaſt in the <hi>Third Century:</hi> For though Biſhop <hi>Parker</hi> will not admit them to have been in the Church till the <hi>Fourth Century,</hi> becauſe no mention
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:56457:39"/>of 'em in any Record before the Council of <hi>Ancyra</hi> ſat, which (notwithſtanding what <hi>Angelocrator</hi> avers, who would have it be after the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> becauſe <hi>Vitalis,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>och,</hi> the firſt named amongſt the Biſhops that ſate in it, was not made a Biſhop before the Year 331.) it's generally held to be in the Year 314. And it's not eaſie to imagine, that theſe <hi>Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repiſcopi</hi> could in ſo ſhort a time ſpring out of Nothing, and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive to that height they were at <hi>An.</hi> 314, or as others 308. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, there were ſeveral <hi>Chorepiſcopi</hi> in the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> that was but Ten or Twelve Years after this; and <hi>Rabanus Maurus</hi> Seven or Eight Hundred Years ago produced an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical Argument to prove, that they were as ancient as City Biſhops: <q>For (ſays he) in the Book which <hi>Damaſus</hi> the firſt wrote on the deſire of <hi>Hierome</hi> the Presbyter, it's affirm'd, That <hi>Linus</hi> and <hi>Cletus,</hi> by the Commandment of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> Ordained Presbyters, who yet ſucceeded him not in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical Chair, <hi>Clemens</hi> being by the Order of this bleſſed Apoſtle, made his Succeſſor: And (ſaith <hi>Maurus</hi>) from hence it is, that the <hi>Chorepiſcopi,</hi> as I ſuppoſe, had their Riſe, and have ever ſince continued in the Catholick Church, who being Ordained, by their own Biſhops, by their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment did Ordain Presbyters, Deacons, and other Inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or Degrees, and diſcharge all the other Offices belonging to Prieſthood. So far <hi>Rabanus.</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>They were but <hi>Presbyters,</hi> and yet did Ordain and Exerciſe Epiſcopal Juriſdiction.</p>
                     <p>That they did at firſt exerciſe <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Juriſdiction in the Countrey, is clear from the 13th Canon of the Council of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyra,</hi> which according to <hi>Zonaras</hi> and <hi>Balſaman</hi> is thus:</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Exactly tranſlated by <hi>Gentianus Hervetus,</hi> Chorepiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos <hi>non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>icere Presbyteros, vel Diaconos Ordinare, ſed ne<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> 
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbis Presbyteros, niſi cum literis ab Epiſcopo permiſſum fuerit, in aliena Parochia.</hi> This, as Biſhop <hi>Parker</hi> confeſſeth, is the moſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect Copy; That <hi>it ſhall not be lawful for Countrey Biſhops to Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain Presbyters or Deacons, nor yet for City Presbyters, without the permiſſion of their Biſhop.</hi> Only he omits this material Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>[in another Pariſh or Dioceſs];</hi> which Words do greatly
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:56457:40"/>confound the Learned Archbiſhop of <hi>Paris, De Marca,</hi> who will therefore have the <hi>Greek</hi> Copy cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected:<note place="margin">Quid eſt illud in <hi>aliena Paraeciâ,</hi> ac ſi Chorepiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pis libera eſſet Ordinatio. Presbyteri in ſua Paraecia ſine literis. <hi>De Marc. de Concord. Sacer. &amp; Imper. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 14. <hi>Sect.</hi> 1, 2.</note> 
                        <hi>What is the meaning of theſe words,</hi> (ſaith he) <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienae paroicia?</hi> as <hi>if it had been lawful for-the <hi>Chorepiſcopi</hi> to Ordain Presbyters in their own Precincts, without the leave of the City-Biſhop.</hi> He will therefore have it, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>in unaquâque Paraecia,</hi> which agrees not only with the Tranſlation of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onyſius Exiguus,</hi> but with an ancient Copy in the Library at <hi>Oxford,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>P.</hi> 140.</note> as <hi>Thorndike</hi> of the <hi>Right of the Church,</hi> reports, who can make no Senſe of <hi>De Marca</hi>'s Emendation: <q>For, ſays he, can the Reading of the laſt words, <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, ſeem probable to Reaſonable Perſons? What Conſequence of Senſe is there in ſaying, <hi>unleſs Licenſe be granted in <hi>every Pariſh?</hi>
                           </hi> Which is plain, when it is ſaid, That the City-Presbyters do nothing in the Pariſh, that is in the Countrey or Dioceſs, without Authority by the Biſhop's Letters.</q> So far <hi>Thorndike,</hi> who is for the blotting <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> out of <hi>Zonara</hi>'s and <hi>Balſanion</hi>'s Copy, and <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> out of the Copy at <hi>Oxford,</hi> and who agrees with <hi>De Marca,</hi> in adding <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> to the Canon, and prefers <hi>Iſidore Mercator</hi>'s Tranſlation before the Original <hi>Greek,</hi> and have it thus, <hi>Vicariis Epiſcoporum, quos,</hi> Graeci Chorepiſcopos <hi>vocant, non licere Presbyteros vel Diaconos Ordinare, ſed nec Presbyteris Civitatis, ſine Epiſcopi Praecepto, am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plius aliquid Imperare, vel ſine Autoritate Literarum ejus in unaquaque parochia aliquid agere:</hi> Whereby, contrary to all Rule, by Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, Mutilation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they impoſe a Senſe directly contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicting the expreſs Words of the Canon; which is done in ſo groſs a manner, that <hi>Thorndike</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was compell'd to acknowledge,<note place="margin">Right of the Church, <hi>pag. 141, 142.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>That for his part he doth not believe that we have the true Reading of this Canon in any Copy that he hath heard of or ſeen.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But why is <hi>Thorndike,</hi> who is followed by Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Parker,</hi> all differing from Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Old E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopal Divines, ſo concern'd to oppoſe the Univerſally Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:56457:40"/>Copies of <hi>Zonaras</hi> and <hi>Balſamon,</hi> but becauſe, do they what they can, it may be eaſily inferr'd, that before the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Ancyra,</hi> the <hi>Chorepiſcopi</hi> did ordain Presbyters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that afterwards they might do it in <hi>their own Pariſhes without leave;</hi> in other Pariſhes with leave, or at leaſt in their own Pariſhes with leave. Thus much is the Import of <hi>Zonara</hi>'s <hi>Balſamon</hi>'s, and the <hi>Oxford</hi> Copies, one of which muſt be receiv'd, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding any thing hitherto oppos'd unto 'em. The whole that <hi>Thorndike</hi> hath laid in againſt us, narrowly look'd into, comes to nothing.</p>
                     <p>The Reaſons why our Copy is to be ſuſpected, ſaith he, are theſe.</p>
                     <q>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. In an <hi>Arabick</hi> Paraphraſe now extant in the <hi>Oxford</hi> Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brary, there is nothing to be found of that Clauſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap>.</item>
                           <item>2. <hi>Iſidore Mercator</hi>'s Tranſlation, which ſeems to be that which was anciently received in the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Churches, before <hi>Dionyſius Exiguus,</hi> wherewith that Copy agreed which <hi>Herve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> tranſlated, as alſo <hi>Fulgentius</hi> his <hi>Breviate,</hi> which Pope <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian</hi> the firſt followed, hath only this, <hi>Vicariis Epiſcoporum, quos Graeci Chorepiſcopos vocant,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ut ſupra.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>3. Can the Reading of the laſt words, <gap reason="foreign">
                                 <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                              </gap> ſeem probable, <hi>&amp;c. ut ſupra.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>4. Seeing this is that which is afterwards provided for, by the Council of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> Cap. LVI. in the ſame Subject, it ſeems very probable, that this ſhould be the proviſion which the Council of <hi>Ancyra</hi> intended, as all <hi>Ignatius</hi> his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles, and other Canons <hi>Apoſt.</hi> XL. <hi>Arelat.</hi> XIX. expreſs it.</item>
                        </list>
                     </q>
                     <p>To all which I reply,</p>
                     <p n="10">1. The <hi>Greek</hi> Copy compared with Tranſlations, having the Reputation of an Original, is not to be neglected, though in the <hi>Arabick Paraphraſe</hi> the Clauſe about City Presbyters is omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; for it might be either negligently or willingly done: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, if this Clauſe had never been in the Original, there ſtill remains enough to carry our Point in that, as we ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after prove the <hi>Chorepiſcopi</hi> were but Presbyters, and yet by the other parts of this Canon had power to ordain both <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> and <hi>Deacons,</hi> at leaſt with the permiſſion of the City-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop.</p>
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:56457:41"/>
                     <p>To the Second, touching <hi>Iſidore</hi>'s Tranſlation, which differs from <hi>Hervetus</hi>'s and <hi>Dionyſius Exiguus</hi>'s, as well as from eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Greek</hi> Copy, cannot be of ſtrength enough to invalidate an Original, any more than the Vulgar, or any other Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Bible, can blaſt the Reputation of the Originals either of the Old or New Teſtament.</p>
                     <p>What hath been already urged about <hi>de Marca</hi>'s diſguſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, and <hi>Thorndike</hi>'s quarrel with <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, is a ſufficient Anſwer to his <hi>Third</hi> Argument: For if the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non hath any meaning, be it <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, or be there an Omiſſion of this Expreſſion, it cannot but be granted, that before this Council the <hi>Chorepiſcopi</hi> did Ordain Presbyters and Deacons without the City-Biſhop's leave, and afterwards with it.</p>
                     <p>To the Fourth, that the Council of <hi>Laodicea</hi> did many Years after this make the ſame Proviſion, hath nothing of Argument in it to prove, That the Council of <hi>Ancyra</hi> did ſo, long before <hi>Laodicea</hi>'s doing It now, ſeeing it's not by way of confirmation of an anteceding Decree, is a ſufficient intimation, that <hi>Ancy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> did it not.</p>
                     <p>However, ſeeing <hi>Thorndike</hi> will provoke us to conſult this 56th, or rather 57th Canon of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> to it we will go; which on a diligent ſearch we find to run thus: <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, [<gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>] ſay ſome, [<gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>] ſay others, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Hervetus</hi> renders it thus, <hi>Quod non oportet in vicis &amp; pagis</hi> Epiſcopos conſtitui, ſed Periodeu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas; hoc eſt, Circumcurſentores. <hi>Dionyſius Exiguus,</hi> Quod <hi>non oporteat in Villulis vel in Agris Epiſcopos conſtitui, ſed Viſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. Iſidore Mercator</hi> thus, <hi>Non oportet in Villis &amp; vicis Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos Ordinari, ſed Viſitatores;</hi> (i. e.) <hi>qui Circumeant, Conſtitui:</hi> No Biſhops ought to be appointed in the Countrey Towns or Villages, but Viſitors. Neither of theſe take notice of the Various Reading: for it may be [<gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>] as well as [<gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>], and ſo be thus tranſlated: <hi>For the future there ſhall not be Ordained in Countrey Places any Biſhops or Periodeutae,</hi> or <hi>Viſitors,</hi> making the <hi>Periodeutae</hi> and Countrey Biſhops the ſame; as <hi>De Marca,</hi> though he obſerves not this various Reading does, <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanter aſſerere audeo eundem eſſe Chorepiſcopum,</hi> &amp; <hi>Periodeutum;</hi> and as the ſame <hi>De Marca</hi> further obſerves, theſe <hi>Periodeutae</hi>
                        <pb n="73" facs="tcp:56457:41"/>were only Presbyters, as in the 4th <hi>Action</hi> of the Council of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> mention is made of <hi>Alexander, Presbyter,</hi> and <hi>Perio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuta,</hi> and in the 11th <hi>Action</hi> of <hi>Valentine, Presbyter,</hi> and <hi>Perio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuta;</hi> whence I infer, that it's clear from this and the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing parts of the Canon, that till this Council, Presbyters were not ſo very much under the Power of the Biſhops, but could act according to their own diſcretion, without conſulting the City-Biſhops. The Canon is, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, and thus rendred by <hi>Hervetus, Eos autem qui prius conſtituti fuerunt, nihil agere ſine mente Epiſcopi, qui eſt in Civitate,</hi> clearly enough inſinuating, that until this Council the <hi>Chorepiſcopi,</hi> the <hi>Periodeutae,</hi> who were but Presbyters, did act in the Country as they judged meet, without conſulting the Biſhop of the City; and it's well known, that their work was to Ordain Presbyters, Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thus much may ſuffice to vindicate what we have drawn from the Council of <hi>Ancyra</hi> to eſtabliſh the Power of the <hi>Chore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopi,</hi> who agreeably enough to the 13th <hi>Canon</hi> of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, might exerciſe Epiſcopal Juriſdiction in their own Precinct, without the leave of the City-Biſhop, and with his Permiſſion they might do ſo out of their own Charge, even in the City.</p>
                     <p>To proceed, it's very clear that long after this time, yea, long after <hi>Damaſus,</hi> this Severity againſt the <hi>Chorepiſcopi,</hi> and <hi>Leo</hi> the Third's Attempt to ſuppreſs and baniſh them, when <hi>Charles</hi> the Great ſent <hi>Arno Invavenſis</hi> to know the mind of his Holineſs about them, they continued in the Exerciſe of their Office, governing the Country-Churches, ordaining Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And altho' <hi>Hincmarus,</hi> as <hi>Baluzius</hi> in <hi>de Marca</hi> out of <hi>Flodoardus</hi> his Hiſtory obſerves,<note place="margin">De Marca de Concord. lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>13, 14.</hi>
                        </note> wrote bitterly againſt thoſe City-Biſhops that had 'em in their Dioceſes,<note place="margin">Fbodoard. Hiſt. Remenf. lib. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>29.</hi>
                        </note> yet <hi>Rabanus Maurus</hi> pleads as warmly in their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,<note place="margin">In Hiſtor. Lanſiaca apud Palladium, c 106. Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Elpidium Monachum Presbyterum ordinatum à Timotheo Chorepiſcopo. Chorepiſcopos in Eccleſiis vacantibus innuit Hugo Flaviniac. an. 776. &amp; Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carius in Hiſt. Epiſcop. Verdanenſium, n. 13. Poſt hunc, Epiſcopatus iſtius Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae per 12. annos va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuus extitit, ſed quidem ſervus Dei (Amalbertus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,) juxta morem illius temporis Chorepiſcopus factus ipſam regebat Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam. <hi>For all theſe ſee</hi> Du Freſne's <hi>Gloſſary,</hi> ver. Chorepiſcopus.</note> and they were continued in <hi>France</hi> and elſewhere. <hi>Elpidrus</hi> a Monk, was or dained Presbyter by <hi>Timothy</hi> a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Biſhop: <hi>Amalbertus,</hi> a <hi>Chorepiſcopus,</hi>
                        <pb n="74" facs="tcp:56457:42"/>governed the Church of <hi>Verdun</hi> during a Vacancy of twelve years, conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Churches, confirm'd Children, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as may be ſeen in <hi>Rudolphus</hi> his Life of <hi>Rabanus Maurus,</hi> and in <hi>De Marca.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>That the <hi>Chorepiſcopi</hi> did exerciſe the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Power, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho' they were but Presbyters, may plainly be ſeen in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees that were againſt 'em, interdicting their preſuming ſo to do for time to come. 'Twas this that fill'd the Soul of <hi>Damaſus</hi> 1.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Vid. Epiſt.</hi> 5. <hi>Damaſi</hi> 1. Proſpero Numidiae primae ſedis Epiſcopo, Leoni, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parato, &amp;c.</note> with ſo much indignation againſt them, that they being but Presbyters, preſumed to diſcharge the Epiſcopal Office: And for this very reaſon it was, that <hi>Leo</hi> the Third, in Anſwer unto the Queſtion mov'd by <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Great,</hi> condemn'd them to Baniſhment, as may be ſeen in the ſelect Eccleſiaſtical <hi>Capitula</hi> of <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, where it's very clear, that tho' the French Prelates mitigated ſomewhat of the Rigour of the Pope's ſevere Decree againſt them, yet concurr'd ſo far with him, as to Ordain that the Country-Biſhops do no more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter on the Execution of the Epiſcopal Office, <hi>ita ut <hi>amplius</hi> nihil de <hi>Cpiſcopali</hi> miniſterio praeſumerent;</hi> and they decreed, That no Country-Biſhop preſume, by Impoſition of Hands, to give the Holy Ghoſt to any, or Conſecrate any Prieſt, Levite, or Subdeacon. And tho' theſe <hi>Capitula</hi> do null and make void all the Ordinations and Conſecrations of the <hi>Chorepiſcopi, Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas</hi> the Firſt doth ratifie and confirm them,<note place="margin">Vide. Epiſt. <hi>15.</hi> Nichol. <hi>1.</hi> Tit. <hi>1.</hi>
                        </note> as may be ſeen in his Epiſtle to <hi>Radolfus,</hi> and thus he did for the very Reaſon, the <hi>Capitula</hi> as well as <hi>Leo</hi> and <hi>Damaſus,</hi> did damn them. <hi>Damaſus</hi> ſays, that <hi>they are the ſame with</hi> Presbyters, <hi>becauſe they are inſtituted according to the Form of the Seventy Diſciples,</hi> who were never veſted with <hi>Jura Epiſcopalia,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Tit. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
                        </note> ſo <hi>Leo</hi> and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect <hi>Capitula</hi> of <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, the <hi>Chorepi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopi
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:56457:42"/>are not Chief Prieſts, nor Biſhops, neither do any of the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopal Rights belong unto them, ſeeing they were inſtituted according to the Form of the Seventy;</hi> for which cauſe let no one ſay,<note place="margin">Et ne alicui talis Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natio, vel Confirmatio, aut Conſecratio <hi>Reiteratio</hi> eſſe videatur.</note> 
                        <hi>That when any of thoſe who have been Ordained by the</hi> Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repiſcopi, <hi>are afterwards Ordained by the City-Biſhop, that they were Re-ordained, but let 'em attend that Saying,</hi> Quod non oſtenditur geſtum, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio non ſinit, ut videntur iteratum. And Pope <hi>Nicholas</hi> 1. gives this as a Reaſon, why he judges their Ordination <hi>valid. The</hi> Chorepiſcopi <hi>were ſuch as the Seventy, ſent out by our Lord Jeſus, who without doubt were veſted with the Epiſcopal Power.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But tho' theſe Papal Determinations are different, yet they agree in witneſſing to this Truth, That the <hi>Chorepiſcopi</hi> exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis'd Epiſcopal Authority. <hi>De Marca</hi> proves the ſame out of the <hi>Arabian</hi> Canons, tranſlated by <hi>Alfonſus Piſanus,</hi> and from the laſt words of the Canon of <hi>Antioch.</hi> Dr. <hi>Parker</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf makes no doubt of it; for (ſays he) <hi>That theſe</hi> Chorepiſcopi <hi>had the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of Proper Biſhops,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Parker</hi>'s Account, <hi>p.</hi> 154.</note> 
                        <hi>appears plainly from the tenth Canon of</hi> Antioch, <hi>that allows them to Ordain the inferiour Officers of the Church.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This of Biſhop <hi>Parker</hi> doth exactly agree with the 55. <hi>Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of <hi>Nice,</hi> as tranſlated out of <hi>Arabick</hi> by <hi>Turrianus</hi> the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit. <hi>When the</hi> Chorepiſcopus <hi>viſits the Churches and Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries under his Power, let him gather together the Elders of Caſtles, and expound unto 'em the Holy Scriptures, and enquire whether they have any Sons or Daughters, and give order that they be brought unto him, that he may ſign 'em,</hi> pray over them, impoſe Hands on 'em, bleſs and <hi>inſtitute Miniſters,</hi> that is, ſay the Notes on this Chapter, <hi>Lectores, Exorciſtae,</hi> &amp; <hi>Hypodiaconi.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And that theſe <hi>Chorepiſcopi</hi> were but of the ſame Order with Presbyters, and were no otherwiſe Biſhops than as all other Presbyters are, is as clear; for their Ordination was by one Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop only, not by three, and when they entred on the Exerciſe of the Epiſcopal Power, they had no new Conſecration, as may be ſeen in the 54. <hi>Chapter</hi> of <hi>Nice,</hi> tranſlated out of the <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bick,</hi> where <hi>Turrianus</hi> renders it thus: <hi>Et debet Epiſcopus</hi> [vid.
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:56457:43"/>Civitatis] <hi>recitare ſuper electum</hi> [ſcil. Chorepiſcopum] <hi>Orationem conſuetam,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Chorepiſcopus non ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabatur, ſed per oratic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem benedicebatur.</note> 
                        <hi>&amp; Benedicere illi, dare<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> illi nomina om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium Eccleſiarum &amp; Monaſteriorum qua ſub Poteſtate ejus ſunt.</hi> The Notes on this Chapter have it, that they were not conſecrated anew to the Office of a Country-Biſhop, but only by the Prayer of the City-Biſhop bleſſed. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſus</hi> 1. expreſly affirms them to be but Presbyters, in theſe words; <hi>Quod ipſi iidem ſunt qui &amp; Presbyteri, ſufficienter inveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, quia ad formam &amp; exemplum ſeptuaginta inveniuntur prius in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituti.</hi> The ſelect <hi>Capitula</hi> of <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Great</hi> concurring with <hi>Leo</hi> the Third,<note place="margin">Tit. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
                        </note> and ſpeaking of the Epiſcopal Rights, ſay the ſame; <hi>Haec verò non à Presbyteris vel Chorepiſcopis, qui ambo unius formae eſſe videntur.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Beſides, ſuch were ſome of the Ancient Canons<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> decreeing that there ſhould be but one Biſhop in a Dioceſs; and he only in the City, that made it neceſſary for ſome of thoſe who an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently would have the Biſhops to be of an Order ſuperiour above Presbyters to hold that theſe <hi>Chorepiſcopi,</hi> tho' they had the name of Biſhop given 'em, and were veſted with the <hi>Jura Epiſcopalia,</hi> were but Presbyters uſurping on the Epiſcopal Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; ſo <hi>Damaſus, Leo,</hi> and many French Biſhops in <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Great</hi>'s days; and it hath alſo put ſome later Writers, ſuch as <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine, Boverius</hi> in his <hi>Paraenetic Cenſure</hi> of <hi>de Dominis, Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of Spalato</hi>'s Book <hi>de Rep. Eccleſ.</hi> and <hi>De Marco</hi> to phanſie, that ſome, made <hi>Chorepiſcopi,</hi> were formerly Conſecrated to the Epiſcopal Dignity, and that others were but Presbyters; and thus by diſtinguiſhing the <hi>Office</hi> from the <hi>Perſon,</hi> they hoped to extricate themſelves; but as Dr. <hi>Parker</hi> well obſerves,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pag.</hi> 158.</note> 
                        <hi>This is precariouſly ſaid without any ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of Pretence for it, but meerly to ſalve his own Hypotheſis.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Others,<note place="margin">Thorndike <hi>of Rights of Church.</hi> p. 146.</note> ſuch as <hi>Thorndike,</hi> are driven to the Invention of another Diſtinction, <q>which is between the <hi>Solemnity</hi> which an <hi>Act is execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with,</hi> and the <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> by which it is done And that it cannot be prejudicial to any Power to do that by another, which ſeemeth not fit to be immediately and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:56457:43"/>perſonally executed by it. Some Acts of the Primitive Church ſeem to require this Diſtinction; as the making of Presbyters by the <hi>Chorepiſcopi,</hi> or Countrey-Biſhops, menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in the ancient <hi>Greek</hi> Canons. Which by <hi>all likelihood were not properly Biſhops,</hi> becauſe not Heads of a City-Church, which is the Apoſtolical Rule for Epiſcopal Churches.</q> Thus <hi>Thorndike,</hi> who differs greatly from the generality of his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, who hold, that though the <hi>Poteſtas Juriſdictionis</hi> may be delegated to one that is not a Biſhop, yet the <hi>Poteſtas Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis</hi> cannot. However, it muſt be acknowledged, that there is a great difference between a Presbyter's Ordaining other Presbyters with the leave of the Biſhop, and his doing it by a <hi>Power derived from the Biſhop.</hi> One veſted with a Power, may not be able to exerciſe it without the leave of another; and yet when he hath leave, he then exerciſes a Power inherent in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>virtute officii.</hi> The Biſhops themſelves cannot exerciſe the Power of Orders without the leave of the Supreme Civil Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate; and now that they do exerciſe it, 'tis <hi>with his leave;</hi> but it does not therefore follow, that the <hi>Power of Orders</hi> is derived from the Supreme Magiſtrate to the Biſhop.</p>
                     <p>In the Council of <hi>Ancyra</hi> it's not ſaid, That the Presbyter ſhall not Ordain Presbyters, unleſs the Biſhop delegates unto him a Power enabling him ſo to do; but he ſhall not exerciſe this Power without the conſent of the Biſhop, which was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned by the Canon, to prevent Schiſms and Diviſions in the Church: So that I cannot ſee how this Diſtinction of <hi>Thorndike,</hi> ſo applauded by Dr. <hi>Parker,</hi> can help 'em.</p>
                     <p>To preſs this yet further, <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth's Suffragans were conſecrated Biſhops, and had the ſame Power <hi>virtute officii,</hi> that any other Biſhop receiv'd at his Conſecration, but may not exerciſe it unleſs by Commiſſion from the City-Biſhop. But when they did exerciſe the Epiſcopal Authority, was it by a Power receiv'd at their Conſecration, and inherent in them, or by a Power deriv'd unto 'em from the City-Biſhop by Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? 'Twas by the former, no doubt; why elſe were they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated? If then this Commiſſion given by the City-Biſhop to the Suffragan, limiting the Exerciſe of his Power, doth not infer, that the Suffragan did not act by a Derived Power, much leſs can theſe Words, <hi>[Let not the Chorepiſcopus Ordain Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:56457:44"/>or Deacons without the conſent of the City-Biſhop]</hi> imply, that the <hi>Chorepiſcopus</hi> deriv'd the Power of Ordaining from the City-Biſhop. The Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln</hi> can't Ordain Prieſts or Deacons in <hi>Weſtminſter-Abby</hi> without the leave of the Dean of <hi>Weſtm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nſter;</hi> and yet when the Biſhop does Ordain any there with the Dean's leave, it's not, I preſume, by any Power de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd from the Dean that he does it, but by a Power inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in himſelf; and the Words <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> import no other leave than this.</p>
                     <p>If then theſe <hi>Chorepiſcopi</hi> be conform'd to the Number of Rural Deanries, and the Rural Deans allowed to exerciſe the ſame Power the <hi>Chorepiſcopi</hi> did in the ancient Church, 'twill afford great Relief to the Conſciences of many Worthy Proteſtant Diſſenting Miniſters, without expoſing the Church of <hi>England</hi> to the Reproach of Novelty. To return to the Archbiſhop's <hi>Reduction,</hi> which continues the Second Propoſition thus.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Archbiſhop.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <q>To this <hi>Synod</hi> the Rector and Church-Wardens might preſent ſuch impenitent perſons as by Admonitions and <hi>Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion</hi> from the <hi>Sacrament</hi> would not be reformed, who if they ſhould ſtill remain contumacious and incorrigible, the Sentence of <hi>Excommunication</hi> might be decreed againſt them by the <hi>Synod,</hi> and accordingly be executed in the Pariſh where they lived. Hitherto alſo all things that concerned the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochial Miniſters</hi> might be referred, whether they did touch their <hi>Doctrine</hi> or their <hi>Converſation,</hi> as alſo the Cenſure of all <hi>New Opinions, Hereſies</hi> and <hi>Schiſms</hi> which did ariſe within that Circuit, with liberty of Appeal, if need ſo require, unto the <hi>Dioceſan</hi> Synod.</q>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="notes">
                     <head>Notes.</head>
                     <p>It is not to be doubted, but that as ſoon as the Church of <hi>England</hi> grants unto the Presbyter the Exerciſe of the <hi>Epiſcopal Rights,</hi> they will be content that the <hi>Rural Dean,</hi> or <hi>Chorepiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus</hi> hold his <hi>Synod</hi> of <hi>Pariſh-Paſtors</hi> or <hi>Rectors</hi> within the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cincts of the Rural Deanry, and exerciſe as much Power as is here deſired.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:56457:44"/>
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>
                     <q>The <hi>Dioceſan Synod</hi> might be held once or twice in the Year, as it ſhould be thought moſt convenient. Therein all the <hi>Suffragans</hi> [i. e. <hi>Chorepiſcopi,</hi>] and the reſt of the <hi>Rectors,</hi> or incumbent Paſtors (or a certain ſelect number of every <hi>Deanry</hi>) within the <hi>Dioceſs</hi> might meet, with whoſe Conſent, or the <hi>major</hi> part of them, all things might be concluded by the <hi>Biſhop</hi> or <hi>Superintendent,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>(i. e.)</hi> Superintendentes, unde &amp; nomen Epiſcopi tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum eſt. <hi>Hieron. Epiſt.</hi> 85. <hi>ad Evagrium.</hi>
                        </note> (call him whether you will) or in his abſence by one of the <hi>Suffragans,</hi> whom he ſhall depute in his ſtead to be <hi>Moderator</hi> of that Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>Here all matters of greater moment might be taken into conſideration, and the Orders of the monthly Synods <hi>reviſed</hi> and (if need be) <hi>reformed:</hi> And if here alſo any matter of Difficulty could not receive a full Determination, it might be referred to the next <hi>Provincial</hi> or <hi>National</hi> Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod.</q>
                  </p>
                  <div type="notes">
                     <head>Notes.</head>
                     <p>Dr. <hi>Poynet,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> pleads for the Word <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perintendent,</hi> as much better than that of <hi>Biſhop;</hi> and it is a word leſs offenſive to the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> than the other is; and perhaps becauſe the <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> found it ſo, he ſpeaks ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently of the Name; and to give Reputation to the word <hi>Superintendent,</hi> refers us unto St. <hi>Hierome:</hi> But it's to be hoped, that the wiſer of all Parties, when they have concerted the thing, will not quarrel about the Name, whether one or the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="part">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>
                     <q>The <hi>Provincial</hi> Synod might conſiſt of <hi>all the Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Suffragans,</hi> and ſuch other of the Clergy as ſhould be elected out of every <hi>Dioceſs</hi> within the <hi>Province;</hi> the <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> of every <hi>Province</hi> might be the <hi>Moderator</hi> of this Meeting, (or in his room, ſome one of the <hi>Biſhops</hi> appointed by him) and all Matters be ordered therein by common conſent, as in the former Aſſemblies.</q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:56457:45"/>
                  <p>
                     <q>This <hi>Synod</hi> might be held every Third Year; and if the Parliament do then ſit, (according to the Act of a <hi>Trien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial</hi> Parliament) both the <hi>Archbiſhops</hi> and <hi>Provincial</hi> Synods of the Land might joyn together, and make up a National Council: Wherein all <hi>Appeals</hi> from <hi>Inferior</hi> Synods might be received, all their <hi>Acts examined,</hi> and all Eccleſiaſtical Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions which concern the State of the whole Nation <hi>eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>This Scheme of Church-Government, drawn up by this Learned Primate, as it is admirably adjuſted to the ſeveral Tempers of Men of different Apprehenſions about ſome things in Church-Government, ſo it is not in the leaſt repugnant to any thing of Chriſt's Inſtitution; for there is not aſcrib'd unto any of the Synodical Conventions a proper Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on over any Parochial Church. That in Matters of greater moment, care be taken, that all things be done in every Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh by a general Conſent, Concord and Agreement, is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary; and to this end, that the Pariſh <hi>Rectors</hi> proceed not to Excommunication until they have conſulted the <hi>Dean Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi>'s Synod; and that what is done by theſe <hi>Synods</hi> be <hi>examined</hi> by Biſhops in a larger Aſſembly, and that by a larger again, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til we come to a National, if the caſe ſo require.</p>
                  <p>Though it be ſaid, Let the Sentence of Excommunication be decreed againſt the obſtinately Impenitent by the Synod, yet it may be underſtood thus, Let the <hi>Rector</hi> of the Pariſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult the Synod, and there come to a Reſolution and Determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation with the conſent of this Synod.</p>
                  <p>Whoever will conſult the Learned Writers of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> particularly Dr. <hi>Burnet,</hi> now Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> will ſee cauſe to conclude them to be againſt the Power and Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Councils:</hi> That they are rather for <hi>Concord</hi> than <hi>Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> That particular Churches, as to matters of Government, are independent on any Convention or Colledge of other Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops or Paſtors whatſoever; that to this very end of ſecuring the Power of the Dioceſan or City-Biſhop, the Dioceſan Church is made a ſingle Church, <hi>Infimae Speciei;</hi> and whatever Power, Authority or Juriſdiction belong unto a particular Church of the loweſt Rank, they are affirmed to belong to the Dioceſan Church; which Dr. <hi>Barrow</hi> hath endeavoured to prove to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent:
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:56457:45"/>So that let the bounds of particular Churches be made Parochial, or of no larger extent than a Pariſh-Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, and the Pariſh-Miniſter be entruſted with Paſtoral Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, to be exerciſed as above-mentioned, 'twill of courſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that what is now ſaid to belong to a Dioceſan, muſt be ſeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the <hi>Pariſh-Church.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There is not ſo much a Controverſie between the Powers, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminences and Priviledges of a particular Church, as about its Bounds and Limits. Reduce the Bounds of a particular Church to thoſe of a Pariſh, and the Debate will be at an end as to this point.</p>
                  <p>That the Primate by <hi>Chorepiſcopi</hi> means Presbyters veſted with the Epiſcopal Rights, is manifeſt from what he and Dr. <hi>Holdſworth</hi> in the end of the Reduction thus aſſert:</p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="approbation">
                     <body>
                        <p>
                           <hi>We are of the Judgment, That the Form of Government here propoſed, is not in any Point repugnant to the Scripture; and that the</hi> Suffragans <hi>mention'd in the Second Propoſition, may lawfully uſe the Power both of</hi> Juriſdiction <hi>and</hi> Ordination, <hi>according to the Word of God, and the Practice of the Ancient Church.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Ja. Armachanus. Rich. Holdſworth.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:56457:46"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> The <hi>Reaſonableneſs</hi> of the Church of <hi>England</hi>'s condeſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to eſtabliſh the Government propoſed by Archbiſhop <hi>Uſher</hi> in this Reduction.</head>
               <p>IF then the Government of the Church of <hi>England</hi> be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to be the ſame held by the Firſt Reformers, and by the Renowned Archbiſhop <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> any Law or Statute to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary notwithſtanding.</p>
               <p>And the <hi>Subſcription</hi> of Submiſſion be only unto the Church-Government, as fram'd accordingly, there are many powerful Preachers (if not moſt of the Sober Godly) amongſt the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters will chearfully enter into Pariſh-Churches, and be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitated to exerciſe their Miniſtry in Publick, whom the Multitude otherwiſe will never hear, nor be benefited by their Talents.</p>
               <p>The Allowance of this can do no hurt to the Biſhops, unleſs the eaſing 'em of an intollerable burthen, or diſcharging 'em of ſuch Duties now incumbent on them, as are impoſſible to be performed by any.</p>
               <p>Beſides, that hereby ſhall all the pious and conſcientious Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh-Miniſters be put upon the attending thoſe Paſtoral Duties which are enjoyned them by the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, in order to the right Guidance and Edification of the particular Churches committed to their Cure.</p>
               <p>And as hereby the Church of <hi>England</hi> will be enlarged and ſtrengthned by the Acceſſion of many Proteſtant Diſſenters, great eaſe given the Biſhops, without the leaſt Diminution of their Temporal Emoluments and Honours; all Pariſh-Paſtors allowed the Exerciſe of their Functions, as the Lord Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them. In like manner hereby,</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Honour due to the <hi>Firſt Reformers,</hi> that with their Blood, or other grievous Sufferings, ſealed to the Truth of the Reformation, ſhall be maintained and <hi>reſtored.</hi> I muſt ſay re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored, becauſe the altering our Epiſcopal Government, and
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:56457:46"/>ſhaping it to the meaſure of the <hi>Canons</hi> of 1603, and ſince to the Act of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> in <hi>Charles</hi> the Second's Reign, hath made it ſo much another thing than what they held and defended, that we cannot entitle them to be the Aſſertors of it without Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, or a Vindication. The Epiſcopacy they were for, I ſay, was but of the ſame Allay with the excellent Moderation of Archbiſhop <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. This Primitive Government Reſtored, doth not in the leaſt interfere, or claſh with, but moſt effectually ſupport the <hi>Ancient Regal</hi> Power in matters Eccleſiaſtical. But the Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Epiſcopacy advanc'd by <hi>Laud,</hi> and in its Heighths of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Right, eſtabliſh'd by <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, will on Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation be found to be held by ſome of the Clergy, as unalte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, to the great Diminution of the King's Eccleſiaſtical Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, and the Power of Parliaments.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This Government <hi>Reſtored,</hi> will give Countenance to the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Reformed Churches abroad, as well as to the Churches of Diſſenters at home, owning their Miniſtry and Sacraments, and holding Communion with them, as with true Goſpel Churches of Chriſt: Whereas the Epiſcopacy <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreſtored,</hi> (our Nobles and Gentry of both Houſes, having not been aware of it) does null their Church-State, deſtroying both their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry and Sacraments; and as that very Learned, but herein more dangerous man, Mr. <hi>Dodwell,</hi> will have it, puts 'em out of the common way of Salvation, and into the ſame deplora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Condition with the <hi>Heathen.</hi> They muſt be ſaved by an uncommon Prerogative, or not at all.</p>
               <p>I the rather inſiſt on this Particular, becauſe, ſince his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Majeſty, the glorious Inſtrument of our Deliverance, hath been brought up, and continues in the Communion of theſe Foreign Reformed Churches, we lye under a ſpecial Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian of our declaring, that we hold Communion with them: And will it not be a ſurpriſing Conſideration, (if there be any who have not yet reflected on it) that our Church owns the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and at the ſame time diſowns the Miniſtry of the Reformed Churches, even of the Churches of which His Majeſty is now a Member?</p>
               <p n="4">4. This Government Reſtored will remove out of the way of thoſe Diſſenters who cannot do all that is neceſſary to their
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:56457:47"/>obtaining the Advantages of this Comprehenſion, the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Blocks, which hinder their holding Communion with the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Reaſon why theſe Diſſenters cannot joyn with the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh-Aſſemblies in the Eſtabliſhed Worſhip, ſo far as I can gueſs, is not the bare uſe of a Liturgy, nor the neglect of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, nor becauſe there are ſome diſorderly Members of their Communion, but becauſe the Specifick Nature of Chriſt's In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted Churches are deſtroyed; the Pariſh-Miniſters, who were Goſpel-Paſtors, depoſed, and Church-Government made impracticable, by the erecting Dioceſan Churches, one of which, compos'd of many Pariſhes, under the Government of one on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Paſtor, call'd the Dioceſan Biſhop, is made a particular Church of the loweſt Rank, and ſubſtituting in the room of Pariſh-Paſtors a New Order of <hi>Sub-half-Presbyters,</hi> affirming all that have been baptiz'd and live within the Terriers or Boundaries of the Dioceſs, how ignorant or ſcandalous ſoever, to be ſit Matter for an Inſtituted Church of Chriſt; and becauſe of their ſetting up Forms of Prayer in oppoſition unto, and ſuppreſſion of Spiritual and Free Prayer; the Corruptions in the Liturgy; and impoſing, as Terms of Communion, ſuch Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies as are, in their Conſciences, ſinful.</p>
               <p>If therefore the deſired Church-Government be ſettled, the Pariſh-Churches will be eſtabliſhed as particular Churches of Chriſt's Inſtitution, their Paſtors Reſtored, Government made practicable, Diſorders amended; and tho ſome things remain in the Pariſhes which theſe men can't conform unto, yet they will own the Pariſhes thus Conſtituted and Reformed, for true Churches, and admit their Members, if deſired, unto Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with them.</p>
               <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notice">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>PLain Dealing: Being a Moderate general Review of the <hi>Scots</hi> Prelatical Clergies Proceedings in the latter Reigns. With a Vindication of the preſent Proceedings in Church-Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs there. Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> near <hi>Mercers-Chappel.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:56457:47"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
